<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC106">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>106</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. P</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>379</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Documents Relating to the University of Cambridge</head>
                <head type="James">Documents Relating to the University of Cambridge</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper (and vellum)</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">

                        <height unit="mm">305</height>


                        <width unit="mm">210</width>

                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">12 x 8.25, and other sizes</measureGrp>, <extent>pp. 690
                        numbered</extent>. Cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">On the flyleaf <supplied>(p. <locus>1</locus>)</supplied>
                    <handNote>in Roman hand</handNote>:<lb/>
                    <q>Who due wilbe a register<lb/> Shuld holde his penne in truthe entyere.<lb/> Ensearch he ought
                        recordys of olde,<lb/> The doute to trye, the right to holde.<lb/> The lawes to knowe he must
                        contende,<lb/> Olde customes eke he shoulde expende.<lb/> No paynes to wryte he may refuse,<lb/>
                        His office ellys he doth abuse.</q><lb/> There is a short table of contents <supplied>on p.
                            <locus>5</locus></supplied>
                    <handNote>in <name type="author">Parker</name>'s hand</handNote>, occupying one leaf.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>pp. 1-84 (85-88 missing) + 89-90 + 90a-d + 91-4, 94a-f, 95-98, 98a-b, 99-108 + 108a-b +
                        109-170 + 170a-b + 171-80 (181-184 missing) + 185-202 + 202a-b + 203-204 + 204a-b + 205-206 +
                        206a-b + 207-250 (251-2 missing) + 253-300 + 300a-d + 301-328 + 328a-b + 329-330 + 330a-d +
                        331-348 (349-350 missing) + 351-358 + 358a-f + 359-364 + 364a-b + 365-378 + 378a-b + 379-380 +
                        380a-d + 381-402 + 402aa-az + 402 ba-bb + 403-406 (407-410 missing) + 411-419 + 420a-c + 421-422
                        + 422b-c + 423-490 + 490a-f + 491-492 + 492a-d + 493a-h + 494 + 495a-j + 496-99 + 499a-b +
                        500-512 + 512a-f + 513-29 (530-533 missing) + 534-540 (541-542 missing) + 534-545 + 545a-b + 546
                        + 546a-b + 547-555 + 555a + 556 + 556a + 557-564 + 564a-d + 565-568 (569-572 missing) + 573-590
                        (591-594 missing) + 595-603 + 603a-p + 604-610 (611-612 missing) + 613-614 + 614a-b + 615-24 +
                        624aa-ci + 625-31 + 631a-b + 632 + 632a-d (flap) + 633-638 + 638a-d + 639-78 + 678a-d + 679-687
                        (688 missing) + 689-691</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="eng" otherLangs="lat">English and Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="7" locusEnd="11">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Papal bulls concerning the privileges of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Bullae papales de privilegiis academies</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>A Record of <date>1419</date>, reciting Bulls of <name type="person">John XXII</name>, <name
                                type="person">Boniface IX</name>, <name type="person">Honorius</name> and <name
                                type="person">Sergius</name></ab>
                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Dyer 1824a">Dyer, <hi rend="italic">Privileges</hi> I 58</ref>
                            etc.</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="12" locusEnd="13">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Writ of <name type="author">Richard II</name> to the vice-chancellor of the <name
                                    type="place">University of Cambridge</name> to secure <name type="person">Henry de
                                    Attlefield</name> to appear to answer <name type="place">Corpus Christi
                                    College</name> on a plea of trespass</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Breve regis <name type="person">Ricardi II</name>, vice-comiti Cantab. directum ut
                                distringat et corpora habeat <name type="person">Henrici de Attelfield</name> et
                                aliorum, ad respond, magistro et scholaribus C. C. C. C. de placito quodam quod vi et
                                armis, etc. <date>anno regni 7<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr></date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Cooper 1842">Cooper, <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> I
                            120</ref></ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>13</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="14" locusEnd="26">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The building of the <name type="place">church of Blessed Mary</name> in <name
                                    type="place">Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De structura <name type="place">ecclesiae B. Mariae Cantab.</name> inchoat.
                                    <date>1478</date>, perfect. <date>1519</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, p. 7</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>16</locus>-<locus>26</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="27" locusEnd="42">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The composition between the university and the town <date>1501</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, p. 1. Abstract in English</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="43" locusEnd="44">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Contents of the black-book of the university made by <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Bucknam</name> master of <name type="place">Gonvill-hall</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="45" locusEnd="47">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Contents of the black paper book of the university made by <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="48" locusEnd="48">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Contents of the black paper book of the proctors accounts begun by <name
                                    type="person">Dr. Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="49" locusEnd="49">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Certain memoranda in the auditors' common chest</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Quae memoranda sunt auditoribus cistae communis</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="50" locusEnd="50">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Receipts to be returned to the pro-chancellor elect by his predecessor</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Quae deposita reddenda pro-cancellario electo ab antecessore suo per syngrapham
                                serratam</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="51" locusEnd="58">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Account of the proctors, <date>1545</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Computus procuratorum <date>1545</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>It was in this year, <date>1545</date>, that <name type="person">Parker</name> procured a
                            new account-book. Grace-Book B (ed. <ref type="bibl" target="Bateson 1905">Bateson</ref>)
                            contains the previous accounts</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="59" locusEnd="60">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Alban Langdale</name>, <title>Account of the tenements conveyed to the
                                    <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> by <name type="person">Master
                                    Thomas Bar</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Computus <name type="person">Albani Langdail</name> de tenementis collatis
                                universitati per <name type="person">Mag. Thomam Baro</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="61" locusEnd="61">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>List of debts of the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> not yet
                                repaid</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Debita universitati necdum soluta</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="61" locusEnd="61">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Note concerning a controversy about the proctorship</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="62" locusEnd="62">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Decree of <name type="person">Stephen Gardiner</name> and <name type="person">Thomas
                                    Thirlby</name> on the controversy about the proctorship</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Decretum <name type="person">Stephani Gardiner episcopi Winton</name> et ... <name
                                    type="person">Thirleby episcopi Westmon.</name> de hac controversia</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">Cf. <ref type="ms" target="CCC127">MS 127.
                                6</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="63" locusEnd="63">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Exoneration of the proctors upon departure from office (<date>1521</date>)</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Exoneratio procuratorum ab officio discedentium <date>1521</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="16" locusStart="63" locusEnd="63">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Note annotated by <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name>, <q>Hoc anno in festo
                                    nativitatis B. Mariae M. P. accessit Cantabrigiam</q></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Manu <name type="person">Matthei Parker</name> annotatur, <q>Hoc anno in festo
                                    nativitatis B. Mariae M. P. accessit Cantabrigiam</q></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="17" locusStart="64" locusEnd="65">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Account of <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name>, vice-chancellor of the <name
                                    type="place">University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Computus <name type="person">Matthei Parker</name> vice-cancellarii <date>37 Hen.
                                    VIII</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="18" locusStart="66" locusEnd="66">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Account of the expenses incurred by <name type="person">Maydew</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Ainsworth</name> during the confirmation of the privileges of the
                                    <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Computus <name type="person">D. Maydew</name> et <name type="person">Mag.
                                    Aynsworth</name> pro expensis circa confirmationem privilegiorum academiae</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, p. 100</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="19" locusStart="67" locusEnd="70">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Expenses of <name type="person">Dr. Maydew</name> and <name type="person">Mr.
                                    Aynsworth</name>, <date>1 Edw. VI</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Expences of <name type="person">Dr. Maydew</name> and <name type="person">Mr.
                                    Aynsworth</name> in the university his suit for the confirmation of antient
                                charters, etc. <date>1 Edw. VI</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, p. 97</ab>
                        <ab>Apparently pp. <locus>51</locus>-<locus>71</locus> are from a single book</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="20" locusStart="71" locusEnd="72">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Writings delivered to the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> by <name
                                    type="person">Matthew Parker</name>, vice-chancellor, <date>1548</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Writings delivered to the university by <name type="person">M. Parker</name>,
                                vice-chancellor <date>1548</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>72</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="21" locusStart="73" locusEnd="90">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Extracts from royal charters, statutes, etc. concerning the taxers office</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="88" locusNew="84">On <supplied>this page</supplied> is pasted a slip with a list and
                            representation of Bakers' marks</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. 85-88 are missing</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="22" locusStart="90" locusEnd="90">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The powers of the vice-chancellor of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name> and of the mayor</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De potestate vice-cancellarii et majoris</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="23" locusStart="90a" locusEnd="90d">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Royal charter concerning the imprisonment of malefactors in the <name type="place"
                                    >castle of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta regia quod malefactores apud castrum imprisonari possunt</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="24" locusStart="91" locusEnd="91">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir James Dyer</name> to the vice-chancellor, with
                                his opinion in a case then depending in the vice-chancellor's court, dated <name
                                    type="place">London</name>
                                <date>Dec. 12, 1557</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="25" locusStart="91" locusEnd="91">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Carne</name> to the vice-chancellor
                                concerning a case in the vice-chancellor's court</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Carne</name> to the same on the same
                                subject</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="26" locusStart="92" locusEnd="93">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Charter of <name type="author">Richard II</name> confirming the privileges of the
                                    <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta <name type="person">Ricardi II</name>, confirmans antiquum privilegium
                                academics, ut cancellarius habeat cognitionem omnimodorum placitorum personalium,
                                    <date>anno regni 7<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr></date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Dyer 1824a">Dyer, <hi rend="italic">Privileges</hi> I 86</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="27" locusStart="94" locusEnd="94b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Complaints of the brewers against the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name>, <date>1550</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Complaints of the brewers against the university <date>1550</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="28" locusStart="94c" locusEnd="95">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Decisions of the University of Cambridge, a letter of <name type="author">Elizabeth
                                    I</name>, and a letter to the <name type="person">bishop of
                                Winchester</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statutum academiae 51, literae regiae, and letter to the bishop of Winchester, de
                                privilegiis academiae quod ad cancellauium pertinet cognitio omnimodorum placitorum
                                personalium</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>On <material>vellum</material></ab>
                        <ab locus="95">Receipt of <name type="person">Edmund Cousin</name> to <name type="person"
                                >Parker</name> for two brass measures, quart and pint of the wine measure, no date</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="29" locusStart="96" locusEnd="97">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Royal writ transferring the case of the mayor and bailiffs of <name type="place"
                                    >Cambridge</name> versus the <name type="place">University</name> to the
                                chancery</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Breve regis majori et ballivis Cantabrigiae directum, ut causa coram justiciariis
                                regis contra privilegia academiae inchoata ad curiam cancellarii referatur. <date>37
                                    Hen. VIII</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="30" locusStart="98" locusEnd="98b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Writs in the case of the mayor and bailiffs of <name type="place">Cambridge</name>
                                versus the <name type="place">University</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Breve vice-comitis Cantab, et breve regis de eadem causa</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>98a</locus> blank</supplied>

                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="31" locusStart="99" locusEnd="102">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Rules governing Stourbridge fair in <name type="place">Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The cry at Sturbridge-fair in the time of <name type="person">queen
                                Mary</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Cooper 1843">Cooper, <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> II
                            18</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="32" locusStart="103" locusEnd="104">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Fines levied at Stourbridge fair in <name type="place">Cambridge</name>,
                                    <date>1553</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Fines levied at Sturbridge-fair <date>1553</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>104</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="33" locusStart="105" locusEnd="105">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the privy council to the barons of the exchequer, <date>Nov. 20,
                                    1550</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the privy-council to the barons of the exchequer, directing them to stop
                                the proceedings in a case between the university and the pewterers company concerning
                                pewter seized at <name type="place">Sturbridge-fair</name>, dated <date>Nov. 20,
                                    1550</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="34" locusStart="106" locusEnd="108">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Record of the Exchequer on the proceedings between the <name type="place">University
                                    of Cambridge</name> and the pewterers company</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>E recordis curiae schaccarii de eadem causa <date>4 Edw. VI</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="35" locusStart="109" locusEnd="109">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Fines levied at Stourbridge fair <date>1555</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Fines levied at <name type="place">Sturbridge-fair</name>
                                <date>1555</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="36" locusStart="109" locusEnd="109">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Royal writ on the disturbance at Stourbridge fair</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Breve regis de causa predicta</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="37" locusStart="110" locusEnd="110">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the privy council to the pewterers company commanding them to drop their
                                suit versus the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name>, dated <name
                                    type="place">Westminster</name>
                                <date>Nov. 21, 1550</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the privy-council to the pewterers company commanding them to drop their
                                suit, dated <name type="place">Westm.</name>
                                <date>Nov. 21, 1550</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="38" locusStart="111" locusEnd="112">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr Buckmaster</name> to <name type="person">Dr
                                    Edmondes</name> vice-chancellor, dated <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>May 14 1543</date>, about some writings and money due to the university</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. Buckmaster</name> to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Edmondes</name> vice-chancellor, dated <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>May 14 1543</date>, about some writings and money due to the university: he also
                                advises him to abolish the taxers office</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="39" locusStart="113" locusEnd="114">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr Buckmaster</name> vice-chancellor, to <name
                                    type="person">Dr Edmundes</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. Buckmaster</name> vice-chancellor, to <name
                                    type="person">Dr. Edmundes</name>, dated in octava dier. palm:he acquaints him that
                                he had carried the determination of the university to the king;that disputes had arisen
                                in the university concerning it ;and that he had refused an appeal in causa
                                correctionis</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="40" locusStart="115" locusEnd="118">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> to <name
                                    type="person">Henry VIII</name> concerning the authority of the pope in <name
                                    type="place">England</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae academiae ad <name type="person">Henricum VIII</name>: determinant questionem
                                sibi propositam, quod pontifex Romanus non habet majorem potestatem intra haec regna
                                quam alius quivis episcopus extraneus: datae <date>2 Maii 1534</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 37</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>118</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="41" locusStart="119" locusEnd="122">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>An order for preaching and bidding of beads in all sermons to be made within this
                                realm <date>1534</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="42" locusStart="123" locusEnd="124">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Audley, lord keeper of the privy seal,</name>
                                to the vice-chancellor of the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> and the
                                mayor of <name type="place">Cambridge</name>, dated <date>June 3</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">lord Audely</name> lord-keeper to the
                                vice-chancellor, dated <date>June 3</date>: he commands the vice-chancellor and mayor to
                                take the oaths of the scholars and inhabitants of <name type="place"
                                >Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="43" locusStart="125" locusEnd="128">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Papal bulls on the privileges of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Bullae papales de privilegiis academiae</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 43, 44 on small <material>paper</material>, forming a separate
                            book</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="44" locusStart="129" locusEnd="162">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Proceedings concerning the privileges, statutes, customs of the University of
                                Cambridge taken from the black book</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Series cujusdam processus habiti pro confirmatione quorundam privilegiorum,
                                statutorum necnon consuetudinum <name type="place">universitatis Cantabrigiae</name>
                                prout habetur in registro vulgariter dicto, the black-book</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 43, 44 on small <material>paper</material>, forming a separate
                            book</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="45" locusStart="163" locusEnd="164">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Of the excommunication of <name type="person">Dr. Cliff</name>
                                <date>1529</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote><name type="person">Dr. Cliff</name> was chancellor to the <name type="person">bishop
                                    of Ely</name>, and having excommunicated a scholar, he was himself excommunicated by
                                the vice-chancellor as guilty of perjury in infringing the privileges of the university;
                                the doctor refusing to submit to this sentence, the cause was referred to <name
                                    type="person">cardinal Wolsey</name>, who determined it in favor of the
                                university</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 12</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="46" locusStart="165" locusEnd="166">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Oration of <name type="author">Master Roo</name> on the occasion of the visit of
                                    <name type="person">Cardinal Wolsey</name> to <name type="place">Kings' College,
                                    Cambridge</name>, <date>1520</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Oratiuncula <name type="person">Mag. Roo</name>, e collegio regali, cum illuc venerat
                                    <name type="place">cardinalis Wolsey</name>
                                <date>1520</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 9</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="47" locusStart="167" locusEnd="169">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Excommunication of <name type="person">Edward Slegge, mayor of Cambridge</name>,
                                    <date>1529</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Excommunicatio <name type="person">Edwardi Slegge</name> villae Cantabr. majoris ob
                                contumaciam, per I. Venetum vice-can. dep. <date>1529</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="48" locusStart="170" locusEnd="170">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Summons of <name type="person">Elizabeth Slater</name>, <date>1529</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Citatio <name type="person">Elizabethae Slater</name> per eundem
                                <date>1529</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="49" locusStart="170a" locusEnd="170b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Patent issued by <name type="person">Elizabeth I</name> to <name type="person">John
                                    Bodeleigh</name> to print the English bible for seven years</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Patent of <name type="person">Q. Elizabeth</name> to <name type="person">John
                                    Bodeleigh</name> to print the English bible for seven years</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="50" locusStart="171" locusEnd="171">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Summons of <name type="person">William Withringham</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Citatio <name type="person">W. Withringham</name> per <name type="person">I.
                                    Edmundes</name> vice-can. <date>1521</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="51" locusStart="172" locusEnd="172">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Excommunication of <name type="person">Robert Cliff</name>, <date>1538</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Excommunicatio <name type="person">D. Cliff</name> per eundem
                                <date>1538</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Cf. <supplied>item</supplied> 45</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="52" locusStart="173" locusEnd="174">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr Smith, vice-chancellor of the University of
                                    Cambridge</name> to <name type="person">Stephen Gardiner, chancellor of the
                                    university</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. Smith</name> vice-chancellor to the bishop of
                                Winchester chancellor, complaining of the commissary of Ely that he had infringed the
                                privileges of the university by citing the baker of <name type="place">St. John's
                                    college</name> into his court in a cause of defamation</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="53" locusStart="175" locusEnd="176">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Note on <name type="person">Thomas Rotherham, Archbishop of York</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="person">Archbishop Rotherham</name> builder of the schools and benefactor
                                to the library</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>A short note in English</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="54" locusStart="177" locusEnd="178">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> to <name
                                    type="person">John Fisher, Bishop of Rochester and university
                                chancellor</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae academiae ad <name type="person">Fisher episcopum Roffens. cancellarium
                                    suum</name> ut causam de privilegiis academiae apud cardinalem legatum pendentem
                                promoveat</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 10</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="55" locusStart="179" locusEnd="179">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Summons of <name type="person">Roger Hayworde</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Citatio <name type="person">Rogeri Hayworde</name> per <name type="person">E. Natures
                                    vice-can.</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="56" locusStart="180" locusEnd="180">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Writ of <name type="person">Edward VI</name> witnessed by <name type="person">Thomas
                                    Ellens</name>, <date>1549</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Breve <name type="person">Edwardi VI</name>, teste <name type="person">Thoma
                                    Ellens.</name>
                                <date>1549</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. 181-184 missing</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="57" locusStart="185" locusEnd="188">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Stephen Gardiner, chancellor of the <name
                                        type="place">University of Cambridge</name></name> to the
                                vice-chancellor</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the bishop of Winchester chancellor to the vice-chancellor, requiring him
                                to punish the regents who eat flesh in Lent, and those who transgressed the rules he had
                                established for the pronunciation of Greek, dated at the court <date>May
                                15</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 43</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="58" locusStart="189" locusEnd="192">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Notes concerning Stourbridge fair in <name type="place">Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Notes concerning Sturbridge-fair</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Has notes of cases arising at the Fair</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="59" locusStart="193" locusEnd="193">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of attorney for <name type="person">William Sherwood</name> and <name
                                    type="person">John Mere</name>, bedells, in a case against the mayor and bailiffs of
                                Cambridge</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae attornatus sub sigillo academiae, nominantes <name type="person">W.
                                    Shyrwood</name><!--Corrected from Thyrwood, James Corrigenda--> et <name
                                    type="person">I. Meer</name> bedellos, attorn, in causa contra majorem et ballivos
                                    <date>25. Hen. VIII</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="60" locusStart="194" locusEnd="194">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Notes on the master of the Glomery</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De magistro Glomeriae</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Magister Glomeriae fuit quondam is, quem nunc vocamus oratorem, solebat presens esse
                                in omni congregatione, et stare in capite, ne quis graduatus admittatur sine ejus
                                approbatione; et in librum archivorum colligebat et coacervabat omnia notabilia
                                academiae. Primus orator erat <name type="person">dom. Crocus</name></quote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="61" locusStart="195" locusEnd="196">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of attorney for <name type="person">Dr Sampson</name> and others in a case
                                against the mayor of <name type="place">Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae attornatus sub sigillo academiae nominantes <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Sampson</name> et alios attorn. in causis contra majorem <date>26 Hen.
                                VIII</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>196</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="62" locusStart="197" locusEnd="199">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articles of certain injuries done by officers of the university to the mayor with
                                answers to them, <date>1533</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articles of certain injuries done by the officers of the university to the mayor,
                                etc. with the answers to them in the margin <date>1533</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 28</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="63" locusStart="200" locusEnd="202b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articles of complaint submitted to <name type="person">Dr Haynes, vice-chancellor of
                                    the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name></name>, by the mayor of <name
                                    type="place">Cambridge</name>, <date>1534</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articles of complaint given in to <name type="person">Dr. Haynes</name>
                                vice-chancellor, by the mayor, etc. <date>1534</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>202</locus> - <locus>202a</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="64" locusStart="203" locusEnd="204b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Cromwell</name> to the mayor and bailiffs of
                                    <name type="place">Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Cromwell</name> to the mayor, etc. rebuking
                                them for infringing the privileges of the university</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 36</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>203</locus> - <locus>204</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="65" locusStart="205" locusEnd="206">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">R. Ainsworth</name> to <name type="person">Dr
                                    Edmundes</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">R. Aynsworth</name> to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Edmundes</name>, dated <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>Feb. 22</date>. He gives him an account of a complaint that had been made against
                                the university before the council by the townsmen</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 34</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="66" locusStart="206a" locusEnd="206b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Audley, lord chancellor,</name> to the vice
                                chancellor of the University of Cambridge</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">lord Audely</name> lord-chancellor, dated <name
                                    type="place">London</name>
                                <date>Jul. 13</date>, commanding the vice-chancellor to repair to <name type="place"
                                    >London</name> to the determination of the cause between the university and the
                                townsmen</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 40</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="67" locusStart="207" locusEnd="208">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">R. Ainsworth</name> to <name type="person">Dr
                                    Edmundes</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">R. Aynsworth</name> to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Edmundes</name>, dated <name type="place">Cambridge</name>
                                <date>Mar. 20</date>, acquainting him that the council had determined the cause in favor
                                of the university</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 34</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="68" locusStart="209" locusEnd="209">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr Haynes</name> to an unnamed doctor appointing him
                                to preach</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. Haynes</name> to Dr. _____, dated <name
                                    type="place">London</name>
                                <date>May 9</date>, informing him that he is appointed to preach at <name type="place"
                                    >St. Paul's cross</name> and at <name type="place">Westminster</name>; and desiring
                                him to assemble the heads, and to consult about the defence of their privileges</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 35</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="69" locusStart="210" locusEnd="210">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Status of the common chest of the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name>
                                <date>1534</date>-<date>1543</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Status cistae communis academiae ab <date>1534</date> ad <date>1543</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 45</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="70" locusStart="211" locusEnd="217">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Complaints of the mayor and bailiffs of <name type="place">Cambridge</name> against
                                the vice-chancellor and the university</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Instructions of certain liberties and privileges as heretofore have been and yet are
                                daily usurped by the vice-chancellor proctors masters and scholars of the <name
                                    type="place">university of Cambridge</name> against the mayor bayliff and burgesses
                                of the said town</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="71" locusStart="218" locusEnd="218">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the council to the vice-chancellor and <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name>, <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the council to the vice-chancellor and university informing them that
                                after hearing their complaints against the mayor of Cambridge and sheriff of the county,
                                they had ordered the said mayor and sheriff to make their submission to the university,
                                dated <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>Oct. 3, 1547</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 78</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="72" locusStart="219" locusEnd="220">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The wording of the submission to be made by the mayor and bailiffs of <name
                                    type="place">Cambridge</name> to the vice-chancellor and university</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The words of their order to be said by the mayor, etc.</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 79</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>220</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="73" locusStart="221" locusEnd="222">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Grievances declared by <name type="person">John Madew</name>, vice chancellor of the
                                    <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> against the mayor and city of
                                    <name type="place">Cambridge</name>, <date>1546</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The griefs declared by <name type="person">Mr. Madew</name> vice-chancellor, etc.
                                    <date>1546</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 75</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="74" locusStart="223" locusEnd="226">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Response of the mayor of <name type="place">Cambridge</name> to the grievances
                                declared by <name type="person">John Madew</name>, vice-chancellor of the
                                university</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The answer made by Mr. mayor, etc. thereunto</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 77</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>225</locus>-<locus>226</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="75" locusStart="227" locusEnd="240">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Response of the chancellor of the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name>
                                to complaints made by the mayor and townspeople of <name type="place"
                                >Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The answer of the chancellor, etc. to certain pretended and surmized articles</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="76" locusStart="240" locusEnd="240">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Lords of the council confirm the right of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name> to hold a court at Stourbridge fair, <date>1534</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Lords of the council confirm the right of the university to hold a court at
                                Sturbridge-fair and declare spices to be victuals</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 40</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="77" locusStart="241" locusEnd="242">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Privileges sued for by the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Privileges sued for by the university</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 86</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>242</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="78" locusStart="243" locusEnd="244">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Edward Seymour, Duke of Somerset</name> to the mayor
                                and burgesses of <name type="place">Cambridge</name>, <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the <name type="author">duke of Somerset</name> to the mayor and
                                burgesses, requiring them to shew cause why certain privileges which they had petitioned
                                against, should not be granted to the university, <name type="place"
                                    >Hampton-court</name>
                                <date>Jan. 4, 1547</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 87</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>244</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="79" locusStart="245" locusEnd="248">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Conditions and objections returned by the mayor and townsmen of <name type="place"
                                    >Cambridge</name> against the suit of the grant of privileges to the <name
                                    type="place">University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Conditions and objections returned by the mayor and townsmen against the suit of the
                                grant</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi> (1838),
                                88</ref>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>248</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="80" locusStart="249" locusEnd="250">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Commission of <name type="person">Henry VIII</name>, to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name> and others to visit the university</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Commission of <name type="person">Henry VIII</name>, to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Parker</name> and others to visit the university, <date>anno regni 37<abbr
                                        rend="superscript">o</abbr></date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. 251-252 missing</supplied>
                        </ab>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 58</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="81" locusStart="253" locusEnd="254">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Valuation of the livings held by the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Valor possessionum <name type="place">universitatis Cantab.</name> in
                                spiritualibus</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="82" locusStart="255" locusEnd="255">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Tithe of churches and colleges in <name type="place">Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Decimae ecclesiarum et collegiorum infra <name type="place">villam
                                Cantab.</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="83" locusStart="256" locusEnd="258">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>List of foundation dates of the colleges of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Tempora quibus singula collegia fundata sunt</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>257</locus> blank, p. <locus>258</locus> address and seal</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="84" locusStart="259" locusEnd="261">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letters of attorney for <name type="person">William Paget</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >William May</name>, <name type="person">Thomas Wendy</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >John Cheke</name>, <name type="person">Thomas Smith</name> and <name type="person"
                                    >William Cecil</name> in all academic cases, <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae attorn. sub sigillo academiae nominantes <name type="person">W. Paget</name>,
                                    <name type="person">W. Meye</name>, <name type="person">T. Wendeye</name>, <name
                                    type="person">I. Cheke</name>, <name type="person">T. Smith</name>, et <name
                                    type="person">W. Cecil</name> attorn. suos in omnibus causis academiae
                                    <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>260</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="85" locusStart="261" locusEnd="261">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Grace concerning <name type="person">William Paget</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >William May</name>, <name type="person">Thomas Wendy</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >John Cheke</name>, <name type="person">Thomas Smith</name> and <name type="person"
                                    >William Cecil</name> for acting in all academic cases, <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Gratiae de eisdem</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="86" locusStart="262" locusEnd="262">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">William Paget</name> and <name type="author">Thomas
                                    Smith</name>, <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae <name type="author">W. Paget</name>, et <name type="author">Thomae
                                    Smith</name>, datae <name type="place">Londini</name>
                                <date>21 Feb. 1547</date> cum quibus miserunt formam compositionis sequentem inter
                                academiam et burgenses faciendae</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 89</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="87" locusStart="263" locusEnd="266">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Copy of an agreement between the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name>
                                and the town of <name type="place">Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Copy of an agreement between the university and the town</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>The articles objected to by the townsmen are underlined</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 90</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="88" locusStart="267" locusEnd="268">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Proceedings between the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> and the
                                town of <name type="place">Cambridge</name> concerning the articles of an
                                agreement</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Proceedings between the university and the townsmen concerning these articles</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="89" locusStart="269" locusEnd="284">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articles of an agreement between the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name> and the town of <name type="place">Cambridge</name> as corrected by
                                the heads</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The said articles as corrected by the heads</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>The mayor and aldermen not agreeing thereto, a stay was made and nothing
                                ended</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 94</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>279</locus>-<locus>283</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="90" locusStart="285" locusEnd="286">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Declaration by the vice-chancellor and the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name> concerning the behaviour of <name type="person">William
                                    Pallet</name>, <date>1552</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Declaration by the vice-chancellor and the <name type="place">university of
                                    Cambridge</name> of the behaviour of one <name type="person">William Pallet</name>
                                deputed purveyor of the kings majesties provision and poultry <date>1552</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>A lively picture of the grievance of purveyance so often and so justly complained
                                of</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 155</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="91" locusStart="287" locusEnd="287">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Conference between several of the heads of <name type="place">Cambridge</name> about
                                enclosing commons and other matters, <date>June 5, 1548</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Conference between several of the heads about enclosing commons and other matters,
                                    <date>June 5, 1548</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Cooper 1843">Cooper, <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> II
                            18</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="92" locusStart="288" locusEnd="292">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Conference between the heads, mayor and townsmen of <name type="place"
                                    >Cambridge</name> about enclosing commons</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Conference between the heads mayor and townsmen about enclosing commons</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Cooper 1843">Cooper, <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> II
                            18</ref></ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>290</locus>-<locus>292</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="93" locusStart="293" locusEnd="299">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Form of a charter of privileges of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name> petitioned for but not granted</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Forma cartae privilegiorum ab academia petitae sed non concessas</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="94" locusStart="300" locusEnd="300">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Grace concerning degrees to be conferred</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Gratia de gradibus conferendis</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="95" locusStart="300a" locusEnd="300b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Petition for a grant of the Franciscan priory to the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Petition for a grant of the priory of friers-minor to the university, and form of the
                                grant, which was not obtained</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>On <material>vellum</material></ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>300a</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="96" locusStart="301" locusEnd="308">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Charter of the mayor and bailiffs of <name type="place">Cambridge</name> concerning
                                the Stourbridge fair</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta majori, etc. Cantab, concessa de nundinis Sturbridge tenendis, pro qua
                                solverunt finem <name type="person">M. Marcarum</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>301</locus>, <locus>304</locus>, <locus>305</locus>, <locus>308</locus>
                                are blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="97" locusStart="309" locusEnd="311">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Taxation of the colleges of the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name> for
                                the tenth and benevolence of <date>1539</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Taxatio collegiorum pro decimis et pro benevolentia <date>1539</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Decimae remissae sunt ad supplicationem Annae reginae</quote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="98" locusStart="312" locusEnd="314">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Jack of the North, beyond the stile, a ballad</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 160</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>314</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="99" locusStart="315" locusEnd="317">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Ballad on the enclosure of commons in <name type="place">Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Another ballad</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>The subject of these ballads is the enclosure of commons, which caused great
                                disturbances in the reign of <name type="person">Edward VI</name></quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>To all false fflattering ffreemen of <name type="place">Cambrige</name>, etc.</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <lg>
                                <l>Thoughe thow take muche payne</l>
                                <l>to ditche vp ageyne</l>
                            </lg>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="100" locusStart="318" locusEnd="318">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Decree for the regulation of the university chest of the <name type="place"
                                    >University of Cambridge</name>, <date>1553</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Decree made by <name type="person">Dr. Madew</name> vice-chancellor, <name
                                    type="person">Dr. Parker</name> and <name type="person">Mr. Gryndall</name> for the
                                regulation of the university-chest, <date>6 Edw. VI</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="101" locusStart="319" locusEnd="321">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Bond given by <name type="person">John Meres</name> and others for payment of money
                                to the common chest</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="102" locusStart="322" locusEnd="322">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Orders for a watch at the time of the Stourbridge fair in <name type="place"
                                    >Cambridge</name>, <date>1550</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Orders for a watch in the time of Sturbridge-fair <date>1550</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">Original Documents</hi>
                                (1838)</ref>, 151</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="103" locusStart="323" locusEnd="325">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Orders for a watch at the time of the Stourbridge fair in <name type="place"
                                    >Cambridge</name>, <date>1551</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The same <date>1551</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="104" locusStart="326" locusEnd="326">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter concerning clothing for some men for the <name type="person">Duke of
                                    Norfolk</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter concerning the cloathing some men to be sent to the duke of Norfolk</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="105" locusStart="327" locusEnd="331">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Account of the charges of raising and arraying men paid by several colleges and
                                townspeople in <name type="place">Cambridge</name>, <date>1544</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Account of the charges of raising and arraying the men and the assessment paid by the
                                several colleges and private persons thereto</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="106" locusStart="332" locusEnd="338">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>An assessment <date>3 Edw. VI</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="107" locusStart="339" locusEnd="340">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Assessment of the university and town of <name type="place">Cambridge</name> for the
                                loan to <name type="person">Mary I</name>, <date>1557</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Assessment of the university and town for the loan to the queen
                                <date>1557</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>The commissioners for the loan thus sent to the university but discharged by
                                letters</quote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="108" locusStart="340" locusEnd="340">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The oath given by the proctors of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name> at the black assembly</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The oath given by the proctors at the black-assembly</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="109" locusStart="340" locusEnd="340">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Black Assembly</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Le black-assembl&#233; tent' <date>Oct. 25, 24 Hen. VIII</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="110" locusStart="341" locusEnd="348">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Orders for commencement at the <name type="place">University of
                                Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The order for the commencement, containing the form of the commencement and vepers in
                                divinity and arts</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. 349 - 350 missing</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="111" locusStart="351" locusEnd="353">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Edward North</name> to the <name type="place"
                                    >University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir Edward North</name>, dated <name type="place"
                                    >London</name>
                                <date>Jan. 16</date>, desiring that the king's scholars may be diligently examined, that
                                such as are most worthy may be nominated on the foundation of the new college</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>352</locus>-<locus>353</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="112" locusStart="354" locusEnd="356">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Indentures of <date>1551</date> and <date>1553</date> found in the common chest of
                                the <name type="place">University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Indentura facta <date>21 Nov. 1551</date>; Indentura facta <date>12 Nov. 1553</date>.
                                Hae indenturae testantur summam in cistis communibus relictam, recedentibus ab officio
                                custodibus</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>356</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="113" locusStart="357" locusEnd="357">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Edward North</name> to the <name type="place"
                                    >University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir Edward North</name> to the university, dated
                                    <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>April 13</date>, informing them that according to agreement he had appointed <name
                                    type="person">Mr. William Cateryk</name> to be by them presented to the vicarage of
                                    <name type="place">Burwell</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 113 sqq. Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Clark 1904">Clark, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Endowments</hi></ref>, pp. 9 sqq.</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="114" locusStart="358" locusEnd="358f">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Indentures of <date>1549</date>, <date>1542</date>, <date>1483</date> and
                                    <date>1548</date> found in the common chest of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Indenturae factae <date>9. Dec. 1549</date>, <date>3 Martis 1542</date>, <date>7 Nov.
                                    1483</date>, and <date>12 Nov. 1548</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Ejusdem formae cum prioribus illis 112</quote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="115" locusStart="359" locusEnd="359">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Edward North</name> to the <name type="place"
                                    >University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir Edward North</name> to the university, dated
                                    <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>May 15</date>:he thanks them for presenting the person whom he had nominated to
                                the vicarage of <name type="place">Burwell</name>, and desires them to assign him a
                                mansion, and to pay his salary quarterly</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="116" locusStart="360" locusEnd="360">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Payments made from the common chest to the vice-chancellor of the <name type="place"
                                    >University of Cambridge</name>, <date>1554</date>-<date>1559</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Solutiones factae cistae communi a vice-cancellariis ab anno <date>1544</date> ad
                                annum <date>1559</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="117" locusStart="361" locusEnd="362">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Money to be returned to the common chest of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name>, <date>1545</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statutum de pecunia cistae refundenda <date>1545</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="118" locusStart="362" locusEnd="363">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Decision concerning the rectory of <name type="place">Burwell</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statutum de rectoria <name type="place">Burwelli</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="119" locusStart="364" locusEnd="364">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Excerpt from a charter of <name type="person">Henry VIII</name> concerning the
                                appropriation of the rectory of <name type="place">Burwell</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Excerpta e charta <name type="person">Henrici VIII.</name> de appropriatione
                                rectoriae de <name type="place">Burwell</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="120" locusStart="364a" locusEnd="364b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Andrew Perne</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name>, <date>1572</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. Andrew Perne</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name> archbishop of Canterbury <date>Oct. 15, 1572</date>: he gives
                                his opinion of the incorporation of the university granted at the purchasing of the
                                rectory of <name type="place">Burwell</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="121" locusStart="365" locusEnd="370">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Lease of the parsonage of <name type="place">Burwell</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Nicholas Bacon</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Lease of the parsonage of <name type="place">Burwell</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Nicholas Bacon, Esq</name>; for 30 years; at the yearly rent of 50Ł. 13s. 6d.
                                    <date>36 Hen. VIII</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="122" locusStart="370" locusEnd="370">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Grace concerning the rectory of <name type="place">Burwell</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Gratia de rectoria de <name type="place">Burwell</name>
                                <name type="person">Mag. Gardiner</name> ad firmam mittenda</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="123" locusStart="371" locusEnd="371">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Bond of Ł100 from <name type="person">Nicholas Bacon</name> to the <name type="place"
                                    >University of Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Bond of 100Ł. from <name type="person">Nicholas Bacon, Esq</name>; to the <name
                                    type="place">university of Cambridge</name> for performance of covenants</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>
