<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC108">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>108</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. 0</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Documents Relating principally to Stoke College, Lincoln Cathedral and Cambridge</head>
                <head type="James">Documents Relating Principally to Stoke College, Lincoln Cathedral and
                    Cambridge</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper (and some vellum documents)</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">298</height>
                        <width unit="mm">216</width>
                    </measureGrp>
                    <measureGrp type="James">12 x 9</measureGrp>, <extent>paged to 564</extent>, <quote>seculo
                            <origDate>xvi</origDate> scriptus</quote>.</p>
                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iii + pp. 1-84 + 84a-f + 85-6 (87-90 missing) + 91-108 (109-110 missing) + 111-164
                        (165-166 missing) + 167-204 + 204a-205a + 205-206 + 206a-207a + 207-388 + 388a-389a + 389-400 +
                        400a-d + 401-558 + 558a-d + 559-564 + ff. iv-v</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="iiir" locusEnd="iiiv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Licence for non residence granted to <name type="person">Pierre Alexander</name>,
                                prebend at <name type="place">Canterbury</name>
                                <date>temp. Elizabeth I</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Licentia regia de non residentia concessa <name type="person">doctori Petro
                                    Alexander</name> prebendario <name type="place">Cantuar.</name>
                                <date>tempore reginae Eliz.</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><material>On vellum</material> (<date>2 Elizabeth</date>)</ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="3" locusEnd="26">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Appropriation of the <name type="place">church of Great Dunmowe</name> in <name
                                    type="place">Essex</name> made to the <name type="place">college of Stoke</name>
                                <date>1481</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Appropriatio <name type="place">ecclesiae de Dunmowe</name> magna in <name
                                    type="place">Essex</name>, facta collegio de <name type="place">Stoke juxta
                                    Clare</name>
                                <date>1481</date>, original</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Reservatur vicario portio congrua et antiqua: - omnia onera per rectorem supportari
                                consueta, decanus et capitulum dicti collegii deinceps supportabunt; - preterea solvent
                                annuatim episcopo London 40s. decano et capitulo <name type="place">London</name> 3s.
                                4d. archdiacono Middlesex 26s. 8d.- presentatio ad vicariam erit in episcopo London, et
                                decano et capitulo collegii de <name type="place">Stoke</name> alternatim: - in die
                                caenae Domini distribuetur pauperibus ejusdem parochiae 5s.</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><material>Vellum</material>, has the notarial mark of <name type="person">N. Collys</name>:
                            see his book no. <ref type="ms" target="CCC170">170</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="27" locusEnd="52">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Appropriation of the <name type="place">church of Wetherfield</name> made to the
                                    <name type="place">college of Stoke</name>
                                <date>1503</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Appropriatio <name type="place">ecclesiae de Wetherfield</name>, facta collegio de
                                    <name type="place">Stoke juxta Clare</name>, circa annum <date>1503</date>,
                                Orig.</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Solvent episcopo London 13s. 4d. decano et capitulo <name type="place">London</name>
                                20d. archidiacono Middlesex 6s. 8d. decanus et capitulum collegii de Stoke habebunt
                                presentationem ad vicariam: - vicarius habebit decimas lanae agnorum vitulorum
                                agistamentorum casei, necnon oblationes et altaragia, omnesque singulas et personales,
                                prediales duntaxat minores mixtas et minutas: et habebit ad minus 10Ł annuatim</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><material>Vellum</material>, notarial mark of <name type="person">Ric. Spencer</name></ab>
                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="53" locusEnd="72">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The reformed statues of <name type="place">Stoke college</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statuta collegii de <name type="place">Stoke</name> reformata</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Haec statuta in hunc ordinem et formam reducta, rata et comprobata sunt deinceps
                                perpetuo observanda, assensu totius capituli Anno Domini <date>1537</date>, <name
                                    type="person">Mattheo Parker</name> decano</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>Continues on pp. <locus>129</locus>-<locus>137</locus>.</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="73" locusEnd="73">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Two letters from <name type="author">John Skypp</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Two letters from <name type="author">John Skypp</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name>, informing him, that it is the queen's [<name type="person">Anna
                                    Boleyn</name>] pleasure that he should come up to court, and that she intends to
                                make him her chaplain</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Correspondence</hi> I, II</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="74" locusEnd="74">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Presentation of <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name> to the deanery of <name
                                    type="place">Stoke College</name> by <name type="person">Queen Anne</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Presentatio <name type="person">Matthei Parker</name> ad decanatum collegii de <name
                                    type="place">Stoke</name> per Annam reginam <date> 4 Nov. 27 Hen.
                                VIII.</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Parker
                                    Correspondence</hi> Ib, V</ref>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="74" locusEnd="74">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Composition of the first fruits of <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name> upon his
                                appointment as dean of <name type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Compositio de primitiis ejusdem <date> 5 Nov. 27 Hen. VIII. </date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="75" locusEnd="82">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Thomas Barnsley</name>, <title>Account statutes of <name
                                    type="place">Stoke College</name> transcribed by <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title></head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statuta antiqua collegii de <name type="place">Stoke</name> facta per <name
                                    type="person">Thomam Barnesley</name> et transcripta per <name type="person">M.
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>Continues on pp. <locus>117</locus>-<locus>124</locus></supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="83" locusEnd="84b">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Sylloge of sermons on the holy scripture held at <name type="place">Stoke</name>
                                <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Sylloge praelectionis in S. scripturas habitae apud <name type="place">Stoke</name>
                                <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="84c" locusEnd="86">



                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Agreement between <name type="person">M. Parker</name> and the executors of <name
                                    type="person">T. Shorten</name> late dean of <name type="place">Stoke</name> about
                                dilapidations, <date>Feb. 18. 27 Hen. VIII.</date></title>

                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="90" locusEnd="90">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The names of the deans of <name type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Nomina decanorum collegii de <name type="place">Stoke</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Note that the 2nd page of this follows <supplied>item</supplied> no. 21</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>Continues on p. <locus>115</locus> and on p. <locus>116</locus>.</supplied>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">Printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Masters 1753"
                                    >Masters's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, App. p. 38-40</ref> (H. P. S.)</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="91" locusEnd="92">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Cecily Neville, Duchess of York</name> to the dean
                                and canons of <name type="place">Stoke</name>
                                <date>Feb. 8</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Cecill duchess of York</name> [mother of <name
                                    type="person">Edw. IV</name>. and <name type="person">Ric. III</name>.] to the dean
                                and canons of <name type="place">Stoke</name>, recommending <name type="person">John
                                    Davy</name> to be appointed verger. <name type="place">Bernardcastle</name>
                                <date>Feb. 8</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="93" locusEnd="94">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Cecily Neville, Duchess of York</name> to the dean
                                and canons of <name type="place">Stoke</name>
                                <date>Dec. 3</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>From the same, recommending <name type="person">Sir Richard Heggis</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Sir Richard Shurborne</name> to be presented unto two prebends in that
                                college. <name type="place">Westminster</name>
                                <date>Dec. 3</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="95" locusEnd="96">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Cecily Neville, Duchess of York</name> to the dean
                                and canons of <name type="place">Stoke</name>
                                <date>7 Jan</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>From the same desiring to have the nomination to the two prebends that shall next
                                become vacant. From the <name type="place">manor of the More</name>, <date>7
                                Jan.</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="97" locusEnd="98">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard [Edenham] bishop of Bangor</name> to <name
                                    type="person">William Wilflete</name> dean of <name type="place">Stoke</name>, <name
                                    type="place">London</name>
                                <date>28 Oct.</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard [Edenham] bishop of Bangor</name> to <name
                                    type="person">William Wilflete</name> dean of <name type="place">Stoke-Clare</name>,
                                acquainting him that he is nominated to a prebend in the college of <name type="place"
                                    >Stoke</name>, and desiring a presentation to the same, and that his brother may
                                have the vicarage of <name type="place">Thaxted</name>. <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>28 Oct.</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="16" locusStart="99" locusEnd="100">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Anthony Denny</name> to the commissioners for
                                dissolution</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Anthony Denny</name> to the commissioners
                                recommending <name type="person">Dr. Parker</name> to them, and desiring that at the
                                dissolution of the college he might have a suitable pension. <name type="place"
                                    >Cheshunt</name>
                                <date>ultimo Feb. 1547</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> p. 33
                                note</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="17" locusStart="101" locusEnd="102">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the commissioners of dissolution to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the commissioners to <name type="person">Dr. Parker</name>, desiring him
                                to have in readiness a rentall and inventory of the possessions of his college. <name
                                    type="place">Blithborough</name>
                                <date>Mar. 5</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="18" locusStart="103" locusEnd="106">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Donations of <name type="person">Edmund earl of march</name> made to <name
                                    type="place">Stoke College</name>
                                <date>1415</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Donationes Edmundi comitis Marchiae factae collegio de <name type="place"
                                    >Stoke</name> et a capitulo ejusdem confirmatae <date>ult. Feb. 1415</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On <material>vellum</material>, <extent>ff. 2</extent> smaller size</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="19" locusStart="107" locusEnd="108">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Nicholas Bacon</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Nicholas Bacon</name> to <name type="person">M.
                                    Parker</name> with his opinion in several cases proposed to him</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, <hi rend="italic">Parker</hi> Appendix
                                II</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="20" locusStart="111" locusEnd="112">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">archbishop Cranmer</name> to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Parker</name>, <name type="place">Lambeth</name>
                                <date>May 5</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">archbishop Cranmer</name> to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Parker</name> appointing him to preach at <name type="place">St. Paul's
                                cross</name>. <name type="place">Lambeth</name>
                                <date>May 5</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>
                                XXVII</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="21" locusStart="113" locusEnd="124">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Walter Haddon</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name> dated at <name type="place">Norwich</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literas <name type="author">Gualteri Haddon</name> ad <name type="person">Mattheum
                                    Parker</name> datae ex suburbano <name type="place">Norwiaco</name> quae Thorpa
                                nuncupatur; orat ut se et amicos suos, quos pestis ab academia fugaverat, in domicilium
                                ejus apud <name type="place">Stoke</name> accipere dignaretur</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Followed by end of <supplied>item</supplied> 11, and of <supplied>item</supplied> 8</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="22" locusStart="125" locusEnd="126">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Instructions of my <name type="person">lord of the March</name> given to the <name
                                    type="person">dean of Stoke</name> for the making of certeine statutes for the
                                college</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="23" locusStart="127" locusEnd="137">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to the king's commissioners for
                                dissolution</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">M. Parker</name> to the king's commissioners,
                                requesting their protection for the college of <name type="place">Stoke</name>, and
                                assigning reasons why it would be more convenient not to suppress it</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, Appendix VI</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Corr</hi>. XXXIII</ref></ab>
                        <ab>Followed by end of <supplied>item</supplied> 4</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="24" locusStart="138" locusEnd="138">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Donation of <name type="person">Edmund earl of March</name> made to <name
                                    type="place">Stoke College</name>
                                <date>1415</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Donatio <name type="person">Edmundi comitis Marchiae</name> facta collegio de <name
                                    type="place">Stoke</name> a capitulo ejusdem confirmata, <date>12 Martii
                                1415</date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="25" locusStart="139" locusEnd="140">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Papal bull for the establishment at <name type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Bulla papalis pro fundatione collegii de <name type="place">Stoke</name></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="26" locusStart="141" locusEnd="142">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Donation of <name type="person">Edmund earl of March</name> of all possessions once
                                pertained to the <name type="place">priory of Stoke</name> to the dean and chapter of
                                    <name type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Donatio <name type="person">Edmundi comitis Marchiae</name> omnium possessionum, quae
                                olim pertinebant ad prioratum de <name type="place">Stoke</name>, decano et capitulo
                                collegii de <name type="place">Stoke</name>, <date> 7 Hen. V </date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="27" locusStart="143" locusEnd="145">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Confirmation of the establishment of <name type="place">Stoke College</name> by the
                                    <name type="person">bishop of Lincoln</name>
                                <date>1422</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Confirmatio collegii de <name type="place">Stoke</name> per <name type="person"
                                    >episcopum Lincoln.</name>
                                <date>1422</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="28" locusStart="146" locusEnd="146">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Oath of the canons at <name type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Juramentum canonici</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="29" locusStart="146" locusEnd="146">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The method of installing canons of <name type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Modus inducendi canonicum per installationem ejusdem</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="30" locusStart="147" locusEnd="147">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Account of <name type="person">Edmund Mortimer</name> earl of March and Ulster,
                                founder of the college of <name type="place">Stoke</name></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="31" locusStart="148" locusEnd="148">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Epitaph of <name type="person">Edmund Mortimer, earl of March</name> in the choir of
                                    <name type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epitaphium ejusdem in choro collegii</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>12 lines beginning</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="148">Instabilis mundus mortalibus ecce minatur</incipit>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="32" locusStart="149" locusEnd="151">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Of <name type="person">Edmund Mortimer, earl of March</name> and founder of <name
                                    type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De <name type="person">Edmundo de Mortuo-mari</name> comite Marchise et fundatore
                                collegii de <name type="place">Stoke</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="33" locusStart="152" locusEnd="152">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Tithes that should be paid by the dean and canons of <name type="place"
                                >Stoke</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Decimas solvendae per decanum et canonicos de <name type="place">Stoke</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="34" locusStart="153" locusEnd="154">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Declaration of the account of master <name type="person">Thomas Bacon</name>,
                                overseer of <name type="place">Stoke College</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Declaratio computi <name type="person">magistri Thomae Bacon</name> clerici,
                                praepositi collegii de <name type="place">Stoke juxta Clare</name>, pro uno anno integro
                                finito ad festum S. Michaelis archangeli, <date> 38 Hen. VIII. </date></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="35" locusStart="155" locusEnd="160">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statutes for the college of <name type="place">Stoke</name>, drawn up by <name
                                    type="person">M. Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="36" locusStart="161" locusEnd="164">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Stokes</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">M. Parker</name> to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Stokes</name>, exhorting him not to raise any controversy, nor to stir up the people
                                to sedition by his preaching, <name type="place">Stoke-college</name>
                                <date>23 Nov.</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Strype1711">Strype Appendix III</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> X</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="37" locusStart="167" locusEnd="168">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. Stokes</name> to the lord privy-seal</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. Stokes</name> to the lord privy-seal, imploring
                                his lordship's protection, and clearing himself from some accusations brought against
                                him</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype Appendix IV</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> p. 14
                            note</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="38" locusStart="169" locusEnd="170">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articles of accusation sent to the <name type="person">lord Audely</name>, lord
                                chancellor, by <name type="person">Mr. G. Colt</name> and others of <name type="place"
                                    >Clare town</name> against <name type="person">M. Parker</name> with his answer to
                                them</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>These articles objected were thus answered by <name type="person">M. P.</name> and
                                sent to the lord chancellor, which heard he blamed the promoters, and sent word that I
                                should go on and fear not such enemies</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>
                                VIII</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="39" locusStart="171" locusEnd="176">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Statutes of <name type="place">Stoke College</name> translated into English by <name
                                    type="person">Matthew Parker</name> from a Latin version by <name type="person">John
                                    Cheke</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statuta collegii de <name type="place">Stoke juxta Clare</name>, scripta Anglice a
                                    <name type="person">Mattheo Parker</name>, et Latine versa per <name type="person"
                                    >Ioannem Cheke</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="40" locusStart="177" locusEnd="207a">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Inventory of all ornaments and other goods of the <name type="place">church of Stoke
                                    by Clare College</name>
                                <date>1534</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Inventorium factum <date>I<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> Julii, 1534</date>, de
                                omnibus iocalibus ornamentis, et caeteris bonis ecclesiae collegiatas de <name
                                    type="place">Stoke juxta Clare</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Divided into Calices | Cruces | Ymagines | Jocalia pro communi usu Collegii | Libri (all
                            service books, some printed) | Candelabra | Caps ( = Copes) | Casule etc. | Ornamenta
                            altarium | Corporalia cum thecis | Vexilla | puluinaria | Coopertoria ymaginum in temp.
                            quadragesimali</ab>
                        <ab>Other items follow</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="41" locusStart="207" locusEnd="208">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Taxatio of the prebends of the <name type="place">cathedral church of
                                Lincoln</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Taxatio prebendarum <name type="place">ecclesiae cathedralis Lincoln.</name> secundum
                                quam solvuntur septimiae non residentium</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="42" locusStart="209" locusEnd="214">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Names and surnames of al canons and prebendaries of the <name type="place">cathedral
                                    church of Lincoln</name>
                                <date>1552</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Nomina et cognomina omnium canonicorum et prebendariorum <name type="place">ecclesiae
                                    cathedralis Lincoln.</name>
                                <date>1552</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="43" locusStart="215" locusEnd="218">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>A declaration of the revenue appertaining to the <name type="place">Lincoln
                                    cathedral</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A declaration of the revenewe appertayning to the <name type="place">cathedral
                                    churche of our blessed ladye of Lincolne</name> with the allowances and yearly
                                charges goinge and issuinge out of the same, made <date>7<abbr rend="superscript"
                                        >o</abbr> die Sept. Anno Domini 1559</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="44" locusStart="219" locusEnd="220">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>A declaration of all the revenue belonging to the fabric of <name type="place"
                                    >Lincoln cathedral</name>
                                <date>1559</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A declaration of all the revenewe belonginge unto the fabrick of the <name
                                    type="place">cathedral church of Lincoln</name>
                                <date>1559</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="45" locusStart="221" locusEnd="222">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The sum of all the lands and livings appertaining unto the vicars of Lincoln</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="46" locusStart="223" locusEnd="224">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Annual revenues of the choir house of <name type="place">Lincoln
                                cathedral</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Revenciones domus choristarum <name type="place">ecclesiae cathedralis beati Mariae
                                    Lincoln</name>, per annum</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="47" locusStart="225" locusEnd="232">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Pensions and other duties due unto the dean and chapter of the cathedral church of
                                Lincoln which has not been paid</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Pencions and other duties due unto the dean and chapter of the <name type="place"
                                    >cathedral church of Lincoln</name> which hath not been paid and are denied since
                                the dissolution of the abbies and chantries</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="48" locusStart="233" locusEnd="238">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Pensions belonging to the choristers of the <name type="place">cathedral church of
                                    Lincoln</name> and unpaid</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Pencions belonging to the choristers of the <name type="place">cathedral church of
                                    Lincoln</name> and unpaid</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="49" locusStart="239" locusEnd="246">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Valor of the possesion of the dean of <name type="place">Lincoln cathedral</name> and
                                the prebends of <name type="place">Corringham</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Valor possessionum decanatus ecclesiae cathedralis Lincoln, et prebendae de
                                Corringham in eadem, ex recordis D. N. regis curiae suae primorum fructuum et
                                decimarum</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="50" locusStart="247" locusEnd="248">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statutum de canonico mortuo et de firmis ecclesiae</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="51" locusStart="249" locusEnd="251">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Extracts from the register of <name type="person">William Alnwick, bishop of
                                    Lincoln</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Quae continentur in registro novo <name type="person">W. Alnewyke</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="52" locusStart="252" locusEnd="254">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>From the oath of deans and others of <name type="place">Lincoln
                                cathedral</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Forma juramenti decani, et cetera, <name type="person">Lincoln</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="53" locusStart="255" locusEnd="260">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Excerpts from the black book which is called the ancient register of <name
                                    type="place">Lincoln</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Excerpta ex nigro libro qui dicitur registrum vetus</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="54" locusStart="261" locusEnd="264">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Contents of a <name type="place">Lincoln</name> register</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Contenta in registro</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="55" locusStart="265" locusEnd="270">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Injunctions given by the most excellent <name type="person">prince Edward VI.</name>
                                in his highness' visitation to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Injunctions given by the most excellent <name type="person">prince Edward VI.</name>
                                in his highness' visitation to the dean and subdean, chancellor, chaunter, treasurer,
                                archdeacons, prebendaries, peti-canons, vicars and all others ministers, primo regni
                                anno</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">See <ref type="bibl" target="Wordsworth 1897b">Bradshaw
                                    and Wordsworth, <hi rend="italic">Lincoln Cathedral Statutes</hi> III 579
                                sqq.</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="56" locusStart="271" locusEnd="272">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The form of the objections of the deans of <name type="place">Lincoln
                                    cathedral</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Forma protestationis decani</title>
                            <!--Corrected from potestationis to protestationis in James Corrigenda-->
                        </head>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="57" locusStart="273" locusEnd="320">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Register of <name type="person">William Alnwick bishop of Lincoln</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Registrum <name type="person">W. de Alnewyke episcopi Lincoln.</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Nova est forma statutorum cum assensu decani et capituli stabilita Anno Domini
                                    <date>1440</date></quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Relates to <name type="place">Lincoln</name></ab>
                        <ab><supplied>This item</supplied> is a separate book of cent. <origDate>xv</origDate>. It is
                            the second draft of the <hi rend="italic">Novum Registrum</hi> of <name type="person">Bishop
                                Alnwick</name>
                            <date>1440</date>, on which see <ref type="bibl" target="Wordsworth 1892"><hi rend="italic"
                                    >Lincoln Cathedral Statutes</hi>, Bradshaw and Wordsworth I 182, 246 etc. and text
                                in Part II</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="58" locusStart="321" locusEnd="334">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Tract concerning the holding of parliament</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Tractatus de parliamento</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Citatur hic tractatus per <name type="person">dom. Elsinge</name> in libro suo, <ref
                                    type="bib" target="Elsynge 1660">Of the lawe of parliaments</ref>, sub titulo
                                tractatus veteris de modo tenendi parliament</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 58 <supplied>and</supplied> 59 form a volume</ab>
                        <ab>Headed</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="321">Sine regali prouidentia impossibile est rebus pacem dare. Mach.
                            primo</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="321">De gradibus parliamenti qui sunt sex in numero</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="321">Rex est caput principium et finis parliamenti</incipit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="59" locusStart="335" locusEnd="336">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Charge or oath given to the privy-counsellors in the star-chamber</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 58 <supplied>and</supplied> 59 form a volume</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="60" locusStart="337" locusEnd="396">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Statutes for the church and college of <name type="place">Strassbourg</name> in <name
                                    type="place">Germany</name> in <name type="person">Martin Bucer</name>'s
                                hand</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Statuta pro <name type="place">ecclesia et collegio Argentinae</name> in Germania
                                scripta a <name type="person">Bucero</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 60 - 63 form a separate volume</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="61" locusStart="397" locusEnd="398">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Oath of <name type="person">John Immanuel Tremellius</name> upon his appointment as a
                                prebend at <name type="place">Strassbourg</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Obligatio <name type="person">Ioannis Himmanuel Tremellii</name> facta quando
                                praebendam accepit in <name type="place">ecclesia Argentina</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 60 - 63 form a separate volume</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>
                                CCXLI, note</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="62" locusStart="399" locusEnd="400">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the <name type="place">College of Strassbourg</name> to <name
                                    type="person">Martin Bucer</name>, <date>1544</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae collegii Argentinae ad <name type="person">Bucerum</name>, quibus eum
                                certiorem faciunt quod electus est in decanum collegii</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 60 - 63 form a separate volume</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="399">Dated <name type="place">Strasburg</name>, <date>pridie Kal. Ap.
                            1544</date></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="63" locusStart="400a" locusEnd="402">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Summons to the diocesan Synod at <name type="place">Saverne</name>, <date>February
                                    1549</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Citatio ad synodum dicecesanam apud <name type="place">Zabern</name> tenendam <date>2
                                    Aprilis</date> per <name type="person">Erasmum</name> ecclesiae Argentinas Alsatias
                                Landgravium</title>, printed with his seal affixed</head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 60 - 63 form a separate volume</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="400b">Dated <date>4 Feb. 1549</date></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="64" locusStart="403" locusEnd="414">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Draft of statutes for <name type="place">Tunbridge school</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Draft of statutes for <name type="place">Tunbridge school</name> erected by <name
                                    type="person">Sir Andrew Judd</name> knight and alderman of London, confirmed by the
                                archbishop of Canterbury and the dean of St. Paul's</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>This school was confirmed by act of parliament <date>1572</date>, which act is not in
                                the printed statute book</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> p.
                                211 note</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="65" locusStart="415" locusEnd="416">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the master and wardens of the skinners company, governors of <name
                                    type="place">Tunbridge school</name>, to <name type="person">archbishop Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the master and wardens of the skinners company, governors of the said
                                school, to <name type="person">archbishop Parker</name>, desiring his confirmation of
                                the statutes drawn by <name type="person">Dr. Nowel dean of St. Paul's</name>, <name
                                    type="place">London</name>
                                <date>May 7, 1564</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>
                                CLX</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="66" locusStart="417" locusEnd="417">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Act of parliament declaring <name type="person">Henry VI</name>, to have forfeited
                                all his estate to <name type="person">Edward IV</name>, and investing <name
                                    type="person">Edward IV</name>, with the <name type="place">dutchy of
                                    Lancaster</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="67" locusStart="418" locusEnd="420">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Charter of <name type="person">Elizabeth I</name> for the foundation of a grammar
                                school at <name type="place">Sevenoaks</name> in the <name type="place">county of
                                    Kent</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta Elizabethae pro fundatione scholae grammaticalis apud <name type="place"
                                    >Sevenoke in comitatu Cantiae</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="68" locusStart="421" locusEnd="426">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Expences at law between <name type="person">archbishop Parker</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Sir John Byron knight</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Expences at law between <name type="person">archbishop Parker</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Sir John Byron knight</name>, farmer of the <name type="place"
                                    >parsonage of Rachedale</name> in the county of <name type="place"
                                >Lancaster</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="69" locusStart="427" locusEnd="428">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Directions for building a school-room at Rochdale</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Directions for building a school-room</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="70" locusStart="429" locusEnd="430">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Francis</name> and <name type="author">Charles
                                    Holt</name> esqrs. and <name type="person">Charles Radcliff</name> to <name
                                    type="person">Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Francis</name> and <name type="person">Charles
                                    Holt</name> esqrs. and <name type="author">Charles Radcliff</name> desiring a longer
                                time may be granted them for building the school at <name type="place">Rachdale</name>,
                                    <date>March 6, 1566</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="71" locusStart="431" locusEnd="432">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Francis</name> and <name type="author">Charles
                                    Holt</name> esqrs. and <name type="person">Charles Radcliff</name> thanking the
                                archbishop for establishing the school, and assuring him of their intention of building
                                a school-house, <date>March 13, 1561</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>From the same, thanking the archbishop for establishing the school, and assuring him
                                of their intention of building a school-house. <name type="place">Rachdale</name>
                                <date>March 13, 1561</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="72" locusStart="433" locusEnd="434">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Francis</name> and <name type="author">Charles
                                    Holt</name> esqrs. and <name type="person">Charles Radcliff</name> thanking the
                                archbishop for establishing the school, and assuring him of their intention of building
                                a school-house</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>From the same on the same subject</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="73" locusStart="435" locusEnd="435">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to the inhabitants of <name
                                    type="place">Rochedale</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the archbishop to the inhabitants of <name type="place">Rachdale</name>
                                concerning the building of the school</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>
                                CLXXIII</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="74" locusStart="436" locusEnd="436">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="person">Sir John
                                    Byron</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same to <name type="person">Sir John Byron</name>, desiring him to
                                pay the remainder of the stipend of the vicar and curate towards the building of the
                                said school</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi>
                                CLXXIV</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="75" locusStart="437" locusEnd="438">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Promissory note from <name type="person">Sir John Byron</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Promissory note from <name type="person">Sir John Byron</name> to the archbishop for
                                payment of the said arrears <date>27 Nov. 4 Eliz</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="76" locusStart="439" locusEnd="440">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Hill</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name>
                                <date>24 Apr. 1564</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Hill</name> to the archbishop acquainting him
                                that two of the inhabitants of <name type="place">Rachdale</name> are come up to town,
                                in order to give bond for building the school-house <date>24 Apr. 1564</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="77" locusStart="441" locusEnd="442">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Francis Holt</name>, <name type="author">Charles
                                    Holt</name> and <name type="author">Charles Radcliff</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name>
                                <date>May 2</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Francis</name> and <name type="person">Charles
                                    Holt</name> esqrs. and <name type="person">Charles Radcliff</name> to the same,
                                acquainting him that the house is finished, and desiring that the suit commenced against
                                them for non-performance of covenants may be staid. <name type="place">Rachdale</name>
                                <date>May 2</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="78" locusStart="443" locusEnd="443">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Hill</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Hill</name> to the same recommending a master
                                for the school at <name type="place">Rachdale</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="79" locusStart="444" locusEnd="444">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Memorandum of the delivery of the deeds concerning the foundation of the school at
                                    <name type="place">Rochdale</name> to <name type="place">Corpus Christi College
                                    Cambridge</name> and to the vicar and churchwardens of Rachdale</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Memorandum of the delivery of the deeds concerning the foundation of the said school
                                to <name type="place">Corpus Christi College Cambridge</name> and to the vicar and
                                churchwardens of Rachdale</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="80" locusStart="445" locusEnd="445">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Francis Holt</name>, <name type="author">Charles
                                    Holt</name> and <name type="author">Charles Radcliff</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name>
                                <date>Sept. 10</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Francis</name> and <name type="author">Charles
                                    Holt</name> esqrs. and <name type="author">Charles Radcliff</name> to the
                                archbishop, beseeching him to give directions for the delivery of the writings relating
                                to the school to them. <name type="place">Rachdale</name>
                                <date>Sept. 10</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="81" locusStart="446" locusEnd="446">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of attorney of the inhabitants of <name type="place">Rochdale</name>,
                                appointing <name type="person">James Wolfenden</name> and <name type="person">John
                                    Warberton</name> their attorneys, <date> May 30, 20 Eliz. </date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter of attorney of the inhabitants of <name type="place">Rachdale</name>,
                                appointing <name type="person">James Wolfenden</name> and <name type="person">John
                                    Warberton</name> their attorneys, <date> May 30, 20 Eliz. </date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 68-81 concerning <name type="place">Rochdale</name>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, p.
                                97</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="82" locusStart="447" locusEnd="448">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Commission of <name type="person">Henry VIII.</name> appointing <name type="person"
                                    >Dr. Parker</name> and others, visitors of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name>
                                <date>16 Jan. 37<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> regni</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Commission of <name type="person">Henry VIII.</name> appointing <name type="person"
                                    >Dr. Parker</name> and others, visitors of the university <date>16 Jan. 37<abbr
                                        rend="superscript">o</abbr> regni</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Commission of <name type="person">Henry VIII</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb 58</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> p. 34
                            note</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="83" locusStart="449" locusEnd="562">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Condition of several of the colleges of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Status omnium fere collegiorum in academia Cantabrigiensi, viz.</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="449">a. Rental of <name type="place">Corpus Christi</name></ab>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb 61</ref> (see below)</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>The accounts for the colleges follow item 86</supplied>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="489">b. Rental of <name type="place">Trinity Hall</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="497">c. <name type="place">Gunvil Hall</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="504">d. <name type="place">King's</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="504">e. <name type="place">Michael House</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="504">f. <name type="place">Queens'</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="504">g. <name type="place">St John's</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="505">h. <name type="place">Pembroke</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="513">i. <name type="place">Trinity</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="517">k. <name type="place">Peterhouse</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="525">l. <name type="place">Clare</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="533">m. Estates of <name type="place">King's</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="537">n. <name type="place">Jesus</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="543">o. <name type="place">Magdalene</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="549">Then a second summary account for all the Colleges, which is printed in <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, p. 61</ref>. This begins at p.
                            <locus>549</locus></ab>
                        <ab locus="559" locusNew="558a">A statement for <name type="place">Goneuill and Caius
                                College</name>, on two leaves</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>These accounts of the revenues and expences of the several colleges were taken at the
                                above visitation</quote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="84" locusStart="457" locusEnd="458">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Account of the report made to the king at court by Matthew Parker and others,
                                following a survey of the possessions of the <name type="place">University of
                                    Cambridge</name> and its colleges</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Account of what passed on the repair of the visitors of the university to
                                court</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb 59</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bruce and Perowne 1853"><hi rend="italic">Correspondence</hi> XXIV</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="85" locusStart="459" locusEnd="461">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Mandamus for electing <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name> master of <name
                                    type="place">Corpus Christi College</name>, <date> 36 Hen. VIII</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Mandamus for electing <name type="person">Dr. Parker</name> master of <name
                                    type="place">Corpus Christi College</name>, <date> 36 Hen. VIII</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="459">Leaf of a handsome service-book (written on one side only) enclosing
                                <supplied>items</supplied> no. 85, 86</ab>
                        <ab locus="461"> Mandamus </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, Appendix v</ref>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">Cf. <ref type="ms" target="CCC114">MS 114. 2</ref> (H. P.
                                S.)</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="86" locusStart="462" locusEnd="488">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>First delineation of the accounts of <name type="place">Corpus Christi College
                                    Cambridge</name> by <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Prima delineatio computi <name type="place">Coll. Corp. Christi</name> per <name
                                    type="person">Matthaeum Parker</name>, <date> I Edw. VI</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="462">Prima delineatio</rubric>
                        <ab locus="487">Other portion of leaf of service-book</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="87" locusStart="563" locusEnd="564">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A note of the principal matters concluded between the queen's majesty's commissioners
                                and the French in Scotland</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Note on the principall matters etc.: one leaf mutilated</ab>

                    </msItem>

                </msContents>

                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 26.11.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
