<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC122">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>122</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. 4</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Certificates and Returns of Livings of the Province of Canterbury</head>
                <head type="James">Certificates</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">315</height>
                        <width unit="mm">234</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">12.5 x 9</measureGrp>, <quote>seculo
                            <origDate>xvi</origDate></quote>.</p>



                <p>The Certificates described by Nasmith were partly in book-form, partly on rolls. All are now bound in
                    book-form in this volume and <ref type="ms" target="CCC097">MS 97</ref>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iii + pp. 1-54 + 57-124 + 124a-125a + 125-192 + 195-440 + ff. iv-v</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="eng" otherLangs="lat">English and Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="3" locusEnd="4">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">archbishop Parker</name> to the officials of the
                                bishop of _____, directing him to make the certificate of his diocese: dated <name
                                    type="place">Lambeth</name>
                                <date>Oct. 1, 1561</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker's Correspondence
                                CXI</ref> and <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins Concilia IV 227</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="5" locusEnd="178">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Returns for <name type="place">London</name> diocese including letter from Bishop
                                    <name type="author">John Scory</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Scory bishop of Hereford</name> sent with the
                                certificate of his diocese, in which he desires his cathedral church may be reformed,
                                dated <name type="place">Whitbourne</name>
                                <date>Feb. 1</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><name type="author">Scory</name>'s letter is included within the Returns for <name
                                type="place">London</name> Diocese</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype Parker I 190 (Chap. V)</ref>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="179" locusEnd="194">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Returns for <name type="place">Rochester</name> diocese</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Returns for <name type="place">Rochester</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="195" locusEnd="267">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Returns for <name type="place">Peterborough</name> diocese</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Returns for <name type="place">Peterborough</name></title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="287" locusEnd="290">

                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Letter from the Council to <name type="person">Parker</name>, asking for
                                returns</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the privy council to the <name type="person">archbishop of
                                    Canterbury</name>, requiring him speedily to send unto them a certificate of the
                                state of his diocese, dated <name type="place">Greenwich</name>
                                <date>9 July, 1563</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Correspondence CXXXIV</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="291" locusEnd="326">

                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Certificate and Returns for <name type="place">Canterbury</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Certificate of the <name type="person">archbishop of Canterbury</name> to the lords
                                of the privy council of the number, state and value of the churches within the <name
                                    type="place">diocese of Canterbury</name> A. D. <date>1563</date>. Certificate of
                                the vice-dean and prebendaries of <name type="place">Canterbury</name> of the uniformity
                                of that church</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="327" locusEnd="338">

                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Certificate and Returns for <name type="place">St Asaph</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Willis 1801">Browne Willis, St Asaph 1801 II 136</ref>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="339" locusEnd="352">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Anthony Kitchin</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name> and Returns of <name type="place">Llandaff</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Letter from Kitchin and Returns for <name type="place">Llandaff</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Kitchin bishop of Landaff</name> to the archbishop,
                                sent with the certificate of his diocese: dated <name type="place">Matherne</name>
                                <date>Jan. 20, 1560</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Willis 1719">Browne Willis, Llandaff</ref>, p. 194</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="353" locusEnd="431">

                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Returns of Livings above Ł30</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Names and values of all livings in each province above 30Ł. a year, and table of the
                                armour they were to furnish</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="357">
                            <name type="place">Winchester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="360">
                            <name type="place">Chichester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="361">
                            <name type="place">Exeter</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="370">
                            <name type="place">St Asaph</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="371">
                            <name type="place">Bangor</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="372">
                            <name type="place">Durham</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="374">
                            <name type="place">Gloucester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="375">
                            <name type="place">Canterbury</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="377">
                            <name type="place">Rochester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="377">
                            <name type="place">Chester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="381">
                            <name type="place">Carlisle</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="382">
                            <name type="place">Coventry and Lichfield</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="385">
                            <name type="place">Hereford</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="385">
                            <name type="place">Bristol</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="387">
                            <name type="place">Worcester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="388">
                            <name type="place">York</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="393">
                            <name type="place">St David's</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="394">
                            <name type="place">Norwich</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="397">
                            <name type="place">Ely</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="398">
                            <name type="place">London</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="403">
                            <name type="place">Bath and Wells</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="406">
                            <name type="place">Sarum</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="410">
                            <name type="place">Lincoln</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="417">
                            <name type="place">Peterborough</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="419">
                            <name type="place">Oxford</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="421">The names of all the dignities etc. in the Cathedral Church of <name
                                type="place">Bangor</name></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="433" locusEnd="434">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Covenant between the master and fellows of <name type="place">Michael House</name>
                                and <name type="person">John Mere</name> for building a wall, dated <date>13 March, 34
                                    Hen. VIII</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On vellum</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="435" locusEnd="436">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Peter Datheen</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Petri Datheni</name> comitis palatini legati ad
                                archiepiscopum in qua gratias agit pro munere sibi ab archiepiscopo oblato et mittit ei
                                numisma principis electoris, data <name type="place">Londini</name>
                                <date>24 Jan. 1574</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Correspondence CCCLXVI</ref>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="437" locusEnd="438">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> in reply to <name type="person"
                                    >Peter Datheen</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Responsio <name type="author">archiepiscopi</name>, data <name type="place"
                                    >Lambeth</name>
                                <date>9 kal. Feb. 1574</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Correspondence CCCLXVI</ref>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="439" locusEnd="440">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the city of <name type="place">Augsburg</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Martin Bucer</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola consulis et prefect. Augustae ad <name type="person">Bucerum</name>, in qua
                                queruntur de <name type="person">Magistro Ioanne Forster</name> concionatore suo</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>A Latin version of <ref type="ms" target="CCC119">MS 119. 3</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: KAW Summer 2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
