<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC134">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>134</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>P. 8</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>239</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Berengaudus, Expositio super septem uisiones libri Apocalypsis</head>
                <head type="James">Berengaudus Super Apocalypsim</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">315</height>
                        <width unit="mm">200</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">12.25 x 8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 170 + 3</extent>,
                        <layout>30 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xii</origDate>, <handNote>in more than one
                        very round and black hand</handNote>.</p>


                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num> i<num>8</num>-xiii<num>8</num> (3 canc.) xiv<num>8</num>-xvi<num>8</num>
                        (one canc.) xvii<num>8</num>-xxi<num>8</num> xxii<num>4</num> b<num>1</num></collation>.</p>

                <p><label>2 fo.:</label>
                    <secFol>at age penitentiam</secFol>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">The flyleaves <supplied>(<locus>iv</locus>-<locus>iiv</locus>,
                            <locus>iiir</locus>)</supplied> are fragments of an account roll. On the first, land
                        <q>iuxta <name type="place">Burghbrygg</name></q> is mentioned. On the second is the entry <q>de
                        manerio de <name type="place">Alwalton</name>.</q> On that at the end <q>ad Rectoriam de <name
                            type="place">Wermer</name>.</q> Alwalton suggests <name type="place">Peterborough</name>:
                    but <name type="place">Pentney</name> (see below) is also possible.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. aa-bb + a-b + i-ii + 1-170 + iii + c-d</foliation>.</p>

                <p function="Addition">On ff. <locus>1r</locus>-<locus>1v</locus> are two letters of <name type="author"
                        >Thomas Becket</name>
                    <handNote>in a hand of cent. <origDate>xii late or xiii early</origDate></handNote>.<lb/> 1. <name
                        type="author">T. dei gr. Cant. Arch.</name> etc. ven. fratri eadem gratia Norwic. episcopo
                    excommunicating <name type="person">Comes Hugo</name>, the <name type="person">Bishops of
                        London</name> and <name type="person">Sarum</name>, <name type="person">Thomas fil.
                        Bernard.</name>, <name type="person">Rand, de Broc</name>, <name type="person">Rodb. de
                        Broc</name> etc.<lb/> 2. <name type="person">Th. d. g. Cant. Arch.</name> etc. dilectis filiis
                    Canonicis Panteneiens. (? of <name type="place">Pentney in Norfolk</name>) excommunicating <name
                        type="person">Comes Hugo</name>.<lb/> A note: <q>Anno <name type="person">Greg. pape VI</name>.
                        in sancta synodo habitus est sermo de corpore et sang. Christi et diuersi diuersa sencientes. ut
                        habetur in registro Greg. primo folio. Denique <name type="person">Berengarius</name>
                    etc.</q></p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="2r" locusEnd="170v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Berengaudus</name>, <title>Expositio super septem uisiones libri
                                Apocalypsis</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="2r" rend="withinContents">At top, old title: <q><name type="author"
                                    >Berengaldus</name> super Apocalipsin</q></ab>

                        <rubric locus="2r">Incipit liber Apocalipsin. id est Revelationis</rubric>
                        <ab>(<decoNote>red capitals</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="2r">Apocalipsis Ihesu Christi etc.</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="2r">
                            <decoNote>Fine initial in red outline: grounds purple and yellow</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>(Text of Apoc. IIII)</ab>
                        <rubric locus="4v">Incipit expositio prime visionis in Apocalipsin</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="4v"><name type="person">Beatum Johannem</name> apostolum et
                            evangelistam</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Migne 017"><supplied>P. L.</supplied> XVII 765 (843)</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="4v">
                            <decoNote>Fine initial in red outline: yellow panelling: grotesque human figures</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The subsequent visions have plainer initials on red and green</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="170r">participes esse mereamur. qui cum patre et spiritu sancto uiuit et regnat
                            in secula seculorum. Amen</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="170r">Explicit expositio libri apocalipsis</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="170r">Quisquis nomen auctoris scire</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="170v">vel certe in melius commutandum</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="170v">Explicit liber</rubric>

                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 31/07/08</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
