<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC164">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>164</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>I. 4</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>98</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Ranulf Higden OSB, Polychronicon. Biblia pauperum etc.</head>
                <head type="James">R. Higden Polychronicon. Biblia Pauperum etc.</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">299</height>
                        <width unit="mm">202</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">11.5 x 8.1</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 1+ 42 + 18 + 34 +
                        2</extent>, <layout>four portions</layout> of cent. <origDate>xiv, xiii, xv</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Multivolume" rend="withinContents"><lb/><label>Volume I:</label> Cent. <origDate>xiv
                        late</origDate>, <handNote>well written</handNote>, <layout>39 lines to a page</layout>.
                        <lb/><label>Volume II:</label> Cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate>, <handNote>small
                    hands</handNote>: <layout>double columns of 55 etc. lines</layout>. <lb/><label>Volume III:</label>
                    A Biblia Pauperum, <decoNote>drawings in outline with washes of yellow, brown, red,
                        purple</decoNote>. Cent. <origDate>xv early</origDate>. <lb/><label>Volume IV:</label> Cent.
                        <origDate>xv</origDate>, <layout>double columns of 46 lines</layout>, <handNote>small
                        hand</handNote>.</p>



                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1 flyleaf, 1<num>8</num> 2<num>10</num> 3<num>8</num>-5<num>8</num> | A<num>12</num> (11,
                        12 canc.) B<num>8</num> || a<num>12</num> b<num>12</num> c<num>10</num> || d
                    (two)</collation>.</p>

                <p><label>2 fo.:</label>
                    <secFol>uocionis</secFol>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">At the bottom of f. <locus locusNew="1r">ir</locus> is:<lb/>
                    <q>liber m. <name type="person">Johannis Gunthorp decani Wellensis</name> emptus a <name
                            type="person">dauid lyenel</name>
                        <date>13<abbr rend="superscript">a</abbr> Julii a<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> vij<abbr
                                rend="superscript">o</abbr>
                            <name type="person">h(enrici)</name></date> vij<abbr rend="superscript">mi</abbr> pro
                            iiij<abbr rend="superscript">s</abbr> iiij<abbr rend="superscript">d</abbr>.</q><lb/>
                    <name type="person">Gunthorp</name> was a considerable collector of books. He was Dean of <name
                        type="place">Wells</name> and died in <date>1498</date>.</p>


                <p function="Additions"><supplied agent="NJM">(f. <locus>iv</locus>)</supplied> The flyleaf, of smaller
                    size than the rest, has a late list of contents.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i + 1-94 + ii-iii + c-d</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <milestone n="I" unit="volume"/>
                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="42v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Ranulf Higden OSB</name>, <title>Polychronicon (incomplete)</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="author">Ranulphi Higdeni</name> polychronici Lib. I. et pars 2ndi</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Prologue to <name type="author">Higden</name>'s <title>Polychronicon</title></ab>
                        <incipit locus="1r">Post preclaros arcium scriptores</incipit>
                        <ab locus="4r">This page is left blank for a <decoNote>large circular diagram of the
                                world</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="25r">The poem on <name type="place">Wales</name> is <layout>in triple
                                columns</layout></ab>
                        <ab>Liber II begins f. <locus>37v</locus>; ends f. <locus>42r</locus> with ch. vi</ab>
                        <explicit locus="42r"><name type="person">Ninus</name> et <name type="person">Semiramis</name>
                            ampliarunt</explicit>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Babington 1869">Rolls ed. II 250</ref>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="42v">blank: pencil note: <q>numerus fo. script. 41</q> (<origDate>xv</origDate>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="42v">
                            <decoNote>A sketch of a ship drawn with dry point</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>



                    <milestone n="II" unit="volume"/>
                    <msItem n="2.1" locusStart="43r" locusEnd="50v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Hugh of Fouilloy OSA</name>, <title>Auicularius (De auibus)</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Moralizationes avium</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>In hoc tractatu spatia ubique occurrunt vacua figuris avium ut videtur
                                designata</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <hi rend="bold">2a</hi>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Begins with a portion of an imperfect tract: about the Fall, and origin of Evil</ab>
                        <incipit locus="1r" locusNew="43r">Quod quia falsum est a deo hoc esse necesse est. Nam quia ab
                            alio hic sit quam a solo deo cum ex ipso auctore operis mali non sit</incipit>
                        <ab locus="1v" locusNew="43v">Ending unfinished</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="43v">cui omnis est subiecta ratio nature quam ut aiunt in muliere.
                            hoc</explicit>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>Change of hand</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <hi rend="bold">2b</hi>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="1v" locusNew="43v">Libellus cuiusdam ad Rainerum de tribus columbis: no title</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="43v">Desiderii tui karissime peticionibus satisfacere cupiens columbam cuius
                            penne etc.</incipit>
                        <ab>Another copy, illustrated, is at <ref type="ms" target="CSS100">Sidney Sussex College, no.
                                100</ref> in my Catalogue: another at <ref type="ms" target="LAML28">Sion College,
                                London</ref>. The tract not infrequently accompanies Bestiaries</ab>
                        <ab>Printed with the works of Hugo de S. Victore II 394</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Spaces are left here for 28 pictures</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Ends with a section on the eagle</ab>
                        <incipit locus="8v" locusNew="50r">Aquila uocata ab acumine oculorum</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="50v">dum se ipsum christo per bonam operationem conformem reddit</explicit>
                        <ab>As in the copy at <ref type="ms" target="LAML28">Sion College</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="2.2" locusStart="50v" locusEnd="50v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Cyprian of Carthage</name>, <title>De dominica oratione</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <hi rend="bold">2c</hi>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="8v" locusNew="50v">Ex tractatu <name type="person">beati cipriani martiris</name>
                            de oratione dominica</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="50v">Sit orantibus sermo et disciplina</incipit>
                        <ab>Followed by extracts from <name type="person">Jerome</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Augustine</name>, <name type="person">Gregory</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="50v" locusEnd="54r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Hugh of Fouilloy OSA</name>, <title>De rota praelationis</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Tractatus de rota fortunae; cum duabus illuminationibus ipsius rotae fraterculis
                                circumdatae, omni venustate denudatis</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="8v" locusNew="50v">Prologue (no title)</ab>
                        <incipit locus="8v" locusNew="50v">Sicut comperi non est tibi frater honerosum diu fuisse
                            discipulum</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="50v">rotam prelationis in capite presentis opusculi pingam</explicit>
                        <ab locus="9r" locusNew="51r">List of capitula (18). (1) de pictura rote; (2) de hiis que sunt
                            in rota; (3) de axe; (4) de modiolo etc.; (18) qualis debeat esse prelatus teste <name
                                type="person">beato Gregorio</name></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="51r">Uiri religiosi uita sicut rota uoluitur</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="51r">
                            <decoNote>Half the page is occupied by a picture of the wheel of Prelacy. At the top is
                                throned the Abbas with crosier: on each side is a monk turning the wheel by the tyre. At
                                bottom sits another with book on desk. All are in black habits. Many inscriptions in red
                                explain the picture. The twelve spokes of the wheel, and its other parts, symbolize
                                virtues</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="10v" locusNew="52v">The first part ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="10v" locusNew="52v">si culmen prelationis ascendere contradicat</explicit>
                        <ab locus="10v" locusNew="52v">Part II</ab>
                        <incipit locus="10v" locusNew="52v">Post rotam uere religionis locuturi sumus frater de rota
                            simulationis iob</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="52v">a legente facilius intelligi possint</explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="52v">Capitula (14). (1) de pictura rote...; (14) de circuitu rote</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="52v">
                            <decoNote>Half the page is occupied by a picture of the same character as before. Abbot at
                                top, monk in brown on L. in black on R., one at bottom sits dejected. These four are
                                respectively Honor possidentis, labor adquirendi, dolor amittentis, pudor nil habentis.
                                The parts of this wheel symbolize vices</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>The edges of 2 leaves following f. <locus locusNew="52v">12r</locus> are intrusive,
                            apparently</ab>
                        <ab>Text</ab>
                        <incipit locus="11r" locusNew="53r">(S)tatura rote similitudinem designat ypocrite</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="12r" locusNew="54r">Et hoc iterum de predictis rotis sufficiat donee de his
                            aliquis potiora dicat</explicit>
                        <ab>This text occurs, without the prologue, in <ref type="ms" target="OBL772">Bodl. MS. Digby
                                171 f. 71</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="54v" locusEnd="60v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Sermons</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Sermones in diversos festos</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="12v" locusNew="54v">Sermons</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="54v">Sufficit tamen de una uirgine loqui uerum</incipit>
                        <ab>Treats of various classes of feasts</ab>
                        <incipit locus="14v" locusNew="56v">Sapientia edificauit sibi domum</incipit>
                        <incipit locus="17v" locusNew="59v">Adorna thalamum</incipit>
                        <incipit locus="18r" locusNew="60r">Septuagessima in alterius rei memoriam</incipit>
                        <incipit locus="18v" locusNew="60v">Vi(n)centi dabo manna absconditum</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="60v">Pencil note. <q>Numerus fo. script. 18</q></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <milestone n="III" unit="volume"/>
                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="61r" locusEnd="94v">
                        <head type="CCC">

                            <title>Biblia pauperum</title>

                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Delineationes historiarum veteris et novi testamenti numero XCVII haud inelegantes,
                                coloribus leviter tinctae</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The pictures (lacunae excepted) exactly coincide with a set in <ref type="ms"
                                    target="LBLK05">British Museum (King's MS. 5)</ref> of Flemish (Dutch) work, very
                                finely coloured. The arrangement in the copy before us is peculiar. The two types are on
                                the Left page one above the other; the antitype on Right page with four busts of
                                prophets bearing scrolls: <figure xml:id="figure372a"/></decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>The text on the Left page is a brief explanation of the type, beginning: <q>Legitur [Gen.
                                cap. xxix<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr>] quod...</q></ab>
                        <ab>On the Right page are usually three verses, e.g. for Epiphany</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="63r">
                            <lg>
                                <l>Plebs notat hec gentes christo iungi cupientes.</l>
                                <l>Christus adoratur aurum thus mirra letatur.</l>
                                <l>Hoc tipice gentem notat ad christum uenientem,</l>
                            </lg>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>of which the 1st and 3rd refer to the types and the 2nd to the antitype</ab>
                        <ab>A reduced facsimile of two pages is given in <ref type="bibl" target="CAS 1893">Camb. Ant.
                                Soc. Proceedings Vol. VII, pi. xii</ref></ab>
                        <ab>The British Museum MS. has its pictures arranged as a series of triptychs</ab>
                        <ab>I give a list of the subjects, with notes from the <ref type="ms" target="LBLK05">British
                                Museum MS.</ref>, which I will call k</ab>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">1</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab>The types are gone: in k they are the Fall and <name type="person">Gideon</name>'s
                                Fleece</ab>
                            <ab locus="1r" locusNew="61r">Annunciation</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">2</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="1v" locusNew="61v">Burning Bush. <name type="person">Aaron</name>'s Rod</ab>
                            <ab locus="2r" locusNew="62r">Nativity</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">3</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="2v" locusNew="62v"><name type="person">Abner</name> comes to <name type="person"
                                    >David</name>, <name type="person">Queen of Sheba</name></ab>
                            <ab locus="3r" locusNew="63r">Adoration of the Magi</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">4</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="3v" locusNew="63v">Purification of women. <name type="person">Hannah</name>
                                offers <name type="person">Samuel</name></ab>
                            <ab locus="4r" locusNew="64r">Presentation of <name type="person">Christ</name>: 4 is
                                wanting in k</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">5</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="4v" locusNew="64v">Flight of <name type="person">Jacob</name> from <name
                                    type="person">Esau</name>. <name type="person">David</name> let down from
                                window</ab>
                            <ab locus="5r" locusNew="65r">Flight into <name type="place">Egypt</name></ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">6</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="5v" locusNew="65v"><name type="person">Moses</name> destroys the Golden Calf.
                                Dagon falls (Two priests carry a jewelled shrine: two images fall)</ab>
                            <ab locus="6r" locusNew="66r">Idols of Egypt fall. (<name type="person">Joseph</name>, and
                                    <name type="person">Mary</name> on the ass, enter on left)</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">7</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="6v" locusNew="66v"><name type="person">Abraham</name> and the three Angels. The
                                Three Children in the Furnace</ab>
                            <ab locus="7r" locusNew="67r">The Transfiguration. 7 is wanting in k.</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">8</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="7v" locusNew="67v"><name type="person">Nathan</name> convicts <name type="person"
                                    >David</name>. <name type="person">Miriam</name> smitten with leprosy</ab>
                            <ab locus="8r" locusNew="68r"><name type="person">Magdalene</name> washes <name
                                    type="person">Christ</name>'s feet</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">9</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="8v" locusNew="68v"><name type="person">Darius</name> bids <name type="person"
                                    >Ezra</name> build the Temple. <name type="person">Judas Maccabaeus</name> cleanses
                                the Temple</ab>
                            <ab locus="9r" locusNew="69r"><name type="person">Christ</name> cleanses the Temple</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">10</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="9v" locusNew="69v"><name type="person">Elisha</name> (<name type="person"
                                    >Elijah</name>) raises the widow's son. <name type="person">Elisha</name> stretches
                                himself on the Shunammite's son</ab>
                            <ab locus="10r" locusNew="70r">Raising of <name type="person">Lazarus</name></ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">11</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="10v" locusNew="70v"><name type="person">Judith</name>'s return with <name
                                    type="person">Holofernes</name>' head. Sons of the prophets meet <name type="person"
                                    >Elisha</name></ab>
                            <ab locus="11r" locusNew="71r">Entry into Jerusalem</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">12</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="11v" locusNew="71v"><name type="person">Melchizedek</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Abraham</name>. The Manna</ab>
                            <ab locus="12r" locusNew="72r">The Last Supper</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">13</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="12v" locusNew="72v"><name type="person">Joseph</name> sold to the Ishmaelites.
                                    <name type="person">Joseph</name> sold to <name type="person">Potiphar</name></ab>
                            <ab locus="13r" locusNew="73r"><name type="person">Judas</name> and the Priests</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">14</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="13v" locusNew="73v"><name type="person">Joab</name> kills <name type="person"
                                    >Abner</name>. <name type="person">Tryphon</name> betrays Jews</ab>
                            <ab locus="14r" locusNew="74r">The Betrayal</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">15</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="14v" locusNew="74v"><name type="person">Jezebel</name> slays prophets. <name
                                    type="person">Daniel</name> cast into the den</ab>
                            <ab locus="15r" locusNew="75r">Dampnacio <name type="person">Christi</name> ad mortem (<name
                                    type="person">Pilate</name> washing his hands)</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">16</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="15v" locusNew="75v"><name type="person">Joseph</name> stripped by his brothers.
                                    <name type="person">Absalom</name> conspires against <name type="person"
                                    >David</name></ab>
                            <ab locus="16r" locusNew="76r">Conspiracio in mortem <name type="person">Christi</name>
                                (Jews on Right <name type="person">Christ</name> bound on Left)</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">17</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="16v" locusNew="76v">Shame of <name type="person">Noah</name>. <name type="person"
                                    >Elisha</name> mocked</ab>
                            <ab locus="17r" locusNew="77r"><name type="person">Christ</name> mocked and crowned with
                                thorns</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">18</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="17v" locusNew="77v"><name type="person">Isaac</name> carries the wood. <name
                                    type="person">Elijah</name> and the widow with two sticks</ab>
                            <ab locus="18r" locusNew="78r">Bearing the Cross</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">19</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="18v" locusNew="78v">Sacrifice of <name type="person">Isaac</name>. Brazen
                                serpent</ab>
                            <ab locus="19r" locusNew="79r">Crucifixion</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">20</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="19v" locusNew="79v">Creation of <name type="person">Eve</name>. Rock smitten</ab>
                            <ab locus="20r" locusNew="80r">The side pierced</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">21</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="20v" locusNew="80v"><name type="person">Joseph</name> put in the pit. <name
                                    type="person">Jonah</name> cast overboard</ab>
                            <ab locus="21r" locusNew="81r">The Entombment</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">22</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="21v" locusNew="81v"><name type="person">Samson</name> carries the gates. <name
                                    type="person">Jonah</name> cast up</ab>
                            <ab locus="22r" locusNew="82r">The Resurrection</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">23</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="22v" locusNew="82v"><name type="person">David</name> kills <name type="person"
                                    >Goliath</name>. <name type="person">Samson</name> rends the lion</ab>
                            <ab locus="23r" locusNew="83r">Harrowing of Hell</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">24</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="23v" locusNew="83v"><name type="person">Reuben</name> finds the pit empty. The
                                spouse in Canticles finds the bedchamber empty</ab>
                            <ab locus="24r" locusNew="84r">The Women at the Sepulchre</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">25</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="24v" locusNew="84v"><name type="person">Habakkuk</name> brought to <name
                                    type="person">Daniel</name> finds him alive in the den. The spouse in Canticles
                                finds her beloved</ab>
                            <ab locus="25r" locusNew="85r">Noli me tangere (<name type="person">Christ</name> has the
                                spade)</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">26</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="25v" locusNew="85v"><name type="person">Joseph</name> makes himself known (the
                                brethren are in a ship). So also in k. The Prodigal's return (the fatted calf slain: a
                                man sharpening his knife)</ab>
                            <ab locus="26r" locusNew="86r"><name type="person">Christ</name> appears to the Virgin and
                                Apostles</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">27</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="26v" locusNew="86v"><name type="person">Gideon</name> and the angel. <name
                                    type="person">Jacob</name> wrestles with the angel</ab>
                            <ab locus="27r" locusNew="87r">Incredulity of <name type="person">Thomas</name></ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">28</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="27v" locusNew="87v"><name type="person">Enoch</name> translated. <name
                                    type="person">Elijah</name> translated</ab>
                            <ab locus="28r" locusNew="88r">Ascension</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">29</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="28v" locusNew="88v">Giving of the Law. <name type="person">Elijah</name>'s
                                sacrifice: fire descends</ab>
                            <ab locus="29r" locusNew="89r">Pentecost</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">30</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="29v" locusNew="89v"><name type="person">Bathsheba</name> seated by <name
                                    type="person">Solomon</name>. <name type="person">Esther</name> seated by <name
                                    type="person">Ahasuerus</name></ab>
                            <ab locus="30r" locusNew="90r">Coronation of the Virgin</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">31</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="30v" locusNew="90v">Judgment of <name type="person">Solomon</name>. The Amalekite
                                slain (2 Sam. i)</ab>
                            <ab locus="31r" locusNew="91r">Last Judgment</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">32</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="31v" locusNew="91v"><name type="person">Job</name> and his children feasting.
                                    <name type="person">Jacob</name>'s ladder</ab>
                            <ab locus="32r" locusNew="92r">Gaudia bonorum. The Heavenly Palace with a crowned head at
                                each window</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <seg>
                            <ab>
                                <hi rend="bold">33</hi>
                            </ab>
                            <ab locus="32v" locusNew="92v"><name type="person">Dathan</name> and <name type="person"
                                    >Abiram</name> swallowed up (standing in earth up to their knees). <name
                                    type="place">Sodom</name> and <name type="place">Gomorrah</name> destroyed</ab>
                            <ab locus="33r" locusNew="93r">Pena dampnatorum. Souls and devils in Hell mouth</ab>
                        </seg>
                        <ab locus="33v" locusNew="93v">On this page a pencil note. Numerus fo. pict. 33. Numerus fo.
                            script, et pict. totius libri 92</ab>
                        <ab>ff. <locus locusNew="94r">34r</locus>-<locus locusNew="94v">34v</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>



                    <milestone n="IV" unit="volume"/>
                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="iir" locusEnd="iiiv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">François de Meyronnes OFM</name>, <title>Moralia siue Liber de
                                uirtutibus (excerpt)</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Fragmentum sermonis</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="James">
                            <title>The Moralia of <name type="author">Fr. de Mayronis</name>, imperfect</title>
                        </head>
                        <incipit locus="iir">Auditu auris audiui te etc. quia uero audicio diuina pertinet
                            etc.</incipit>
                        <ab>See <ref type="ms" target="OME201">MS. Merton College, Oxford 201. 1</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 28/11/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
