<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC168">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>168</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. Y</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Documents Relating to Bishop Cox of Ely</head>
                <head type="James">Documents Relating to Bp Cox of Ely</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">300</height>
                        <width unit="mm">209</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">11.7 x 8.5</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. circa 200</extent>, many
                    blank. Cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate>, <handNote>in various hands</handNote>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance"><name type="person">Stanley</name> is responsible for calling this volume <hi
                        rend="italic">Misc</hi>. Y, and he is wrong. <name type="person">Parker</name>'s own <hi
                        rend="italic">Misc</hi>. Y, which contained chiefly medical tracts, is lost, and the present
                    volume was given by <name type="person">Dr J. Jegon</name>, Master from <date>1590 to
                    1602</date>.</p>
                <p function="Provenance">
                    <supplied>A note on the first page (f.<locus>viiir</locus>) reads:</supplied>
                    <quote>
                        <q>This booke conteyninge some fragments of that excellent man <name type="person">Richard
                                Cox</name> bishoppe of Elie, <name type="person">Roger Cox</name> sonne to the B. gave
                            to me <name type="person">J. Jegon</name>.</q>
                    </quote>
                </p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-viii + 1-38 + 38a + 39-210 + ix-x</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="56r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The location of places derived from the church fathers and others</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Loci communes ex patribus, &amp;c. collecti</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Collected from Fathers and medieval writers</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="56v" locusEnd="63v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Notes on church history <date>603</date> AD - <date>1509</date> AD</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Notae historicae ordine chronologico dispositae de rebus ecclesiasticis ab anno
                                    <date>603</date> ad annum <date>1509</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Mostly on the Popes</ab>

                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="64r" locusEnd="66v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws of <name type="person">Cnut</name>, <name type="person">Ethelred</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Edgar</name>, <name type="person">Edmund</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >Athelstan</name>, <name type="person">Ine</name> and <name type="person"
                                    >Alfred</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges <name type="person">Canuti</name>, <name type="person">Ethelredi</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Edgari</name>, <name type="person">Edmundi</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >Adelstani</name>, <name type="person">Inae</name> et <name type="person"
                                    >Aluredi</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>(4 pp.) called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (p. xxii)</ref>
                            <hi rend="italic">Corpus</hi></ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="67r" locusEnd="102v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Poems on the butcher of <name type="place">Paris</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carmina in Lanienam Parisiensem</title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locusNew="67r">In perfidiam et crudelitatem quam <name type="person">Carolus nonus
                                Galliae Rex</name> in Christianos exercuit</rubric>
                        <ab>A series of 8 Latin poems: the first begins</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="67r">
                            <lg>
                                <l>Fama fuit Moscum furiis urgentibus arma</l>
                                <l>Aduersus ciues expediisse suos</l>
                            </lg>
                        </incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="72r">Two pages, one with swan-marks (?) of <name type="person">Roger</name>, <name
                                type="person">Richard</name>, <name type="person">John</name>, <name type="person">Jane
                                Cox</name>, <name type="person">Eliz. Whithed</name>, and <name type="person"
                                >Brame</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="73r">The other with miscellaneous notes</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="73v">27 blank leaves</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="103r" locusEnd="103r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Bishop Cox of Ely</name> exhorting the parishioners of
                                every parish to be charitable to their poor neighbours: dated <name type="place"
                                    >Dodington</name>
                                <date>12 July, 1569</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter exhorting the parishioners of every parish to be charitable to their poor
                                neighbours, sent by order of council: dated <name type="place">Dodington</name>
                                <date>12 July, 1569</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 5-11 occupy 5 pp.</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="103r" locusEnd="103r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Bishop Cox of Ely</name> to the ministers of every
                                parish to certify the names of those that refuse to come to church and receive the
                                sacraments: dated <name type="place">Somersham</name>
                                <date>13 November 1569</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter to the ministers of every parish to certify unto him the names of those that
                                refuse to come to church and receive the sacraments, sent by order of council: dated
                                    <name type="place">Somersham</name>
                                <date>13 November 1569</date></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="103v" locusEnd="103v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Bishop Cox of Ely</name> enjoining the ministers to use
                                only the catechism set forth in the book of service, dated <name type="place"
                                    >Somersham</name>
                                <date>7 August 1572</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter enjoining the ministers to use only the catechism set forth in the book of
                                service, and to certify unto him quarterly the names of such parents as refuse
                                permitting their children to learn it, dated <name type="place">Somersham</name>
                                <date>7 August 1572</date></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="103v" locusEnd="103v">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter to the churchwardens of a parish to take down their roode-loft and
                                superstitious dome, dated <name type="place">Somersham</name>
                                <date>16 December 1572</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The <q>superstitious dome</q> is most likely a picture of the Doom or Last Judgment. <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Gorham. Gorham and Bird 1857">Gorham, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Gleanings</hi> p. 452</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="104r" locusEnd="104r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Bishop Cox of Ely</name> to the ministers of his
                                diocese to be diligent in catechising, dated <name type="place">Ely-palace</name>
                                <date>March 1, 1572</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter to the ministers of his diocese to be diligent in catechising, dated <name
                                    type="place">Ely-palace</name>
                                <date>March 1, 1572</date></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="104r" locusEnd="104v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the council to <name type="person">Bishop cox of Ely</name>, requiring
                                him to enforce the observance of uniformity in religion thro' his diocese, dated <name
                                    type="place">Greenwich</name>
                                <date>7 November 1573</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the council to the bishop, requiring him to enforce the observance of
                                uniformity in religion thro' his diocese, dated <name type="place">Greenwich</name>
                                <date>7 November 1573</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins, <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV
                                279</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="105r" locusEnd="115v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Cox, bishop of Ely</name> to the several
                                parishes to enforce the observance of uniformity in religion</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the bishop to the several parishes on this occasion</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locusNew="105v">Blank leaves</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="116r" locusEnd="117r">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Prayers for the beginning of every year in the queen's reign</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 12-15 occupy 5 pp.</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="117r" locusEnd="117r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Coronation oath</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Juramentum regis quando coronatur</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="117r" locusEnd="117r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>A prayer for the beginning of every year in the queen's reign</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Another prayer for the beginning of every year in the queen's reign</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="117v" locusEnd="119v">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Prayers against the adversaries of the godley</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="16" locusStart="120r" locusEnd="161v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Form and order of the psalmes</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The forme and order of the psalmes as they were used to be songe in the house of the
                                late right reverend father <name type="person">Richard Cox sometime L. B. of
                                Ely</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Metrical Psalms</title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locusNew="120r">Munday morning Psal. 1</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="120r">That man is bleste that hath not gone etc.</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="122v">Ends with Thursday morning</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="123r">Blank leaves</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="17" locusStart="162r" locusEnd="170v">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Lists of fairs</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Occupies 9 ff.</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="18" locusStart="171r" locusEnd="173v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Epitaph of pope <name type="person">Sixtus V</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epitaphia <name type="person">papae Sixti</name></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="19" locusStart="174r" locusEnd="194r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Historical notes beginning in <date>1558</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Notae historicae incipientes A. D. <date>1558</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Scattered over several leaves: may be of interest</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="20" locusStart="194v" locusEnd="199v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Poems in Latin and English</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carmina Latina et Anglicana</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Includes several poems to <name type="person">Queen Elizabeth</name>, an epitaph for <name
                                type="person">Richard Cox</name> etc.</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="21" locusStart="200r" locusEnd="200r">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Verses written by a prisoner, signed C. <q>Like as the byrde in the cage
                                enclosed</q></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locusNew="200r">Signed <name type="author">R. or P.
                                &#964;&#949;&#955;&#959;&#962;</name></ab>
                        <ab>21-24 (4) are in one good hand</ab>

                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="22" locusStart="200v" locusEnd="201v">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Verses in praise of retirement signed C. W. <q>Myne owne <name type="person">Ihon
                                        Poyntz</name> sins ye delite to know</q></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locusNew="201v">Signed <name type="author">R. W.</name></ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="23" locusStart="201v" locusEnd="203v">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Proverbs</title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locusNew="201v">Many a man makes Ryme and lokes to no reason</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="203v">Before 24 is a theological extract in Latin</ab>

                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="24" locusStart="204r" locusEnd="208v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>English verses</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>English verses with the following burdens</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>(1)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="204r">
                            <lg>
                                <l>Hold back thy tonge at meat and meal;</l>
                                <l>Speake but few wordes, bestow them well</l>
                            </lg>
                        </incipit>
                        <ab>(2)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="204v">
                            <lg>
                                <l>The black shepe is a perylous beast,</l>
                                <l>Cujus contrarium falsum est</l>
                            </lg>
                        </incipit>
                        <ab>(3)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="205r">
                            <lg>
                                <l>Say well and do well they are things twayne;</l>
                                <l>Thryse happye is he, in whom both raygne</l>
                            </lg>
                        </incipit>
                        <ab>(4)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="205v">
                            <lg>
                                <l>My derlyng dere long have I sowght,</l>
                                <l>Lost is my labour, she is clere nowght</l>
                            </lg>
                        </incipit>
                        <ab>(5)</ab>

                        <incipit locusNew="207v">
                            <lg>
                                <l>Lorde wounde my fleasshe with thy feare</l>
                                <l>For I feare thy judgements</l>
                            </lg>
                        </incipit>

                        <ab>(6)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="208r">
                            <lg>
                                <l>For he that by wyll doth rule his witte</l>
                                <l>Doth oftymes loose when he shulde knitte</l>
                            </lg>
                        </incipit>


                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">These verses were printed in the <ref type="bibl"
                                    target="Goodwin 1844">Percy Society's publications (H. P. S.), vol. XIII, no. 50,
                                    1844, by James Goodwin</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="25" locusStart="209r" locusEnd="210r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Speech of <name type="person">Cromwell earl of Essex</name> at his execution</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Speech as I conjecture of <name type="person">Cromwell earl of Essex</name> at his
                                execution</title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locusNew="209r">Masters I am come hither to dye</incipit>
                        <ab>(2 pp.)</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="26" locusStart="210v" locusEnd="210v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Prayer to be said before the Mass</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Oratio dicenda ante missam</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 26, 27. On one page, the last</ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="27" locusStart="210v" locusEnd="210v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Indulgence granted to the confraternity of St Christopher and St George in the <name
                                    type="place">city of York</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Indulgentia concessa confraternitati S. Christophori et Georgii in <name type="place"
                                    >civitate Eboraci</name></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 5/12/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
