<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC173">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>173</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>S. 11</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>269</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">The Parker Chronicle</head>
                <head type="James">Anglo-Saxon Chronicle. Anglo-Saxon Laws. Sedulius</head>


                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">290</height>
                        <width unit="mm">210</width>
                    </measureGrp>, Volume I: <measureGrp type="James">11.3 x 8.3</measureGrp>, Volume II: <measureGrp
                        type="James">11.1 x 8.2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 56 + 27</extent>, <layout>two
                    volumes</layout>: I, cent. <origDate>ix-xi</origDate>; II, cent. <origDate>viii-ix</origDate>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label><lb/>
                    <label>Volume I:</label>
                    <collation>1<num>8</num> (wants 1) 2<num>10</num> (1 canc., 8 canc.: one added) | 3<num>10</num> (3
                        and 7 canc., 10* added) 4<num>8</num> (wants 8) | 5<num>10</num> (1 canc.) 6 [marked
                            E]<num>14</num> (3, 5, 9 canc.) 7<num>4</num> (4 somewhat
                        cut)</collation>.<lb/><label>Volume II:</label>
                    <collation>A<num>2</num> B<num>10</num> C<num>8</num> D<num>8</num> (wants 8)</collation>.<lb/><hi
                        rend="italic">New Pal Soc</hi>.: <collation>1<num>8</num> (wants 1) 2<num>10</num> (one canc., 7
                        added) 3<num>8</num> (+1) 4<num>8</num> (wants 8)</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">Volume I: It was in the Library of <name type="place">Christ Church,
                        Canterbury</name>, no. 311 in <name type="person">Prior Eastry</name>'s Catalogue (<ref
                        type="bibl" target="James 1903"><hi rend="italic">Ancient Libraries</hi>, pp. xxvi, 509</ref>).
                    The first leaf with press-mark etc. has disappeared since Parker's time<hi rend="footnote">The first
                        remaining page is numbered 3 by <name type="person">Parker</name>.</hi>. It appears to have been
                    written at <name type="place">Winchester</name> down to the year <date>1001</date>, and thereafter
                    at <name type="place">Christ Church, Canterbury</name>. <name type="person">Professor Earle</name>
                    suggested that it was transferred from Winchester to Canterbury when the monks at the latter place
                    were endeavouring to repair the losses in their library caused by the fire of <date>1067</date>
                        (<ref type="bibl" target="Plummer 1892">Plummer, p. xxv note</ref>). Another possibility (<ref
                        type="bibl" target="NPS 1907">
                        <hi rend="italic">New Pal. Soc.</hi>
                    </ref>) is that <name type="person">&#198;lfheah, bishop of Winchester</name>, may have brought
                    it with him when he became archbishop in <date>1006</date>.<lb/> At the Dissolution the volume came
                    into the hands of <name type="person">Dr Nicholas Wotton the first Dean of Canterbury</name>, who
                    gave it to Parker. See <ref type="bibl" target="Plummer 1892">
                        <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi>
                    </ref>.<lb/></p>

                <p function="Additions">The contents of the first volume are briefly these:<lb/> Chronicle, ff.
                        <locus>1r</locus>-<locus>32r</locus>.<lb/> Latin Acts of <name type="person">Lanfranc</name>, f.
                        <locus>32r</locus>-<locus>32v</locus>.<lb/> Laws, ff.
                    <locus>33r</locus>-<locus>52v</locus>.<lb/> Lists of proper bishops etc. ff.
                        <locus>53r</locus>-<locus>55v</locus> (f. <locus>56r</locus>, <locus>56v</locus> blank.)</p>

                <p function="Additions">A <origDate>xiiith cent.</origDate> scribble on the 2nd leaf of the Chronicle,
                    another on f. <locus>55v</locus>, and two others on ff. <locus locusNew="82r">26r</locus> and <locus
                        locusNew="83v">27v</locus> of the Sedulius, seem to me to be all in one hand. If so, the two
                    portions have long been bound together</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-ii + 1-83 + iii-iv</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="ang" otherLangs="lat">Old English and Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <milestone n="I" unit="volume"/>
                    <msItem n="1.1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="32r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle, A-version, preceded by the West-Saxon Royal
                                Genealogy</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>The most recent edition is that of the <name type="person">Rev. C. Plummer</name>, M.A.,
                            Corpus Christi College, Oxford (<ref type="bibl" target="Plummer 1892">vol. I, 1892</ref>,
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Plummer 1899">II, 1899</ref>). His symbol for this MS. is
                            &#256;. He describes it fully at p. xxiii sqq. of vol. II</ab>
                        <ab>Facsimiles in <ref type="bibl" target="Petrie 1848"><hi rend="italic">Mon. Hist. Brit.</hi>
                                pl. xxiii, xxiv</ref> and <ref type="bibl" target="NPS 1907"><hi rend="italic">New Pal.
                                    Soc.</hi> pls. 134-136</ref></ab>
                        <ab>On previous editions of the text see <ref type="bibl" target="Plummer 1892">Plummer's <hi
                                    rend="italic">Introduction</hi></ref></ab>

                        <ab>The Chronicle, <layout>mostly in single columns</layout> except f. <locus>1v</locus> (part)
                            to f. <locus>4v</locus> sub fin. where it is <layout>in double columns: number of lines
                                varying from 39 to 25</layout></ab>
                        <ab>A complete survey of the hands in which this is written is given by <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Plummer 1892">Plummer, p. xxv, § 13</ref> and in the <ref type="bibl"
                                target="NPS 1907">
                                <hi rend="italic">New Pal. Soc.</hi>
                            </ref><lb/> Plummer's list summarized is as follows:<lb/> 1. To the end of f.
                                <locus>16r</locus> death of <name type="person">Suibhne</name> in <date>891</date>, and
                            the year-number <date>892</date>.<lb/> 2. f. <locus>16v</locus> including part of
                                <date>894</date> (to Ac hi haefdon).<lb/> 3. f.
                            <locus>17r</locus>-<locus>17v</locus>.<lb/> 4. f. <locus>18r</locus> to f.
                                <locus>21r</locus> sub fin. (end of <date>912</date>).<lb/> 5. f. <locus>21r</locus> sub
                            fin. to f. <locus>24v</locus> sub fin. (end of <date>921</date>) except three lines on f.
                                <locus>28v</locus>.<lb/> 6. Three lines on f. <locus>23v</locus> (gefaran mehte ...
                            abraecon), four lines on f. <locus>24v</locus> (beginning of <date>922</date>): apparently
                            more, now erased and re-written on f. <locus>23v</locus>. A poor scribe.<lb/> 7. f.
                                <locus>25r</locus>-<locus>25v</locus> to end of <date>924</date>, half of f.
                                <locus>25v</locus> left blank.<lb/> 8. f. <locus>26r</locus> to f. <locus>27v</locus>,
                            end of <date>955</date>.<lb/> 9. f. <locus>28r</locus> and year-number <date>968</date> on
                            f. <locus>28v</locus>.<lb/> 10. f. <locus>28v</locus> to f. <locus>30r</locus> sub fin., end
                            of <date>1001</date>, except the last ten words.<lb/> So far the <name type="place"
                                >Winchester</name> portion.<lb/> 11. (Year-numbers on f. <locus>30r</locus>?) f.
                                <locus>30v</locus> to f. <locus>31v</locus>, end of <date>1066</date>, except the last
                            sentence about the comet and the fragmentary charter at <date>1031</date>.<lb/> 12. f.
                                <locus>31v</locus> last sentence of <date>1066</date> and first part of
                                <date>1070</date> to gehersumnesse mid a&#240;swerunge.<lb/> 13. The charter at
                                <date>1031</date> and the remainder of <date>1070</date>.<lb/> 14. The Latin Acts of
                                <name type="person">Lanfranc</name> and some of the lists of bishops etc.</ab>
                        <ab>There are also numerous interpolations, most of them by the scribe 14 who is also according
                            to <ref type="bibl" target="Plummer 1892">Mr Plummer</ref> the scribe of <ref type="ms"
                                target="LBLCD8">Domitian A. VIII (the Latin-Saxon Chronicle called F)</ref>. Others
                            are:<lb/> The annals <date>710</date> accidentally omitted, supplied by scribe 8.<lb/>
                            Additions at <date>923</date> and <date>941</date> by no. 11 (a <name type="place"
                                >Christchurch</name> hand).<lb/> Additions relating to <name type="person"
                                >Dunstan</name> at <date>925</date> (first part), <date>943</date>, <date>956</date>,
                                <date>959</date>, <date>961</date>, by no. 12.<lb/> Early additions at
                            (<date>688</date>), <date>728</date>, <date>870</date>, <date>890</date>, <date>993</date>,
                                <date>1001</date>.<lb/> At <date>988</date> is a
                                <handNote>beautifully-written</handNote> small Latin note on the death of <name
                                type="person">Dunstan</name>.<lb/> The hands were dated as follows by <ref type="bibl"
                                target="NPS 1907">Dr G. F. Warner (l. c. p. xxvii note)</ref>. Nos. 1-6
                                <date>900-930</date>; no. 7 <date>cir. 930</date>; no. 8 <date>cir. 960</date>; no. 10
                                <date>cir. 1000</date>; no. 11 <date>cir. 1075</date>.<lb/> For remarks on the character
                            and affinities of the script, the description in <ref type="bibl" target="NPS 1907">
                                <hi rend="italic">New Pal. Soc.</hi>
                            </ref> should be consulted</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="RJR"><ref type="bibl" target="Cameron 1973">Cameron B17.1</ref>,
                                incorporating the Chronicle poems <ref type="bibl" target="Cameron 1973">Cameron
                                    A10.1-4</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="1.2" locusStart="32r" locusEnd="32v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Acta Lanfranci</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>The Latin Acts of <name type="author">Lanfranc</name> are printed by <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Plummer 1892">Plummer, vol. I, App. B, pp. 287-292</ref>. In the MS. this
                            Parkerian note is prefixed to them in the margin</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="32r">hec habentur in libro S. Aug. cui titulus est Diversi tractatus monasterii S.
                            Augustini</ab>
                        <ab>The book here mentioned was formerly in <name type="person">Parker</name>'s possession, but
                            is marked in his Register as missing at the time when the collection was bequeathed to the
                            College. It is now <ref type="ms" target="LAM213">MS. 1213 in the Lambeth Library</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="33r" locusEnd="52v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Anglo-Saxon Laws of <name type="person">Alfred</name> and <name type="person"
                                    >Ine</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>The next two quires containing the Laws are <handNote>apparently all in one hand</handNote>,
                            with <layout>25 lines to a page</layout></ab>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann, <hi rend="italic">Gesetze</hi> p.
                                xxiv</ref>, calls this MS. E, and assigns it to <date>cir. 925</date>. It is the oldest
                            of his authorities. Text, p. 16</ab>
                        <ab>The writer in <ref type="bibl" target="NPS 1907">
                                <hi rend="italic">New Pal. Soc.</hi>
                            </ref> speaks of the writing as <q>rounded English minuscules of the eleventh
                            century</q></ab>
                        <ab locus="33r">The capitula occupy ff. <locus>33r</locus>-<locus>35r</locus></ab>
                        <ab locus="35v">blank</ab>
                        <ab locus="36r"> Laws of <name type="person">Alfred</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="39v">
                            <supplied>Laws</supplied> of <name type="person">Ine</name>
                        </ab>
                        <!--<ab>Neumes at end on f. <locus>52v</locus></ab>-->
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="RJR">
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Cameron 1973">Cameron B14.4</ref>
                            </supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="53r" locusEnd="56v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Lists of popes and English bishops</title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locus="53r">Incipiunt nomina pontificum romane urbis</rubric>
                        <ab>The names as far as <name type="person">Damasus</name> are in one hand: from Damasus to
                                <name type="person">Julius</name> in a second hand, and from <name type="person"
                                >Liberius</name> (lx) to <name type="person">Marinus</name> (cxxxv—the numbers being
                            continued to clxx) in a hand which may be that of the Latin on f. <locus>32r</locus> (Acts
                            of Lanfranc)</ab>
                        <ab>Two blank pages follow (ff. <locus>53v</locus>, <locus>54r</locus>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="54v">Then the list of the Popes who sent palls to archbishops, <handNote>mostly in
                                one hand</handNote> of cent. <origDate>xi</origDate> (scribe of Acts of Lanfranc<hi
                                rend="footnote"><name type="person">Lanfranc</name>'s name is written in
                            capitals.</hi>): but the last two entries are added later, viz. <name type="person">Urbanus
                                Anselmo</name>, <name type="person">Paschalis Radulfo</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55r">The lists of Archbishops and Bishops on the next leaf are <handNote>in one
                                hand, English</handNote> of cent. <origDate>x (?)</origDate>. They are <layout>in five
                                columns</layout></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55r">Column 1:<lb/> Nomina archiepiscoporum dorouernensis ecclesie,<lb/> i <name
                                type="person">Agustinus</name> to xxiii <name type="person">Dunstan</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55r">Column 2:<lb/> Nomina episcoporum hrofensis ecclesie,<lb/> i <name
                                type="person">Paulinus</name> to xv <name type="person">&#198;lfstan</name></ab>

                        <ab locusNew="55r">Column 3:<lb/>
                            <q>Nomina episcoporum orientalium Saxonum</q><lb/> i <name type="person">Mellitus</name> to
                            xx <name type="person">&#198;lfstan</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55r">Column 4:<lb/> Nomina episcoporum australium Saxonum<lb/> i <name
                                type="person">&#503;ilfri&#240;</name> to xvii <name type="person"
                                >&#198;&#254;elgar</name></ab>

                        <ab locusNew="55r">Column 5:<lb/> Nomina episcaporum occidentalium Saxonum.<lb/> i. Primus
                            occidentalium Saxonum <name type="person">birinus</name> fuit episcopus qui cum consilio
                                <name type="person">honorii papae</name> uenerat <name type="place">brittanniam</name>
                            to xix <name type="person">Ealhfer&#240;</name><lb/> After xiii the numbers were
                            originally written wrong and corrected</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v">On verso, original hand</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v">Col. 1 continues lists of West Saxon Bishops.<lb/> xx <name type="person"
                                >Tumberht</name> to xxvii <name type="person">&#230;lfheah</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v">Col. 2. Nomina episcoporum Scireburnensis ecclesie<lb/> i <name type="person"
                                >Aldhelm</name> to xix <name type="person">&#230;&#447;elsige</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v">Col. 3. Nomina episcoporum &#447;iltuniensis ecclesie<lb/> i <name
                                type="person">&#230;&#254;elstan</name> to vii <name type="person"
                            >sigric</name></ab>
                        <ab>And, below</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v">Nomina episcoporum cridiensis ecclesiae<lb/> i <name type="person"
                                >Eadulf</name> to iii <name type="person">Alf&#447;old</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v">Besides these are three Latin paragraphs <decoNote>in brown ink</decoNote>
                            <handNote>in <name type="place">Christ Church (Canterbury)</name> hand</handNote>, viz.</ab>
                        <ab>a. (col. 1)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v"> Nomina episcoporum lindisfarnensis id est dunelmensis ecclesie. <name
                                type="person">Aidanus</name>, <name type="person">Finanus</name> etc. </ab>
                        <ab>ending</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v">
                            <name type="person">Walcherus</name>, <name type="person">Willelmus</name>, <name
                                type="person">Rannulfus</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>b. (col. 4)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v"> Nomina episcoporum eboracensis ecclesie<lb/> Primus ipsius ecclesie presul
                            erat <name type="person">paulinus</name>. Ordinatus arusto (sic for a iusto) archiepiscopo
                            accipiens pallium ad consecrandum dorobernensem archiepiscopum ab <name type="person"
                                >honorio papa</name> Hac enim de causa pallium habuit. (Here 1.5 lines erased.) Turbatis
                            postea rebus northanhymbrorum <name type="person">paulinus</name> rediit cantiam et quoniam
                            rofensis ecclesia pastore tunc fuerat destituta: inuitante honorio archiepiscopo curam
                            ipsius ecclesie suscepit. in qua moriens pallium reliquit. Post cuius discessum ab ecclesia
                            eboracensi quod fuit anno. <date>dc xxxiii</date> dominice incarnat. usque <date>dcc.
                                xxxv.</date> annum incarnacione dominice hoc est per cii. annos presides eboracenses non
                            habuerunt pallium. Primus ipsius ecclesie presul <name type="person">paulinus</name>. <name
                                type="person">Ceadda</name>, <name type="person">Wilfridus</name> etc. to <name
                                type="person">Thomas</name>, <name type="person">Gerardus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Thomas</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>c. Across the page at bottom</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v"> Sciendum quod <name type="person">theodorus</name> archiepiscopus sepe
                            northanhymbrorum prouinciam sua presentia uisitauit epos, ordinando et in quibus locis ante
                            non fuerant constituendo et alia primatis anglorum officia administrando. Testatur namque
                            beda quod pulso ab episcopatu pro sua inobedientia <name type="person">Wilfrido</name> duos
                            in eius locum substituit episcopos (etc. he ordained other bishops and presided at a synod
                            in <name type="place">Northumbria</name>). Hec et alia nonnulla ex iure primatis anglorum
                            suo tempore ibidem exercuit. etiam eo tempore quo eboracensis ecclesia suum episcopum
                            habuit. <name type="person">bosam</name> uidelicet qui <name type="person">Wilfrido</name>
                            successerat </ab>
                        <ab>After this a hand more like that of the Lists, but not identical with it, writes</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="55v"> Hec sunt nomina regum cantie post aduentum <name type="person">Sancti
                                Augustini</name>, <name type="person">&#198;gelberhtus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Eadbaldus</name>, <name type="person">Hercanberhtus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Egberhtus</name>, <name type="person">Lotharius</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Wihtredus</name>, <name type="person">Eadberhtus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >&#198;gelbertus</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>The last leaf of the quire (7) is ruled but blank <supplied>(f.
                                    <locus>56r</locus>-<locus>56v</locus>)</supplied>: edges have been cut off it</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <milestone n="II" unit="volume"/>
                    <msItem n="4.1" locusStart="57r" locusEnd="58v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Sedulius</name>, <title>Letter I to <name type="person"
                                    >Macedonius</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <!--<ab>Neumes litter this copy of Sedulius - more needs to be done with this</ab>-->
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>
                                <name type="author">Sedulius</name>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>(cent. <origDate>viii-ix</origDate>
                            <name type="person">Bradshaw</name>)</ab>
                        <ab>ff. <locus locusNew="57r">1r</locus>-<locus locusNew="58v">2v</locus> are <layout>in single
                                lines</layout>, <handNote>in a different hand from the rest</handNote><hi
                                rend="footnote">f. <locus locusNew="58v">2v</locus> may very well be by a third
                                hand</hi>, <layout>33 lines to a page</layout>. The rest is <layout>in double columns of
                                27 lines</layout>. <handNote>Both hands are of Celtic aspect. The first is much rounder
                                and more legible than the second</handNote></ab>
                        <ab>At the top of f. <locus locusNew="57r">1r</locus>
                            <decoNote>in large capitals</decoNote> is</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="57r">FRI &#208;ESTAN</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="57r">(followed by diacon in minuscule)</ab>
                        <ab>The first three letters appear to have been written over some others, two of which appear to
                            be IN. The letters in DE<supplied agent="RJR">S (with a tall minuscule s)</supplied> seem
                            perhaps to be altered from DEI. I have some suspicion that an inscription in capitals IN DEI
                            NOMINE has been partly erased and adapted to FRI&#208;ESTAN. Dr G. F. Browne, Bishop of
                            Bristol, has suggested that this name may be an early signature of <name type="person"
                                >Frithestan afterwards (<date>909</date>) Bishop of Winchester</name></ab>
                        <ab>References are made here to the edition by <ref type="bibl" target="Huemer 1885">Huemer in
                                the Vienna <hi rend="italic">Corpus Scriptt. Eccl. Latt.</hi> (1885)</ref> for which
                            this manuscript was not used</ab>
                        <rubric locus="1r" locusNew="57r">Incipit epistula <name type="person">sedulii</name> ad
                            macedonium praesbiterum</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="57r"><name type="person">Sedulii</name> iuxta fidem catholicam christiani.
                            Inquo sunt haec uersibus heroicis paschalis carminis Libri u.</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="57r">Sancto ac beatissimo patri macedonoi presbitero sedulius in christo
                            salutem</ab>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Huemer 1885">p. 1</ref>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="57r">Priusquam me uenerabilis pater</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="58v">Cum [patre et <hi rend="italic">corr.</hi>] sancto spiritu per omnia
                            (in cuncta <hi rend="italic">corr.</hi>) secula seculorum</explicit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Huemer 1885">p. 13</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>Corrector adds in space</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="58v"> h p usque ad passionem et resurrectionem ascensionemque domini nostri Ihesu
                            Christi </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Red capitals</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="58v">Explicit epistola <name type="author">Sedulii</name> ad Macedonium
                            presbiterum</rubric>

                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="4.2" locusStart="59r" locusEnd="79v">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Sedulius</name>, <title>Carmen paschale</title></head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>
                                <name type="author">Sedulius</name>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>The second hand</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="3r" locusNew="59r">
                            <decoNote>Large initial P with serpent heads and panels of interlaced work: dotted with red
                                and ? purple</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="59r">Paschales quicumque dapes</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Huemer 1885">p. 14</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Titles are in small capitals: often in the margin</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Smaller initials are sometimes plain Roman in red: some are of the Celtic type,
                                with dots about them</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="12r" locusNew="68r">
                            <decoNote>A bit of Celtic ornament drawn in the margin</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="12v" locusNew="68v">
                            <decoNote>Upper L. corner in red RA. Each book has an interesting initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <!--<ab locusNew="68v"><decoNote>also on this page, partially erased sketch of person with outstretched hand, and fully erased figure above that</decoNote></ab>-->
                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="23v" locusNew="79v">per tanta uolumina libros</explicit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Huemer 1885">p. 146</ref>)</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="79v">Explicit liber u.</rubric>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4.3" locusStart="79v" locusEnd="80r">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Sedulius</name>, <title>Hymn <q>A solis ortus
                                cardine</q></title></head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>
                                <name type="author">Sedulius</name>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locusNew="79v">Incipit carmen (de laud)e christi</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="23v" locusNew="79v">A solis ortus cardine</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Huemer 1885">p. 163</ref>)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="80r">caelis reddidit</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="80r">Explicit carmen de (?na)t' domini nostri Ihesu Christi</rubric>
                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="4.4" locusStart="80r" locusEnd="81r">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Sedulius</name>, <title>Letter II to <name type="person"
                                    >Macedonius</name></title></head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>
                                <name type="author">Sedulius</name>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locus="24r" locusNew="80r">Incipit Epistolis sancti <name type="author">Seduli</name>
                            ad</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="24r" locusNew="80r">Sancto ac beatisimo patri macedonio praes. <name
                                type="author">Sedulius</name> in Christo salutem</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Huemer 1885">p. 171</ref>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="80r">Praecipisti reuerendae mi domine paschalis carminis textum</incipit>
                        <ab>Ends f. <locus locusNew="81r">25r</locus> col. 1</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="81r">cum patre et sancto spiritu per omnia secula seculorum. Amen,
                            beatissime ora pro me pater, finit</explicit>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="4.5" locusStart="81r" locusEnd="81v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Verses of <name type="person">Damasus</name> on <name type="person">St
                                Paul</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locus="25r" locusNew="81r">Iam dutum salus (saulus) procerum praecepta secutus cum
                            domino patrias uellet praeponere leges</incipit>
                        <ab>(Verses of Damasus on <name type="person">St Paul</name>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Migne 013">P. L. XIII 379</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>Ending</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="81v">Sancte tuus damasus uoluit triumphos</explicit>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="4.6" locusStart="81v" locusEnd="82v">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Sedulius</name>, <title>Elegia</title></head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>
                                <name type="author">Sedulius</name>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <incipit locus="25v" locusNew="81v">Cantemus socii domino cantemus honorem</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Huemer 1885">Hymnus I. p. 155</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="25v" locusNew="81v">At bottom an omission of a couplet is supplied</ab>
                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="82v">
                            <lg>
                                <l>Cum sancto spiritu gloria magna patri</l>
                                <l>Finit hoc opusculum deo gratias. Amen</l>
                            </lg>
                        </explicit>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="4.7" locusStart="82v" locusEnd="83v">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Augustine</name>, <title>De ciuitate Dei, xviii.23
                                (excerpts) with three versions of Sibylline prophecies</title></head>

                        <rubric locus="26v" locusNew="82v">Hec sunt uaticiniae sibillae (?de Christo)</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="83r">In manus infidelium post ea ueniet. dabunt et deo alapas
                            manibus</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="83r">Et tunc ab inferis regressus ad lucem ueniet primus resurrectionis
                            principio reuocatus ostenso</explicit>
                        <ab>(Aug. de civ. dei xviii 23 from Lactantius)</ab>
                        <incipit locus="27r" locusNew="83r">Iudicii signum tellus sudore madescit</incipit>
                        <ab>(Aug. de civ. dei xviii 23)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="83v">e caelo ignisque et sulphur(is) annis</explicit>
                        <incipit locus="27v" locusNew="83v">Hos predicens uersus sanctus / <name type="person"
                                >Agustinus</name> ex libro sybellae adsu / mens in xxuii (blank) dei de greco /
                            translates inseruit. non nulli hanc / sybellam aput grecos / natam ferunt eo tempore quo /
                            romulus romam condidit in iudea / aesaia et osse profetantibus regnante ezechia, alii uero
                            belli troiani temporibus quaedam de Christo / manifesta scribsise</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="83v">Item in / ... uersos de aduentu Christi</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="83v">Iudicii signum su / dauit rupada tellus / et saecli ueniet qui / cuncta
                            lauabit secoram / celsus iudex orbemque probabit / etc.</incipit>
                        <ab>The writing of col. 2 is very faint. Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="83v">Salpix luctifera caelo tune uoce sonabit / Adfore iam monstrantur
                            erumnasque adfore / Saec<supplied agent="RJR">u</supplied>li. loetiferumque chaus monstrauit
                            terra de (?hiscens)</explicit>
                        <ab>This second version is not among those given by <ref type="bibl" target="Alexandre 1853"
                                >Alexandre (<hi rend="italic">Oracula Sibyllina</hi> II 230)</ref></ab>
                        <ab>In the earlier part have been a good many Anglo-Saxon glosses, but a large number are
                            erased. After col. 1 of f. <locus locusNew="64v">8v</locus> glosses of any kind decrease
                            markedly in number</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="RJR">Old English glosses to Sedulius are <ref type="bibl"
                                    target="Cameron 1973">Cameron C97.2</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: RJR 19/12/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
