<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>


                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC251">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>251</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>H. 7</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>89</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Bury St Edmunds Chronicle</head>

                <head type="James">Chronicon Buriense</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">280</height>
                        <width unit="mm">190</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">11 x 7.5</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 103</extent>, <layout>34
                        lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv</origDate>, <handNote>very well written</handNote>.
                        <decoNote>There is a quantity of unusual and pretty pen-work, in pink and green, on the margins
                        of the earlier leaves</decoNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>8</num> b<num>8</num> (wants 8) | c<num>8</num>-n<num>8</num>
                    </collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">The book is doubtless from <name type="place">Bury St Edmunds</name>. On f.
                        <locus>1r</locus> is the pressmark E. 43.<hi rend="footnote">It is not easy to see why this
                        pressmark was given to this book. The letters of the pressmarks of <name type="place"
                            >Bury</name> uniformly corresponded to the subjects of the books (e.g. B for Biblia): also,
                        there is another extant volume marked E. 43 (viz. <ref type="ms" target="LAM218">Lambeth MS.
                            218</ref>, Epistolae Alcuini). The proper letter for the present volume is C
                        (=Chronica).</hi> A long life of <name type="person">St Edmund</name> is in the text, and there
                    are notes relating to the Abbey at the end.</p>


                <p function="Research">The <q>Cronica que liber Regius appellatur</q> is referred to in Flete's <hi
                        rend="italic">History of Westminster Abbey</hi> (see <ref type="ms" target="CCC287">MS 287.
                        3</ref>)<hi rend="footnote">See the edition by <ref type="bibl" target="Armitage Robinson 1909a"
                            >Dr J. Armitage Robinson, Dean of Westminster, 1909, p. 3</ref>.</hi> (but the passage cited
                    by him is not in the text of this MS.) with the note <q>Cronica Regia ideo dicitur quia <name
                            type="person">Rex Richardus secundus</name> eam scribi fecit a monacho quodam cenobii <name
                            type="place">S. Edmundi de Burye</name>.</q> I think it possible that the present MS.
                    contains a shortened text of this <hi rend="italic">Chronica Regia</hi>.</p>



                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iv + 1-103 + v-viii</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>

                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="15v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Bury St Edmunds Chronicle</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Chronicon Buriense</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab locus="1r"> Chronicle of the Popes (to <name type="person">Gregory IX</name>,
                                <date>1370</date>), extracted from another Chronicle </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r"><name type="person">Petrus</name> fuit primus papa post Iesum Christum
                            quo anno <name type="person">Petrus</name> apud <name type="place">Romam</name> duos
                            ordinauit</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">
                            <decoNote>There is a good blue initial and within it an outline drawing of <name
                                    type="person">Peter</name>, throned as Pope, holding keys and book: outside, on L.,
                                is <name type="person">St Paul</name></decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <rubric locus="3r">Explicit de libro quarto</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="3r">Incipit de libro quinto</rubric>
                        <ab>(Capitulum I.)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="3r"><name type="person">Hillarius</name> post <name type="person"
                                >leonem</name> successit</incipit>

                        <rubric locus="5v">Explicit de libro iiii<abbr rend="superscript">to</abbr></rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="5v">Incipit de libro v<abbr rend="superscript">to</abbr> (sic)</rubric>

                        <ab>(Capitulum 2.)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="5v"><name type="person">Martinus</name> papa post <name type="person"
                                >Iohannem</name></incipit>

                        <rubric locus="8v">Explicit de libro sexto</rubric>

                        <rubric locus="8v">Incipit de libro septimo</rubric>

                        <incipit locusNew="8v"><name type="person">Hildebrandus</name> qui et <name type="person"
                                >Gregorius</name> vii<abbr rend="superscript">us</abbr></incipit>

                        <ab>Ends (Capitulum 46)</ab>
                        <explicit locus="12v"><name type="person">Gregorius</name> undecimus diaconus cardinalis prius
                                <name type="person">Petrus</name> Rogeri nuncupatus</explicit>



                        <ab>ff. <locus>13r</locus>-<locus>15v</locus> blank</ab>



                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="16r" locusEnd="100r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>
                                <name type="person">Chronicle of England</name>
                            </title>
                        </head>

                        <!-- Not the Brut chronicle?? -->
                        <rubric locus="16r">Incipit historia de <name type="person">Bruto</name> Rege Britonum cum aliis
                            Regibus <name type="place">Anglie</name> linealiter ab eo descendentibus usque ad Regem
                                <name type="person">Ricardum secundum</name> qui presentem fecit compilari historiam
                            anno. Regni sui quarto decimo</rubric>

                        <ab locusNew="16r">
                            <decoNote>The initial has a seated king, crowned and robed, with shield and bannered lance,
                                in the same style as the other figured initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="16r">De Patre istius <name type="person">Bruti</name> historie videntur
                            dissonare. nam Britonum historia dicit istum brutum fuisse filium <name type="person"
                                >Siluii</name></incipit>
                        <ab>There are marginal references (not consecutive) to chapters of a work unnamed</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="34r">The account of <name type="person">St Edmund</name> occupies ff. <locus
                                locusNew="34r">32r</locus>-<locus locusNew="42v">43v</locus>. <decoNote>It has a large
                                coloured initial and begins</decoNote></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="34r"><name type="person">Sanctus Edmundus</name>
                            <name type="person">Alkamundi</name> Regis Saxonie et <name type="person">Siware</name>
                            Regine filius anno ab incarnatione domini (bis) dcccxli<abbr rend="superscript"
                            >o</abbr></incipit>
                        <ab>The last event recorded is <name type="person">Bishop Bateman</name>'s attempt on the
                            privileges of <name type="person">St Edmund</name> (<date>1344</date>) and his death, with
                            miraculous signs accompanying. This ends:</ab>
                        <explicit locus="42v">cotidie magnifice operatur in suo martire glorioso</explicit>
                        <ab>An account of <name type="person">St Edwold</name> follows:</ab>
                        <incipit locus="42v">Postquam autem beatissimus rex <name type="person">Edmundus</name> mutauit
                            per triumphum martirii</incipit>
                        <ab>Ends f. <locus>100r</locus> with accession of <name type="person">Richard II</name></ab>
                        <explicit locus="100r">ac etiam voto communi singulorum in regnum successit Anglorum anno etatis
                            sue undecimo</explicit>
                        <ab>ff. <locus>100v</locus>-<locus>102r</locus> blank</ab>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>102v</locus> a note on the <name type="place">old round chapel of St Edmund at
                                Bury</name>. This note also occurs in the <ref type="ms" target="COA030">MS. Arundel xxx
                                at the College of Arms</ref>. See my <ref type="bibl" target="James 1895a"><hi
                                    rend="italic">Essays on the Abbey of Bury St Edmunds</hi>, C. A. S., p.
                            188</ref></ab>

                        <incipit locus="102v">Anno domini <date>m<abbr rend="superscript">lo</abbr> cc<abbr
                                    rend="superscript">mo</abbr> lxxv<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr></date> deposita
                            est capella rotunda in cimiterio monachorum in qua corpus <name type="person">Sancti
                                Edmundi</name> primo iacuit ante translacionem suam</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="102v">ex parte australi ubi nunc est capella <name type="person">Sancti
                                Botulphi</name> et ortus feretrariorum</explicit>


                        <ab locusNew="103r"> Pensio scolarium.<lb/> In primis de feretrariis ad festum <name
                                type="person">S. Michaelis</name> iii<abbr rend="superscript">s</abbr> vi<abbr
                                rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/> Item de diuersis fratribus ad fest. <name type="person"
                                >S. Andree</name> xxii<abbr rend="superscript">s</abbr><lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> de celerario pro <name type="person">Abbate Will.</name>
                                xviij<abbr rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> pro <name type="person">Will. Rowham</name> xii<abbr
                                rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/> ... <lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> pro <name type="person">priore Joh. Gofford</name> xx<abbr
                                rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> de Camerario pro <name type="person">Ed<abbr rend="superscript"
                                    >o</abbr> Bokynham</name> xiiii<abbr rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> pro <name type="person">henr. de stablys</name> iiiij<abbr
                                rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> de manerio de hesete ad fest. purif. xx<abbr rend="superscript"
                                >d</abbr><lb/> ... <lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> de <name type="person">thoma munchesey</name> xii<abbr
                                rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> de sacrista pro <name type="person">Abb. Will. cratfeld</name>
                                iii<abbr rend="superscript">s</abbr> iiij<abbr rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/> ... <lb/>
                            <supplied>Item</supplied> de <name type="person">magistro cripte</name> x<abbr
                                rend="superscript">d</abbr><lb/> etc. </ab>
                        <ab>No other proper names occur</ab>


                    </msItem>


                </msContents>



                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text:copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 6.3.2007</p>
                            <p>remarks: </p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>



            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
