<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC272">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>272</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>O. 5</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>211</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">The Psalter of Count Achadeus</head>
                <head type="James">Psalterium Achadei Comitis</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">266</height>
                        <width unit="mm">210</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">10.5 x 8.3</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 183 + 3</extent>,
                        <layout>20 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>ix late</origDate>, <handNote>in a Caroline
                        minuscule, pale ink, fine ornaments</handNote>.</p>
                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1<num>8</num> (wants 4, 5) 2<num>8</num>-4<num>8</num> (wants 4) 5<num>8</num>
                            6<num>8</num> (wants 3) 7<num>8</num> (wants 7) 8<num>8</num> 9<num>8</num> (wants 8)
                            10<num>8</num> 11<num>8</num> (wants 8) 12<num>8</num>-14<num>8</num> (wants 4, 5)
                            15<num>8</num> 16<num>8</num> (wants 4) 17<num>8</num>-20<num>8</num> 21<num>4</num>
                            22<num>8</num> 23<num>8</num> 24<num>4</num> 25<num>8</num> 26 (one), 3
                        flyleaves</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance" rend="afterContents">Of the persons mentioned in the Litany <supplied>(ff.
                            <locus>151r</locus>-<locus>154r</locus>)</supplied>
                    <name type="person">Marinus</name>, consecrated Pope in <date>December 882</date>, died in <date>May
                        884</date>. <name type="person">Carloman</name>, sole king in <date>882</date>, died in
                        <date>884</date>. <name type="person">Fulco, Archbishop of Rheims</name>, was consecrated on
                        <date>10 March 883</date>. This gives a date between <date>March 883</date> and <date>May
                        884</date> for the writing of the Litany.</p>

                <p function="Provenance" rend="afterContents">Of the Saints: <name type="person">Sixtus</name>, <name
                        type="person">Sinicius</name>, <name type="person">Nivardus</name>, are of <name type="place"
                        >Rheims</name>. Also <name type="person">Sindulfus</name>: <name type="person">Cilinia</name> is
                    mother of <name type="person">St Remigius</name>. <name type="person">Theoderic</name> is of <name
                        type="place">Cambrai</name>, <name type="person">Theodulf</name> of <name type="place"
                        >Rheims</name>. The occurrence of <name type="person">Remigius</name>
                    <decoNote>in gold capitals</decoNote> is a further indication of <name type="place">Rheims</name>.
                    It is not clear why <name type="person">Abundus</name> is in gold unless it be to mark the end of
                    the list of Confessors. The reason for the importance given to <name type="person">Columbanus</name>
                    is also to seek.</p>

                <p function="Provenance" rend="afterContents">That the book was in later times the property of <name
                        type="place">Christ Church, Canterbury</name>, the flyleaves at the end <supplied>(ff.
                            <locus>ir</locus>-<locus>iiv</locus>)</supplied> seem to show: and also the large inserted
                    frontispiece to the Psalter <supplied>(f. <locus>3v</locus>)</supplied> appears to me to be in a
                    style characteristic of <name type="place">Christ Church</name>. It is like the work in the glossed
                    Gospels (<ref type="ms" target="CTC151">Trinity College B. 5. 5</ref>) only not so good.</p>

                <p function="Additions">An old note (<origDate>xvi</origDate>) on f. <locus>1r</locus>: Hic codex
                    scriptus temporibus <name type="person">Marini papae</name> et <name type="person">carlomanni</name>
                    anno Domini <date>885</date> Mar. Scot. ut infra in Litania.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + 1-2 + 2a + 3-183 + i-iii + c-d</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="183v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Psalter of <name type="person">Count Achadeus</name></title>

                        </head>

                        <ab locusNew="1r">
                            <decoNote>Title in red rustic capitals</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="1r">Incipit Prologus pro origo prophetiae <name type="person">Dauid regis</name>
                            psalmorum numerum cl</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r"><name type="person">Dauid</name> filius <name type="person">iesse</name>
                            cum esset in regno suo</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Migne 093"><supplied>P. L.</supplied> XCIII 477</ref>)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="1v">canticum graduum xv</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="1v">Incipit Praefatio <name type="author">Sancti Hieronimi</name>
                            presbiteri</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="1v">Psalterium <name type="place">romae</name> dudum positus</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Migne 029"><supplied>P. L.</supplied> XXIX 117</ref>, etc.) </ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="2v">de purissimo fonte potare</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="2v">Explicit praefatio <name type="author">Sancti Hieronimi</name>
                            presbiteri</rubric>


                        <rubric locusNew="2v">Incipit cantica Psalmorum</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="2v">Canticum psalmorum animas decorat</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Migne 131"><supplied>P. L.</supplied> CXXXI 142</ref>: <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Migne 142"><supplied>P. L.</supplied> CXLII 46</ref>)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="2ar">in caelo deus mirificabit</explicit>
                        <ab>f. <locus locusNew="2av">3v</locus> was originally blank, apparently. <decoNote>It
                                    <supplied>was</supplied> covered by a leaf cut from a <origDate>xii</origDate>th
                                cent. Psalter<supplied>, once</supplied> pasted on to it <supplied>and now
                                    lifted</supplied></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="3v">
                            <decoNote>This leaf has an elaborate full-page initial B and the letters EATUS  VIA
                                PECCATORUM in gold capitals on blue (and white) ground</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="3v">
                            <decoNote>The letter B is filled with conventional foliage and convoluted stems, in the
                                curves of which are many small white animals. The ground of this is gold. In the stem of
                                the B is a medallion with gold ground containing a crowned bust of <name type="person"
                                    >David</name>. Outside the letter the ground is blue</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="3v">
                            <decoNote>The frame is of gold and red (dotted with white): at the angles are four
                                medallions and in the middle of the sides four half-medallions, all with gold ground.
                                Those at the angles have: top L., bust of white-bearded man: lower L., bust of beardless
                                man; upper and lower R., busts of kings. Those in the sides have: upper and lower C.,
                                busts of angels: L. side small man in red and blue: R., small man in red with
                                shield</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="3v">
                            <decoNote>The work is bold and rich but not very delicate</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab locusNew="4r">Text begins imperfectly in Ps. ii. 2</ab>
                        <incipit locus="4r">Asstiterunt reges terrae</incipit>
                        <ab>There is a marginal gloss<handNote> in a very beautiful small hand</handNote>. The
                            references to the text are made (on ff. <locus>4r</locus>, <locus>5r</locus>) by Greek
                            letters. It begins</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="4r">Reges autem terre <name type="person">herodem</name> dicit qui infantes
                            occidit. alterumque <name type="person">herodem</name> nepotem eius qui <name type="person"
                                >pilato</name> in nece christi consensit</incipit>
                        <ab>At the end of each Psalm is a Collect, that for Ps. ii is</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="4v">Disrumpe domine nostrorum uincula peccatorum</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The initials of Psalms and verses are usually in fluid gold throughout the book.
                                On f. <locus>7r</locus> are two initials filled with blue. On f. <locus>1r</locus> the
                                initial is handsome, in fluid gold edged with red, blue ground: the letter surrounded by
                                gold foliage. On ff. <locus>1v</locus>, <locus>2v</locus> late pen-flourishing has been
                                added to the initials</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>After f. <locus>25v</locus> a leaf is gone with end of Ps. xxv and beginning of
                                xxvi. The latter had a large initial occupying most of the page: the set-off is visible
                                on f. <locus>26r</locus></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>After f. <locus>39v</locus> a leaf is gone with the beginning of Ps. xxxviii. The
                                set-off of the full-page initial is well seen on f. <locus>39v</locus></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>On f. <locus>51r</locus> are two small decorative initials.</decoNote>
                            <decoNote>After f. <locus>51v</locus> a leaf is gone with most of Ps. li: little of the
                                set-off can be seen.</decoNote>
                            <decoNote>The first words of Ps. lii are in gold capitals</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>After f. <locus>65v</locus> a leaf is gone with the beginning of Ps. lxviii. The
                                set-off of the initial is very visible on f. <locus>65v</locus></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>After f. <locus>81v</locus> a leaf is gone with part of Ps. lxxx. The set-off of
                                the initial is very visible on f. <locus>82r</locus></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>On f. <locus>98r</locus> is the only large initial which has survived; to Ps.
                                xcvii. It is of gold edged with red, with panels of patterned blue, filled with green
                                and with gold interlacings: outside is gold foliage in two colours of gold</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>After f. <locus>100v</locus> two leaves gone with part of Ps. ci. Set-off of
                                initial on f. <locus>101r</locus></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>After f. <locus>114v</locus> a leaf gone with Ps. cix and part of cx</ab>
                        <ab>On <locus locusNew="143r">142r</locus> two small decorative initials</ab>
                        <ab>Ps. cl ends on f. <locus>150r</locus>. The Collect is</ab>
                        <incipit locus="150r">Armoniae nostrae suauissime melos</incipit>
                        <ab>Gloss ends</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="150r">in spiritu qui spiritus est laudare non desinit</explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="150r"><decoNote>In gold capitals</decoNote> at the foot of the page is</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="150r"><name type="person">Achadeus</name> misericordia dei <lb/> comes. hunc
                            psalterium <lb/> scribere iussit</ab>
                        <ab>f. <locus>150v</locus> blank</ab>

                        <ab locusNew="151r">Then follows the Litany on four leaves <handNote>in a smaller script than
                                before but very probably by the same scribe</handNote>. <decoNote>The text is arranged
                                in double columns and in arched or pedimented frames like those in which, in early
                                gospel books, the Canons of the Gospels are written. In this MS. the shafts are purple
                                or green, marbled, and have plants twined spirally about them. The plinth on which they
                                stand is yellow with red patterns, and the lintel above in one case of purple and
                                elsewhere of yellow and red. The tympana above this are filled with conventional foliage
                                in gold and colour, and above the arches or gables are birds pecking at
                                leaves</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>The text is</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="151r">Incipit letania</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="151r">Kyrieleison. Ter, Xpe eleison. ter, Kyrieleison. ter. Xpe audi nos. ter.
                            Sancta <name type="person">Maria</name>. or</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="151r">
                            <decoNote>(so far in gold capitals)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="151r"><name type="person">Michahel</name>, <name type="person">Gabrihel</name>,
                                <name type="person">Raphahel</name>. S. chorus archangelorum
                            (<decoNote>red</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="151r"><name type="person">Petre</name>, <name type="person">Paule</name>, <name
                                type="person">Andrea</name>, <name type="person">Iacobe</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Iohannes</name>, <name type="person">Philippe</name>, <name type="person"
                            >Iacobe</name>, <name type="person">Toma</name>, <name type="person">Bartholomee</name>,
                                <name type="person">Mathee</name>, <name type="person">Simon</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Tadee</name>, <name type="person">Mathia</name>. S. chorus apost. (red)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="151r"><name type="person">Stephane</name>, <name type="person">Iohannes</name>,
                                <name type="person">Marce</name>, <name type="person">Luca</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Line</name>, <name type="person">Clete</name>, <name type="person">Clemens</name>,
                                <name type="person">Cleopha</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="151v"><name type="person">Barnaba</name>, <name type="person">Ignatii</name>,
                                <name type="person">Apollonaris</name>, <name type="person">Chrisogone</name>, <name
                                type="person">Alaexander</name>, <name type="person">Dionisi</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Rustice</name>, <name type="person">Eleutheri</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Maurici</name>, <name type="person">Corneli</name>, <name type="person"
                            >Cypriane</name>, <name type="person">Georgi</name>, <name type="person">Cristophore</name>,
                                <name type="person">Iuliane</name>, <name type="person">Leudegari</name>, <name
                                type="person">Sixte</name>, <name type="person">Laurenti</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Ypolite</name>, <name type="person">Uincenti</name>, <name type="person">Uictor</name>,
                                <name type="person">Candide</name>, <name type="person">Quintine</name>, <name
                                type="person">Luciane</name>, <name type="person">Crispine</name>, Crispiniane, <name
                                type="person">Cosma</name>, <name type="person">Damiane</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Uictorice</name>, <name type="person">Tiburti</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Ualeriane</name>, <name type="person">Pancrati</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Geruasi</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="152r"><name type="person">Protasi</name>, <name type="person">Celse</name>, <name
                                type="person">Sebastiane</name>, <name type="person">Marce</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Marcelliane</name>, <name type="person">Fabiane</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Urbane</name>, <name type="person">Simphoriane</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Saturnine</name>, <name type="person">Nicasi</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Timothee</name>, <name type="person">Apollonaris</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Rufine</name>, <name type="person">Firmine</name>, <name type="person"
                            >Ualeri</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="152r"><name type="person">SCE REMIGI</name> (<decoNote>gold capitals</decoNote>).
                                <name type="person">Hilari</name>, <name type="person">Benedicte</name>, <name
                                type="person">Germane</name>, <name type="person">Romane</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Siluester</name>, <name type="person">Ambrosi</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Gregorii</name>, <name type="person">Hieronime</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Augustine</name>, <name type="person">Eusebi</name>, <name type="person"
                            >Isidore</name>, <name type="person">Martine</name>, <name type="person">Leo</name>, <name
                                type="person">Sulpici</name>, <name type="person">Aniane</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Amande</name></ab>

                        <ab locusNew="152v"><name type="person">SCE COLUMBANE</name> (<decoNote>gold capitals, red
                                dots</decoNote>) <name type="person">Brici</name>, <name type="person">Goar</name>,
                                <name type="person">Medarde</name>, <name type="person">Maximine</name>, <name
                                type="person">Candide</name>, <name type="person">Antoni</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Machari</name>, <name type="person">Teuderice</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Teudulfe</name>, <name type="person">Memmi</name>, <name type="person">Lupe</name>,
                                <name type="person">Arnulfe</name>, <name type="person">Nivarde</name>, <name
                                type="person">Sixte</name>, <name type="person">Sinici</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Basole</name>, <name type="person">Uedaste</name>, <name type="person">Onesime</name>,
                                <name type="person">Sindulfe</name>, <name type="person">Filiberte</name>, <name
                                type="person">Audoine</name>, <name type="person">Siluine</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Carlepphe</name>, <name type="person">Richari</name>, <name type="person"
                            >Pacomi</name>, <name type="person">Fortunate</name>, <name type="person">Troiane</name>,
                                <name type="person">Marcelline</name>, <name type="person">Arseni</name>, <name
                                type="person">Celsine</name>. <name type="person">Sce abunde</name> (<decoNote>gold
                                letters</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="153r"><name type="person">Felicitas</name>, <name type="person">Perpetua</name>,
                                <name type="person">Sincletica</name>, <name type="person">Agatha</name>, <name
                                type="person">Lucia</name>, <name type="person">Agnes</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Cecilia</name>, <name type="person">Anastasia</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Genufefa</name>, <name type="person">Scolastica</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Eulalia</name>, <name type="person">Eugenia</name>, <name type="person">Eufemia</name>,
                                <name type="person">Petronilla</name>, <name type="person">Cristina</name>, <name
                                type="person">Columba</name>, <name type="person">Iuliana</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Afra</name>, <name type="person">Lucina</name>, <name type="person">Beatrix</name>,
                                <name type="person">Tecla</name>, <name type="person">Teodosia</name>, <name
                                type="person">Susanna</name>, <name type="person">Sabina</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Magra</name>, <name type="person">Prisca</name>, <name type="person">Saturnina</name>,
                                <name type="person">Cilinia</name>, <name type="person">Eutropia</name>, <name
                                type="person">Eufrosina</name>, <name type="person">Praxedis</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Margarita</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="153v"><name type="person">Potentiana</name>, <name type="person">Balbina</name>,
                                <name type="person">Radegundis</name>, <name type="person">Monegundis</name>. S. chorus
                            uirginum</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="153v">Omnes sancti orate pro nobis</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="153v">Propitius esto, etc...</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="153v">Ut pacem uobis dones...</ab>
                        <ab locus="154r">Ut <name type="person">Marinum</name> apostolicum in sancta religione
                            conseruare digneris</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="154r">Ut <name type="person">Karlomannum</name> regem perpetua prosperitate
                            conseruare digneris</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="154r">Ut (blank) reginam conseruare digneris</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="154r">Ut <name type="person">Folconem episcopum</name> cum omni grege sibi
                            commisso, etc.</ab>
                        <ab>No specially monastic suffrages occur</ab>
                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="154r">XPE AUDI NOS. TER. KYRIELEISON. XPELEISON. KYRIELEISON</explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="154r">
                            <decoNote>All in gold capitals</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>f. <locus>154v</locus> blank</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <handNote>In a script of the former size</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="155r">Ps. cli, beginning imperfectly</ab>
                        <incipit locus="155r">Pascebam oves patris mei</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="155r">a filiis israel. Deo gratias</explicit>

                        <rubric locus="155r">Incipiunt Cantici</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="155r">Canticum <name type="person">Isaie</name> prophete ad matutinas feria
                            II</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="155v">Canticum <name type="person">Ezechiae</name></ab>
                        <ab>The rubric here is</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="155v">OSCRIPTOREZACHARIE <hi rend="footnote">Probably a mistake for
                                    <q>scriptura <name type="person">regis ezechie</name></q> and not containing the
                                name of the
                            scribe</hi><!--James corrects scriptum to scriptura in corrigenda--></rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="156v">Canticum <name type="person">Annae</name></rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="157r">Canticum <name type="person">Moysi</name> prophete</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="158v">Canticum <name type="person">Abbacuc</name> prophete</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="159v">Canticum Deuteronomii</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="162v">Hymnum trium puerorum</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="163r">(<decoNote>small decorative initial</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="163v">Hymnum <name type="person">Zacharie</name></rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="164r">Canticum Sanctae <name type="person">Mariae</name></rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="164v">Canticum <name type="person">Simeon</name></rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="164v">Hymnum die dominico ad matutinas</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="164v">Te Deum</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="165v">Hymnum angelicum</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="165v">Gloria in excelsis</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="166r">Incipit fides catholica</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="166r">Quicumque</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="167v">Oratio Dominica</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="168r">Incipit symbolum</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="168r">(In margin the Aue <handNote>in a hand of cent.
                                <origDate>xiv</origDate></handNote>)</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="168r">Incipit Oratio <name type="person">Sancti Benedicti</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locus="168v">Dominator domine deus omnipotens qui es trinitas una</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Migne 101"><supplied>P. L.</supplied> CI 1400</ref>)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="170r">ut faciam uoluntatem tuam quia tu es deus meus tibi honor et gloria In
                            saecula saeculorum. Amen</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="170r">Orationes ad uesperas seu ad matutinas et ad tertiam et ad nonam seu ad
                            sextam</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="170r">Et ne nos inducas</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="170r">Orationes ad secundam</rubric>
                        <explicit locusNew="171v">Domine deus uirtutum conuerte nos</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="171v">Orationes maiores ad matutinas uel ad uesperas</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="171v">Oremus pro omni gradu ecclesiae</incipit>

                        <ab locusNew="171v">Includes: Pro abbate nostro</ab>
                        <rubric locus="172r">Orationes ad completa</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="172r">Domine exaudi, etc.</incipit>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>173r</locus> near the end: Exaudi deus <name type="person">Karlomanno
                                regi</name> uita</ab>


                        <rubric locusNew="173r">Incipit Responsoria per totum annum in diuino officio canenda. Isti
                            responsi sunt canendi ab aduentu domini usque in uigilio domini. Capitulum</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="173r">Ecce dies ueniunt dicit dominus et suscitabo</incipit>
                        <ab>Neumes occur on f. <locus>174v</locus></ab>
                        <!--<ab locusNew="174v">Neumes, only one line, for Response: "Ab omni via mala per..."</ab>-->
                        <ab>The Responses for the Temporal end f. <locus>176v</locus>. Then follow responses for <name
                                type="person">S. Michael</name> and for Common of Saints, ending f.
                            <locus>178r</locus></ab>
                        <rubric locus="178r">Orationes ad secundam</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="178r">Orationes ad tertiam</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="178r">Orationes ad sextam</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="178v">Orationes ad nonam</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="178v">Orationes ad vesperas</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="178v">Orationes pro semetipso</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="178v">Domine deus meus qui non habes dominum</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="179r">Qualiter orat. pro uiuo aguntur</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="179r">Qualiter orat. pro una femina</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="179r">Qualiter pro pluribus uiuis</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="179v">Qualiter pro uno defuncto</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="179v">Incipiunt orationes</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="179v">Domine deus omnipotens qui in trinitate perfecta</incipit>


                        <ab>Six prayers</ab>
                        <rubric locus="180r">Oratio <name type="person">Sancti Gregorii</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="180r">Rex seculorum et domine dominator</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="180v">Oratio <name type="person">Sancti Hieronimi</name></rubric>

                        <incipit locusNew="180v">Domine Iesu Christe dona mihi ut ambulem secundum mandata</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="180v">Alia</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="180v">Domine Iesu Christe noli me confundere</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="180v">Oratio <name type="person">Sancti Agustini</name> Episcopi</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="180v">Miserere domine super animas quas creasti</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="181v" locusNew="181r">Dicit <name type="person">S. Gregorius</name> Episcopus
                            cognoscatis quicunque hanc orationem omni die cantauerit sic dicit ipse <name type="person"
                                >Sanctus Gregorius</name> quod nec malus homo nec diabolus nocere non potest ipsi homini
                            nec animae nec corpori</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="181v">Domine exaudi orationem meam quia iam cognosco quod tempus meum prope
                            est</incipit>

                        <rubric locus="182v">Confessio</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="183r">Confiteor domino et tibi frater</incipit>



                        <ab locusNew="183r">
                            <handNote>In another hand, not much later</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="183r">Collecta in Exaudi domine iustitiam meam</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="183r">Conuerte domine oculos</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="183r">Collecta in Nisi dominus aedificauerit</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="183r">Domorum spiritalium</incipit>
                        <ab>The above were omitted in the text</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="183r">
                            <handNote>Prayer in the same hand</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="183r">Clementissime deus qui me inutilem famulum tuum</incipit>

                        <explicit locusNew="183v">adiuuante atque trahente qui</explicit>

                        <ab locusNew="ir">The <supplied>first two</supplied> flyleaves (ff.
                                <locus>ir</locus>-<locus>iiv</locus>) are from a roll or book of <name type="place"
                                >Christ Church, Canterbury</name>, records of courts (<origDate>xiv</origDate> or
                                <origDate>xv</origDate>) </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="iv">Acta in <name type="place">ecclesia Christi cant.</name></incipit>
                        <ab>(year not given)</ab>
                        <ab>Many Kentish place-names occur</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="iiir">On the last flyleaf <supplied>(f. <locus>iiir</locus>)</supplied> are many
                            unimportant scribbles</ab>

                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: RJR</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
