<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC279">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>279</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>O. 20</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>221</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Synods and Canons (Hibernensis), Synodus Patricii. Augustini dicta de conjugum ratione.
                    Liber ex Lege Moysi. Canones Hibernensis</head>
                <head type="James">Synodus Patricii. Canones</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">260</height>
                        <width unit="mm">170</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">10.2 x 7.1</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 96</extent>, <layout>20
                        lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>ix-x (or x)</origDate>, in the opinion of <name
                        type="person">Mr. Bradshaw</name>. <handNote>In a large, dispersed, slightly sloping minuscule:
                        not English</handNote>. <decoNote>Initials mostly in plain red or black. Rubrics in
                        capitals</decoNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1<num>8</num>-4<num>8</num> 5<num>10</num> 6<num>8</num>-10<num>8</num> 11<num>10</num>
                        (wants 1) 12<num>6</num> (wants 6)</collation>. The old pagination is incorrect by 2 after p.
                        <locus>69</locus>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">From <name type="place">Worcester</name>: see below.</p>
                <p function="Provenance">On pp. 30 sqq. <ref type="bibl" target="Bradshaw 1893">Mr. Bradshaw</ref>
                    prints <q>the paragraphs partly of Irish origin which are appended to the <hi rend="italic">Liber ex
                            lege Moysi</hi></q> and discusses them. On p. 32 he says <q>until fresh evidence is
                        forthcoming, I shall believe that the present manuscript, whether it was itself transcribed in
                        the <name type="place">Cambrai</name> and <name type="place">Arras</name> district or elsewhere,
                        owes its origin to manuscripts then preserved in <name type="place">Brittany</name>.</q></p>


                <p function="Research">The <hi rend="italic">Synodus</hi> (pp. <locus>1</locus>-<locus>11</locus>) is
                    printed by <ref type="bibl" target="Haddan and Stubbs 1873">Haddan and Stubbs</ref> II 330.</p>
                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>pp. i-iv + 1-69 + 69b-c + 70-89 + 89b-c + 90-188 + v-viii</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1" locusEnd="188">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Synods and Canons (Hibernensis), Synodus Patricii. Augustini dicta de conjugum
                                ratione. Liber ex lege Moysi. Canones Hibernensis</title>
                        </head>
                        <!-- Subdivide item? -->

                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>In large red and black capitals</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="1">Incipit <lb/> Sinodus <lb/> Episco<lb/>porum <lb/> idest <lb/> Patricii
                            Auxilii Issernini <lb/></rubric>
                        <incipit locus="1" locusNew="2">Gratias agimus deo patri</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="2">
                            <decoNote>Initial <q>Gra</q> in red, filled with yellow</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="11">
                            <decoNote>On p. <locus>11</locus> initial in red and green with bird's head: on pp.
                                    <locus>42</locus>, <locus>43</locus>, <locus locusNew="74">72</locus>, etc. roughly
                                ornamented initials</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Bradshaw 1893">Mr. Bradshaw's account of the manuscript in his
                                tract on <hi rend="italic">The Early Collection of Canons known as the Hibernensis</hi>
                                (Cambridge, 1893)</ref> is the best available. I quote the principal part of it
                            here</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <q><ref type="ms" target="CCC279">MS 279</ref> in the collection given by <name
                                    type="person">Archbishop Parker</name> to <name type="place">Corpus Christi
                                    College</name> is another MS. of which it is very difficult to give in a few words a
                                thoroughly satisfactory account. It contains four principal pieces, of which the third
                                and fourth belong together, all transcribed by a very inaccurate copyist of the
                                    <date>X</date>th or <date>IX-X</date>th century. The first (leaves <locus
                                    locusNew="1">1r</locus>-<locus locusNew="11">6r</locus>) is the <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Synodus Episcoporum id est Patrici Auxilii et Issernini</hi>, a set of canons
                                printed by <ref type="bibl" target="Spelman 1639">Spelman</ref> (and from him by others)
                                from this copy. Indeed they have not been preserved at all except here and in the
                                citations from them which occur in the <hi rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi>. The second
                                (leaves <locus locusNew="12">6r</locus>-<locus locusNew="105">55r</locus>) is a
                                collection of testimonia arranged roughly under certain subjects, some having rubrics
                                and some not, but without any apparent method or sequence. It begins with some dicta of
                                    <name type="person">St Augustine</name> de conjugum ratione. The authorities are
                                such as are cited in the <hi rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi>, and in many cases the
                                passages are identical. They include <name type="person">Patricius</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Gildas</name>, and the latest author cited is <name type="person"
                                    >Isidorus</name>. But the collection is certainly not derived from the <hi
                                    rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi>, being rather a compilation drawn independently from
                                the same sources; and as under some heads passages are cited from <name type="person"
                                    >Gildas</name> which do not occur in the <hi rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi>, it
                                follows that the compilation must have been made in some district where his writings
                                were accessible; and we thus obtain some sort of clue to the locality in which it
                                originated. The third and fourth pieces are (3) the <hi rend="italic">Liber ex Lege
                                    Moysi</hi> (<locus locusNew="106">55v</locus>-<locus locusNew="159">80r</locus>) and
                                (4) a series of extracts, in order, from the A-text of the <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Hibernensis</hi> (<locus locusNew="161">81r</locus>-<locus locusNew="187"
                                    >94r</locus>), with some independent paragraphs, many of Irish origin, interposed
                                    (<locus locusNew="159">80r</locus>-<locus locusNew="161">81v</locus>) between the
                                two, and others of a different kind at the end (<locus locusNew="187">94r</locus>-<locus
                                    locusNew="188">96v</locus>), the last breaking off abruptly (<locus locusNew="188"
                                    >96v</locus>) in consequence of the loss of two leaves
                                    (<locus>97r</locus>-<locus>98v</locus>) at the end of the last quire.</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <q>The <hi rend="italic">Liber ex lege Moysi</hi> is a collection of extracts, in order,
                                from Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy, which, so far as I can ascertain, is
                                only known to exist in the position in which we here find it. It will be seen below that
                                in three of the <name type="place">Brittany</name> manuscripts in our list (nos. <ref
                                    type="ms" target="BNF182">4</ref>, <ref type="ms" target="LBLOE3">7</ref>, <ref
                                    type="ms" target="BMO221">10</ref>), it occurs prefixed to the A-text of the <hi
                                    rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi>. In one of these (no. <ref type="ms" target="BNF182"
                                    >4</ref>) it follows immediately upon the general rubric or title of the <hi
                                    rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi>, while in another (no. <ref type="ms" target="LBLOE3"
                                    >7</ref>) it follows immediately upon the introductory paragraphs <hi rend="italic"
                                    >De synodis</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Index titulorum</hi> at the beginning of
                                the <hi rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi>; facts which clearly point to some connexion
                                between the two works, at least so far as their origin is concerned. The series of
                                extracts from the <hi rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi> begins (after a passage from Tit.
                                8, <hi rend="italic">De recapitulatione septem graduum</hi>, Cap. 2, which serves as an
                                introduction) with Tit. 1, <hi rend="italic">De episcopo</hi>, Cap. 3, and goes on to
                                Tit. 48 (your <ref type="bibl" target="Wasserschleben 1874"><hi rend="footnote">Dr.
                                        Wasserschleben's</hi> 50</ref>), <hi rend="italic">De reliquiis in deserto
                                    humatis</hi>, Cap. 1. Of the paragraphs at the end of the volume I have nothing to
                                say in connexion with our subject; but those which immediately follow the <hi
                                    rend="italic">Liber ex lege Moysi</hi> are of particular interest to us, as it is to
                                them that we shall have to look for our best clue to the history of the MS. Only let me
                                first draw attention to two points, of which the bearing will be more clearly seen when
                                I come to speak of the <name type="place">Brittany</name> MSS.</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <q>Of the four principal pieces in the present volume nos. 1, 2, and 4 are quite free from
                                any interlinear or marginal gloss; while in no. 3 (the <hi rend="italic">Liber ex lege
                                    Moysi</hi>) and in the paragraphs of Irish origin appended to it, glosses are more
                                or less thickly strewn, for the most part Latin, but in about a dozen cases Irish. These
                                Irish glosses have been printed by <ref type="bibl" target="Stokes and Strachan 1903">Mr
                                    Whitley Stokes</ref> from the copies which I sent him; and from his commentary it is
                                clear that, judging from the confusion of s and f and other mistakes, they cannot have
                                been written by a scribe who knew anything of the Irish language. The character is
                                certainly not that which would be used by an Irish scribe, even on the continent, in
                                writing words in his own language. We are therefore brought to the conclusion that the
                                copyist of this MS. must have had before him a manuscript already containing these Irish
                                glosses, and must have been employed in a locality where such books were preserved
                                ...</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <q>I am inclined to think that the present volume may have been copied from three several
                                manuscripts containing respectively, (1) the <hi rend="italic">Synodus Patricii</hi>,
                                (2) the <hi rend="italic">Augustini Dicta de conjugum raione, etc.</hi> and (3) the <hi
                                    rend="italic">Liber ex lege Moysi</hi> and Hibernensis-extracts; and that this third
                                manuscript may have been copied from two others, one containing the <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Liber ex lege Moysi</hi> with paragraphs at the end, all more or less noted with
                                Latin and Irish glosses, and the other containing a set of excerpta from the <hi
                                    rend="italic">Hibernensis</hi>. I do not wish to lay any great stress on the
                                necessity of its having originated in this particular way; but it is as well to show how
                                the present result may have been produced.</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <q>Now that we have reached this point, it becomes clear that, in order to ascertain
                                anything definitely concerning the origin of this manuscript, we must look (1)
                                internally, to the <hi rend="italic">Synodus Patricii</hi> which forms no. 1, the
                                citations from <name type="person">Patricius</name> and <name type="person"
                                    >Gildas</name> in no. 2, and the <hi rend="italic">Liber ex lege Moysi</hi> with its
                                appended paragraphs and Irish glosses in no. 3; and (2) externally, to what we can learn
                                of its later history.</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <q>This latter point, concerning its external history, is easily disposed of. The book came
                                to <name type="place">Cambridge</name> on <name type="person">Archbishop Parker</name>'s
                                death in <date>1575</date>, and belonged to him for some time previous to that date. It
                                bears at present no mark at all to indicate any earlier ownership, but a little patience
                                has fortunately brought this to light. In printing the canons of the <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Synodus Patricii</hi> (<ref type="bibl" target="Haddan and Stubbs 1873">Councils,
                                    Vol. 2, page 330, note a</ref>) <name type="person">Mr Haddan</name> says : <q>There
                                    is another (very imperfect) copy of them (<date>xvth</date> century) in <ref
                                        type="ms" target="CCC298">MS 298, no. 22</ref>.</q> But, on examining this <ref
                                    type="ms" target="CCC298">MS 298</ref> in <date>1879</date>, I found that the latter
                                part of the volume was not a <date>xvth</date> century MS., but a mass of colectanea
                                made by <name type="person">Parker</name>, and by others for him, from various
                                manuscripts; and that the incomplete copy of our canons mentioned by <ref type="bibl"
                                    target="Haddan and Stubbs 1873">Haddan</ref> is a transcript, from the very MS. 279
                                which is now under discussion, in the familiar handwriting of <name type="person"
                                    >Parker</name> himself, who has written at the top the following heading : <q>Ex
                                    libro quodam vetusto ecclesiae <name type="place">wigornensis</name>.</q> From this
                                it follows that the original, at the time this was written, had been lent to <name
                                    type="person">Archbishop Parker</name> from the library of <name type="place"
                                    >Worcester</name> cathedral, and that it afterwards passed, like many more of the
                                most precious possessions of our cathedral and monastic libraries, into the private
                                library of the Archbishop. Once traced to <name type="place">Worcester</name>, it is not
                                difficult to see how the book may have come to <name type="place">England</name> (for it
                                was certainly not written in either <name type="place">England</name> or <name
                                    type="place">Ireland</name>) with one of the Norman or Lotharingian bishops
                                introduced in the <date>eleventh</date> century by <name type="person">Edward the
                                    Confessor</name> or <name type="person">William the Conqueror</name></q>
                            <hi rend="footnote">I note that <ref type="bibl" target="Elrington and Todd 1847-64k">Ussher
                                        (<hi rend="italic">Original of Corbes</hi>, etc. Opera XI 433)</ref> says <q>In
                                    a very ancient book which belonged to the cathedral church of <name type="place"
                                        >Worcester</name>, and may now be seen in <name type="place">Benett
                                        College</name> library in <name type="place">Cambridge</name>, there are extant
                                    certain canons bearing this inscription 'Synodus episcoporum id est Patricii,
                                    Auxilii, Issernini.' </q> [<name type="person">M. R. J.</name>]</hi>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>The last text in the volume ends imperfectly</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="188">Item <name type="person">gregorius</name>. quedam femina sanctimonialis
                            in ea ecclesia sepulta iuxta altare pars</explicit>

                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, but not by a second person</p>
                            <p>msCheck: EB 27/11/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
