<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC002I">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>2I</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Under C. 2</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>356</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">The Bury Bible</head>
                <head type="James">Bibliorum Pars I</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">522</height>
                        <width unit="mm">360</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">20.6 x 14</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 357</extent>
                    <supplied>(now bound in three parts)</supplied>, <layout>double columns of 42 lines</layout>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xii</origDate>, <handNote>in a magnificent round hand</handNote>, <decoNote>and with
                        splendid ornaments</decoNote>.</p>
                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num> (1 canc.) I<num>10</num> (wants 4 and 7: 8 is a double leaf),
                            II<num>8</num>-XLIV<num>8</num> XLV<num>6</num> (wants 5, 6)</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">The book comes from <name type="place">Bury St Edmunds Abbey</name>. On the
                    upper corner of f. <locus>2r</locus> (first leaf of text) is a mark rather smaller than in most Bury
                    books, but of the same kind: B. 1.<lb/> The press-mark shows that this was the first book in class
                    B. The B here stands for <hi rend="italic">Biblia</hi>.<lb/> Further, at f. <locus>322r</locus> the
                    edge of the leaf has been mended with a patch of vellum in <origDate>cent. xv</origDate> on which
                        <decoNote>is sketched a crowned head (cut off at the neck) and a scroll inscribed <hi
                            rend="italic">hic, hic, hic</hi></decoNote>. This represents <name type="person">St
                        Edmund</name>'s head, which called out <q>Here, here,</q> to those who were searching for it
                    after the martyrdom. It fixes the provenance in a very satisfactory way.<lb/> In the old catalogue
                        (<date>cent. xii, xiii</date>) of the Abbey books preserved in a <ref type="ms" target="CPC047"
                        >MS. at Pembroke College</ref> and printed in my <ref type="bibl" target="James 1895"><hi
                            rend="italic">Essays on the Abbey of Bury</hi>, 1895, p. 23</ref>, the second item is
                        <q>Bibliotheca in duo uolumina (!)</q>: and in the <ref type="bibl" target="Arnold 1892"><hi
                            rend="italic">Gesta Sacristarum</hi>, Arnold, <hi rend="italic">Memorials of Bury St Edmunds
                            Abbey</hi> (Rolls Series II, p. 290)</ref> in the account of <name type="person"
                        >Hervey</name> (sacrist under <name type="person">Anselm</name> in <date>1121-1148</date>) this
                    passage occurs:<lb/>
                    <q>Iste <name type="person">Herveus</name> frater <name type="person">Taleboti prioris</name> omnes
                        expensas inuenit fratri suo priori in scribenda magna bibliotheca et manu <name type="person"
                            >magistri Hugonis</name> incomparabiliter fecit depingi. Qui cum non inueniret in partibus
                        nostris pelles uitulinas sibi accommodas, in <name type="place">Scotiae</name> partibus
                        parchamenas comparauit.</q><lb/> This passage seems to refer specially to the illuminating of
                    the Bible in question. I interpret it thus: that <name type="place">Hervey</name> found the money
                    for his brother the prior to have a great Bible written, and had it painted after a matchless sort
                    by the hand of <name type="person">Master Hugo</name>. The latter not finding vellum to suit him in
                    our district procured parchment from <name type="place">Ireland</name>.<lb/> Clearly there cannot
                    have been any difficulty in getting good vellum to write upon in <name type="place">England</name>.
                    But the special vellum required by the painter was a superior and rarer article. Now it will be
                    found that in this Bible all or almost all of the paintings are done upon separate pieces of vellum
                    which have been pasted down on the leaves of the book.<lb/> I have no hesitation therefore in
                    identifying the volume before us with a portion of the Bible of <name type="person">Magister
                        Hugo</name>. It is most interesting to have a work of this artist preserved. Like many workers
                    of his time, he exercised more than one craft. He is recorded to have made the bronze doors of <name
                        type="place">St Edmund's Church</name>, to have carved a fine rood for it, and to have cast a
                    great bell.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iii + 1-121 + iv-vi</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="enm">Latin with some later scribbles in Middle
                        English.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1v" locusEnd="121v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Bury Bible</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="1r">blank except for scribbles of <origDate>cent. xv</origDate> viz.</ab>
                        <ab locus="1r">To <name type="person">master Adam</name> this be deliuered (?) with spede</ab>
                        <ab locus="1r">Hec sunt nomina filiorum israel etc.</ab>
                        <ab locus="1v">
                            <decoNote>Full page initial to <name type="author">Jerome</name>'s Prologue</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="1v">
                            <decoNote>At top in red</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="1v">Incipit epistola <name type="author">beati Ieronimi</name> presbiteri ad
                            paulinum in omnibus diuine hystorie libris</rubric>
                        <ab>Text</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="1v">Frater Ambrosius</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="1v">
                            <decoNote>The letters after the initial being red, blue, crimson and green capitals.<lb/>
                                The page is framed in double bands of gold between which are acanthus and vine patterns
                                of classical aspect<lb/> In the stalk of the F are three medallions framed in gold, and
                                with grounds of dark red representing:<lb/> a. A centaur galloping, with long green
                                shield, and lance with pennon.<lb/> b. A man in cap and cloak, his R. foot gone, wearing
                                a wooden leg attached to his knee, running after a hare which he is clipping with
                                shears.<lb/> c. A mermaid holding two fishes.<lb/> Below this a man with basket
                                gathering grapes.<lb/> The main ground of the letter is blue, and it consists of
                                conventional foliage in gold, red, green, pink, purple, blue, in which are introduced
                                bearded human heads with gold horns, a man with a mace, white birds, and two splendid
                                purple apes, drawn from the life.<lb/> The whole work is magnificent.<lb/> The leaf is a
                                double one</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="2r">
                            <decoNote>Col. 1 is in coloured capitals, red, blue, green, yellow, and contains 13 lines of
                                8-10 letters each</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="5v">Explicit Epistola</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="5v">Incipit prologus <name type="author">beati Ieronimi presbiteri</name> in
                            libro Bresith idest Genesis</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="5v">Desiderii mei</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="5v">
                            <decoNote>Magnificent initial D on a piece of vellum pasted on to the leaf</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="6r">Explicit prologus. Incipiunt Capitula</rubric>
                        <ab>Genesis has 79 capitula (wrongly numbered)</ab>
                        <ab>After this a leaf is unhappily gone, which must have contained the frontispiece to
                            Genesis</ab>
                        <ab locus="7r">(a double leaf) <decoNote>has seven lines of writing in red, blue, green and
                                yellow capitals</decoNote></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="7r">Principio</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="7r">super aquas</explicit>
                        <ab>Genesis ends</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="32r">Explicit liber Bresith id est genesis. habet versus tria milia
                            octingentos</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="32r">Incipiunt capitula libri Hellesmoth idest Exodi (xxi)</rubric>
                        <ab locus="32v">Two-thirds of f. <locus>32v</locus> are blank. A picture has been stripped
                            off</ab>
                        <ab locus="33r">The first column with the initial to Exodus and beginning of text <decoNote>in
                                coloured capitals</decoNote> (as before) is a patch stuck on</ab>
                        <rubric locus="53v">Explicit Ellesmoth idest Exodus habet versus quatuor milia</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="53v">Capitula of Leviticus (xvi)</ab>
                        <ab locus="54r">A picture which filled almost all of f. <locus>54r</locus> has been stripped
                            off</ab>
                        <!--                                                            <ab locus="54r">Music in white mensural notation on 4-line stave</ab>-->
                        <ab locus="54v">Leviticus. <decoNote>Decorative initial, not stuck on</decoNote></ab>
                        <rubric locus="69r">Explicit liber Leviticus qui hebraice dicitur vaiecra havet versus II
                                CCC<abbr rend="superscript">tos</abbr></rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="69r">Capitula of Numbers (xxxi)</ab>
                        <ab locus="70r">(double leaf). Frontispiece to Numbers, full-page. <decoNote>Double gold frame
                                with classical leaf-pattern on black ground<lb/> Two pictures. Above: Blue ground. On L.
                                the Father nimbed, with white hair and beard, seated upon clouds (red, blue and green
                                with jagged edges) holds a gold tablet with arched top. On R. the Son seated on similar
                                clouds, nimbed and bearded, holds a gold staff. Each points downwards.<lb/> The Father
                                is in purple over blue, the Son in red (purplish) over orange, over green. Their mantles
                                are edged with gold.<lb/> Behind each is a green panel.<lb/> Below. Blue ground with
                                green panel in C.<lb/> On L. a group of six men face R.; one leans on axe, one sits on
                                the ground. They are the people or the spies. On R. <name type="person">Moses</name>
                                (not nimbed or horned) addresses them: behind him is <name type="person">Aaron</name>
                                and a group of six or seven elders. <name type="person">Aaron</name> is older
                                (blue-haired)</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="70r">Names have been scribbled in <origDate>cent. xv</origDate> on the ground,
                            e.g. <q>populus</q>, <q>Aaron</q>, and: <q>tome portur</q></ab>
                        <ab locus="70v">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial to Numbers, not stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="92r">Explicit liber Numeri qui hebraice dicitur vaiedaber habet versus
                            III</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="92r">Capitula of Deuteronomy (152)</ab>
                        <ab locus="94r">Full-page frontispiece to Deuteronomy, double leaf</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="94r">
                            <decoNote>Border and backgrounds as for Numbers</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="94r">
                            <decoNote>Above. On L. the Son (?) nimbed, with golden rod. <name type="person">Moses</name>
                                nimbed, horned and white-haired, holds book inscribed (<origDate>xiv</origDate>) <q>hec
                                    dicit dominus deus</q> and addresses five men seated on R.<lb/> Below. <name
                                    type="person">Moses</name> in C. horned, nimbed, white-haired, holding gold tables,
                                turns to four men on L. and points to a mount on R. on which is a tree with two white
                                birds, a blue ram? a purple goat and two red pigs. Flames(?), like the <q>clouds</q> of
                                the upper picture to Numbers, break out of the mount. This has to do with the law of
                                unclean beasts, etc.</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="94v">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial, not stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="113v">Explicit Addabarim quod Grece dicitur Deuteronium Latine secunda lex habet
                            versus duo milia sescentos</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="113v">Prol. to <name type="person">Joshua</name> and Judges</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="113v">Tandem finito pentatheuco</incipit>
                        <ab locus="114r">Argumentum</ab>
                        <incipit locus="114r">Ihesus filius naue in typum</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="114r">regna describit</explicit>
                        <ab locus="114r">Capitula of <name type="person">Joshua</name> (xxxii)</ab>
                        <ab locus="115r">
                            <decoNote>has been a double leaf with full-page picture, now stripped off</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="115r" locusNew="115v">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 01/08/08</p>
                            <p>remarks: the "old catalogue" mentioned by James is Pembroke College Cambridge 47 (per
                                CBMLC, Benedictine's Volume, p. 50</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
