<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC002II">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>2II</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Under C. 2</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>356</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">The Bury Bible</head>
                <head type="James">Bibliorum Pars I</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">522</height>
                        <width unit="mm">360</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">20.6 x 14</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 357</extent>
                    <supplied>(now bound in three parts)</supplied>, <layout>double columns of 42 lines</layout>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xii</origDate>, <handNote>in a magnificent round hand</handNote>, <decoNote>and with
                        splendid ornaments</decoNote>.</p>
                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num> (1 canc.) I<num>10</num> (wants 4 and 7: 8 is a double leaf),
                            II<num>8</num>-XLIV<num>8</num> XLV<num>6</num> (wants 5, 6)</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">The book comes from <name type="place">Bury St Edmunds Abbey</name>. On the
                    upper corner of f. <locus>2r</locus> (first leaf of text) is a mark rather smaller than in most Bury
                    books, but of the same kind: B. 1.<lb/> The press-mark shows that this was the first book in class
                    B. The B here stands for <hi rend="italic">Biblia</hi>.<lb/> Further, at f. <locus>322r</locus> the
                    edge of the leaf has been mended with a patch of vellum in <origDate>cent. xv</origDate> on which is
                    sketched a crowned head (cut off at the neck) and a scroll inscribed <hi rend="italic">hic, hic,
                        hic</hi>. This represents <name type="person">St Edmund</name>'s head, which called out <q>Here,
                        here,</q> to those who were searching for it after the martyrdom. It fixes the provenance in a
                    very satisfactory way.<lb/> In the old catalogue (<date>cent. xii, xiii</date>) of the Abbey books
                    preserved in a <ref type="ms" target="CPC047">MS. at Pembroke College</ref> and printed in my <ref
                        type="bibl" target="James 1895"><hi rend="italic">Essays on the Abbey of Bury</hi>, 1895, p.
                        23</ref>, the second item is <q>Bibliotheca in duo uolumina (!)</q>: and in the <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Arnold 1892"><hi rend="italic">Gesta Sacristarum</hi>, Arnold, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Memorials of Bury St Edmunds Abbey</hi> (Rolls Series II, p. 290)</ref> in the account of
                        <name type="person">Hervey</name> (sacrist under <name type="person">Anselm</name> in
                        <date>1121-1148</date>) this passage occurs:<lb/>
                    <q>Iste <name type="person">Herveus</name> frater <name type="person">Taleboti prioris</name> omnes
                        expensas inuenit fratri suo priori in scribenda magna bibliotheca et manu <name type="person"
                            >magistri Hugonis</name> incomparabiliter fecit depingi. Qui cum non inueniret in partibus
                        nostris pelles uitulinas sibi accommodas, in <name type="place">Scotiae</name> partibus
                        parchamenas comparauit.</q><lb/> This passage seems to refer specially to the illuminating of
                    the Bible in question. I interpret it thus: that <name type="place">Hervey</name> found the money
                    for his brother the prior to have a great Bible written, and had it painted after a matchless sort
                    by the hand of <name type="person">Master Hugo</name>. The latter not finding vellum to suit him in
                    our district procured parchment from <name type="place">Ireland</name>.<lb/> Clearly there cannot
                    have been any difficulty in getting good vellum to write upon in <name type="place">England</name>.
                    But the special vellum required by the painter was a superior and rarer article. Now it will be
                    found that in this Bible all or almost all of the paintings are done upon separate pieces of vellum
                    which have been pasted down on the leaves of the book.<lb/> I have no hesitation therefore in
                    identifying the volume before us with a portion of the Bible of <name type="person">Magister
                        Hugo</name>. It is most interesting to have a work of this artist preserved. Like many workers
                    of his time, he exercised more than one craft. He is recorded to have made the bronze doors of <name
                        type="place">St Edmund's Church</name>, to have carved a fine rood for it, and to have cast a
                    great bell.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iii + 122-241 + iv-vi</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="122r" locusEnd="241v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Bury Bible</title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="128v">Explicit liber <name type="person">Josue Bennun</name> habet versus I DCCC
                            L</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="128v">Capitula of Judges (xviii)</ab>
                        <ab locus="129r">has been double. <decoNote>Full-page picture stripped off</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="129v">
                            <decoNote>Large decorative initial on verso</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="143v">Explicit liber Sophim id est ludicum habet versus I septingentos
                            quinquaginta</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="143v">Capitula of <name type="person">Ruth</name> (x). <name type="author"
                                >Ieronimus</name> in lib. ruth. Ruth moabitis (2.5 lines)</ab>
                        <ab locus="143v">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="145v">Explicit liber <name type="person">Ruth</name> habet versus mille ducentos
                            quinquaginta (!)</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="145v">Prologue to Kings</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="145v">E (sic) viginti et duas litteras</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="146v">Capitula (not <supplied>all</supplied> numbered <supplied>- first 33
                                numbered</supplied>)</ab>
                        <rubric locus="146r" locusNew="147r">Expliciunt capitula scripta a <name type="person">beati
                                Ieronimi</name> in libro Regum i<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> et ii<abbr
                                rend="superscript">o</abbr></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="147r"><name type="person">Samuhel</name> in <name type="person">heli</name>
                            mortuo</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="147r">imperii sacramenta testatur</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="147r">Explicit prologus</rubric>
                        <ab locus="146r" locusNew="147v">
                            <decoNote>A double leaf. On verso frontispiece to 1 Kings.<lb/> Border and backgrounds as
                                before.<lb/> Above. <name type="person">Elkanah</name> on L. gives robes to <name
                                    type="person">Hannah</name> and <name type="person">Peninnah</name> (the former
                                bowing).<lb/> Below. On L. <name type="person">Eli</name> in low white mitre, red
                                chasuble with gold pall, blue dalmatic or tunicle, stole, alb, with crosier, stands
                                under a building and listens to <name type="person">Hannah</name> who stands (separated
                                from him by a shaft) praying. On R. <name type="person">Hannah</name> in bed, flames or
                                clouds in front; above, a seated nurse tends the child <name type="person"
                                >Samuel</name>.<lb/> Names have been scribbled on the background, e.g. <q>
                                    <name type="person">Colchestra</name>
                                </q>.</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="147r" locusNew="148r">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="154r">
                            <decoNote>A little grotesque man is sketched in the margin</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="167r">Explicit <name type="person">Samuhel</name> liber regum primus, habens
                            versus duo milia trecentos</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="167r">Capitula libri II (xviii)</ab>
                        <ab locus="167v">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial, stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="182r">Explicit <name type="person">Samuhel</name> liber regum secundus habet
                            versus II CC</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="182r">Capitula libri III (xviii)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="182v">Prologue</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="182v">Malachi idest tertius</incipit>
                        <ab locus="183r">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial, stuck on: dark green ground</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="200v">Explicit <name type="person">Malachim</name> idest regum liber tertius
                            habet versus II quingentos</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="200v">Capitula libri IV (110)</ab>
                        <ab locus="201v">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial, not stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="218v">Explicit liber regum IIII</rubric>
                        <ab>f.<locus>219r</locus>-<locus>219v</locus>
                            <decoNote>now blank has had a full-page picture stuck upon the verso</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="220r">Prologue to <name type="person">Isaiah</name></ab>
                        <incipit locus="220r">Nemo cum prophetas</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="220r">
                            <decoNote>Initial on green and blue ground. Above, a man with a mace holding a rope attached
                                to muzzle of a (red) bear below on L. At bottom lie three round cakes (?) and a wooden
                                trough with a long handle</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="220v">
                            <decoNote>Initial to <name type="person">Isaiah</name>, stuck on. The prophet with white
                                hair and beard seated on rocks, many coloured, holding out blank scroll. Divine Hand
                                above. Green ground</decoNote>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 01/08/08</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
