<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC339">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>339</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>O. 13</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>217</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Richard of Devizes OSB (attrib.), Annales Wintonienses, Chronicon de tempore regis
                    Ricardi. Peter of Ickham OSB, Compilatio de gestis Britonum et Anglorum</head>
                <head type="James">Richard of Devizes. Peter de Ickham, etc.</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum (and paper)</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">220</height>
                        <width unit="mm">172</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <layout>two volumes</layout>, <extent>ff. 1 + 6 + 43 + 51</extent>.</p>

                <p function="Multivolume"><lb/><label>Volume I:</label>
                    <measureGrp type="James">8.6 x 6.7</measureGrp>, <layout>31 lines to a page</layout>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xii-xiii early</origDate>.<lb/>
                    <label>Volume II:</label>
                    <measureGrp type="James">8.5 x 7</measureGrp>, <layout>36 lines to a page</layout>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xiv</origDate>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1 vellum flyleaf, 6 paper, 1<num>8</num>-4<num>8</num> 5<num>6</num> (6 canc.)
                            6<num>8</num> (wants 7, 8) || a<num>16</num> b<num>12</num> c<num>8</num>-e<num>8</num> (1
                        canc.)</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance" rend="afterContents"><supplied>The material on f.
                            <locus>91r</locus>-<locus>91v</locus></supplied> points to the book having been at <name
                        type="place">Lilleshull</name> or in its neighbourhood when this was written.</p>

                <p function="Additions">Flyleaf <supplied>(ff. <locus>ir</locus>-<locus>iv</locus>)</supplied>, part of
                    a leaf of a <origDate>xv</origDate>th cent. missal <handNote>in very large hand</handNote>. On the
                    six paper leaves <supplied>(ff. <locus>iir</locus>-<locus>viv</locus>)</supplied> is an alphabetical
                    table of cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-vii + 1-94 + c-d</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <milestone n="I" unit="volume"/>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="24v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Richard of Devizes OSB (attrib.)</name>, <title>Annales Wintonienses, to
                                1138</title></head>
                        <head type="Nasmith"><title>Historia <name type="place">Angliae</name> a <name type="person"
                                    >Bruto</name> ad primordia regni <name type="person">Stephani</name> regis</title>
                            [autore <name type="author">Ricardo Divisiensi</name> secundum <name type="person"
                                >Balaeum</name>]</head>
                        <ab>Headed (<origDate>xvi</origDate>)</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="1r"><name type="author">Richardus Divisiensis</name> ut in <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bale 1557">Baleo 28</ref></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Britannia maior insula est ad septentrionem sita</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">In the margin, partly cut off</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">M)agistro ade ! suus de<lb/> meo malo mirum mu <lb/> temporibus accidit ut
                            etiam fi <lb/> placeant sapientibus</ab>
                        <ab>The margins are full of erased entries (see <ref type="bibl" target="Howlett 1886"><hi
                                    rend="italic">Chronicles of Stephen</hi>, etc. III, p. lxxi</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>10r</locus> (margin) is a late note of the foundation of <name type="place"
                                >Cricklade university</name> and on f. <locus>13r</locus> in the same hand a note of the
                            foundation of <name type="place">Oxford</name>. A few other notes in the same hand
                            occur</ab>
                        <ab>and on f. <locus>13r</locus> in the same hand a note of the foundation of <name type="place"
                                >Oxford</name>. A few other notes in the same hand occur</ab>

                        <ab>At <locus>24v</locus> is a break, the text ends (in <date>1138</date>)</ab>
                        <explicit locus="24v"><name type="person">Brianus</name> firmauit <name type="place"
                                >Walingeford</name> et <name type="place">oxoniam</name></explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="24v">After this a note by <name type="author">Bale</name> (?),<q>vsque ad annum
                                domini <date>1245</date> apud <name type="person">Thomam knyght
                            bibliopolam</name></q></ab>

                        <ab>So far the text, as pointed out by Dr Luard (<ref type="bibl" target="Luard 1865"><hi
                                    rend="italic">Annales Monasterienses</hi> II p. xi</ref>), is the source of the <hi
                                rend="italic">Winchester Annals</hi> (<ref type="ms" target="LBLD13">Domit. XIII</ref>):
                            the resemblance is fairly exact down to <date>1066</date></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="25r" locusEnd="43v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Richard of Devizes OSB</name>, <title>Chronicon de tempore regis
                                Ricardi</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="author">Ricardus Divisiensis</name> ad <name type="person"
                                    >Robertum</name> olim priorem Wynton ad Cartusiam migratum de rebus gestis <name
                                    type="person">Ricardi I</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="25r"><handNote>In the same hand</handNote>, beginning with a red initial</ab>
                        <incipit locus="25r">Uenerabili patri et semper domino <name type="person">Rob.</name> olim
                            priori Wintoniensis ecclesie: Suus <name type="author">Ricardus</name> dictus
                            diuisiensis</incipit>

                        <ab>This Chronicle was last edited by <ref type="bibl" target="Howlett 1886">Howlett, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Chronicles of Stephen</hi>, etc. II<supplied>I</supplied> 381-454 (and
                                Introd. LXVIII sqq.)</ref></ab>
                        <ab>It ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="43v">de gratia gentilium consequeretur</explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="43v">The colophon (if any) is obscured by a patch (the greater part of two leaves)
                            of a closely written <origDate>xiii</origDate>th cent. Canon Law MS. pasted over the lower
                            part of f. <locus>43v</locus></ab>
                        <ab>There is but one other copy of this Chronicle (<ref type="ms" target="LBLD13">Domit.
                                XIII</ref>) in the same hand: according to <ref type="bibl" target="Howlett 1886"
                                >Howlett</ref> both are in the autograph of <name type="author">Richard of
                                Devizes</name>. He assigns the date <origDate>1192-1202</origDate> to both MSS</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <milestone n="II" unit="volume"/>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="43v" locusEnd="94v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Peter of Ickham OSB</name>, <title>Compilatio de gestis Britonum et
                                Anglorum</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="author">Petri de Yckham</name> compilatio de gestis Britonum ac Anglorum
                                ad annum <date>1327</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locusNew="43v">On the margins of the patch stuck on f. <locus>43v</locus> are some
                                <origDate>xvi</origDate>th cent. notes referring to the following treatise</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="43v">
                            <q>Hec Historia explicit in ultimo anno Henrici (corr. to <name type="person"
                                >Edwardi</name>) secundi. Hoc est a. d. <date>1327</date>. Verisimile est hunc Authorem
                                fuisse <name type="author">Petrus de Ickham</name>. et alius quispiam ab anno
                                    <date>1272</date> continuauit historiam ad annum <date>1327</date>. vide <ref
                                    type="bibl" target="Bale 1557">Bale 327</ref></q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="43v">
                            <q><name type="place">Cantabrigia</name> facta uniuersitas per Curiam Romanam
                                    <date>1320</date></q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="43v">
                            <q>Author horum annalium fuit <name type="author">Radulphus Remington</name> clericus
                                Eboracensis notarius publicus qui interfuit in illo processu <name type="place"
                                    >Cantabrigiae</name> et habetur in registro Collegii Corporis Christi. In libro qui
                                dicitur Miscellanea Cantabrigiae fol. 135 Et illic introducitur <name type="person"
                                    >Johannes episcopus</name> seruus seruorum dei qui fecit <name type="place"
                                    >Cantabrigiam</name> uniuersitatem tempore <name type="person">Edouardi
                                    secundi</name> etc.</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="43v">Another annotator refers to the Bull of <name type="person">Honorius</name>
                            <date>624</date></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="43v">A third adds: <q>Forte author huius non fuit <name type="author">Rad.
                                    Remington</name> notarius publicus Ebor. qui vixit a. d. <date>1430</date> ut in
                                recordis Cantabrigiae et in pag. 126 in Mescellanea Cantabrigiae apparet</q></ab>
                        <ab>Are some of these notes by <name type="person">Dr Caius</name>?</ab>
                        <ab>Text</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="44r">Non solum audiendis Scripture sacre uerbis aurem sedulus auditor
                            accommodare tenetur</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="44r">qui omnes fere toto regno imperabant</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="44r">De <name type="place">Britannia</name> insula occeani</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="44r"><name type="place">Britannia</name> occeani insula cui quondam <name
                                type="place">Albion</name> nomen fuit</incipit>
                        <ab>Hand changes at f. <locus locusNew="60r">17r</locus>, part of <locus locusNew="59v"
                                >16v</locus> is blank but there is no break. See <ref type="ms" target="CCC427">MS
                                427</ref></ab>
                        <ab>Ends in <date>1327</date></ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="91r">quorum quidam ut prescriptum est mortem ignominiosam non inmerito
                            pertulerunt</explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="91r">
                            <handNote>A large scrawly hand continues</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="91r">Post quem regnauit Edwardus filius eius et dictus est <name
                                type="person">Edwardus tercius</name></incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="91r">After a few lines the accession of <name type="person">Richard II</name> is
                            noted, and it is said that</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="91r"><q>rex iste <name type="person">Ric.</name> versus <name type="place"
                                    >Salop.</name> itinerans pro fine parliamenti faciendo infra <name type="place"
                                    >Monasterium de Lilleshull</name> in festo Conuersionis <name type="person">Sancti
                                    Paule</name> viz. nocte precedente et die illo nocteque sequente qui tunc dies
                                veneris fuit perendi- (<locus locusNew="91v">48v</locus>) navit cum Regina sua filia
                                regis ffrancie</q>. After the king's departure; <q><name type="person">Dux vero
                                    Lancastrie</name> finito parliamento captus febre cum uxore sua <name type="person"
                                    >Katerina</name> ad <name type="place">monasterium de Lilleshull</name> reuersus
                                est</q>. He was received (with his wife) into the fraternity; so also was <name
                                type="person">Will. Chetewynd</name>. <q>Dux vero conuentui xx libros auri contulit.
                                Predicto vero anno isti in fraternitatem recepti fuerunt. Dux predictus cum uxore sua et
                                armigero predicto Dominus <name type="person">Joh. de Cherleton</name>. Dom. de Powys.
                                    <name type="person">Ric. Chelmewyk'</name> armiger prox. regi. <name type="person"
                                    >Will. Thornehull</name> dominus de Eten Costeyn et fflorancia uxor eius. <name
                                    type="person">Rogerus Massy de Wych</name> strenuus armiger predicti ducis. <name
                                    type="person">Dom. Adam persale</name> dom. de ydeshale uxore eius prius recepta.
                                dum <name type="person">Baldewyno ffreuyle</name> erat copulata</q></ab>



                        <ab>The <ref type="ms" target="OBL401">Laudian MS. Misc. 730</ref> (in the Bodleian Library) of <q>
                                <name type="author">Peter of Ickham</name>
                            </q> (which ends at <date>1272</date>) has the note <q>Hic multa desunt ab hoc anno
                                    <date>1272</date> usque ad annum <date>1327</date> et hoc totum habetur in veteri
                                libro ligato<!--liguto - corrected in James Corrigenda--> cum <name type="author"
                                    >Richardo Divisiensi</name>.</q></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="92r">On <locus locusNew="92r">49r</locus> scribbled prayer or invocation to the
                            Virgin</ab>
                        <ab><locus locusNew="92v">49v</locus> blank</ab>
                        <ab>On <locus locusNew="93r">50r</locus> a Confiteor ill-written</ab>
                        <ab><locus locusNew="93v">50v</locus>-<locus locusNew="94v">51v</locus> blank</ab>

                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 8/4/08</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
