<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC349">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>349</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>23. 1</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>344</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Statutes of Cathedrals, etc.</head>
                <head type="James">Statutes of Cathedrals, etc.</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">305</height>
                        <width unit="mm">203</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">12 x 8.2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. A-K, and pp. 310
                        numbered</extent>. Cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate>, <handNote>in various hands</handNote>.</p>



                <p function="Additions"><decoNote>Title in red chalk</decoNote> by <name type="person"
                    >Parker</name>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iii + ff. a-h + j + pp. k-l + pp. 1-88 (89-92 missing) + 93-264 (265-266 missing) +
                        267-310 + ff. iv-v</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="iiir" locusEnd="Dv">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Summa statuti facti I<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr>
                                <name type="person">Elizabethae</name> de reformatione statutorum ecclesiarum
                                cathedralium, D</title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="iiir">Statuta et charte regine de ecclesiis nuper erectis</rubric>

                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="Dv" locusEnd="Dv">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The queen's commission to the archbishop of <name type="place">Canterbury</name>, the
                                bishop of <name type="place">London</name> and the rest of the commissioners for
                                ecclesiastical causes, empowering them to revise and reform the statutes of all
                                cathedral churches, date June 4, <date>anno regni 4</date><abbr rend="superscript"
                                    >to</abbr>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="Er" locusEnd="Er">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>General imperfections in the statutes of <name type="person">king
                                Henry</name></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="Er" locusEnd="Gr">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Reformations of the defects and enormities of the old statutes</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="Hr" locusEnd="Hv">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Doubt arising about the interpretation of a passage in the incorporation of the
                                cathedral church of <name type="place">Canterbury</name> by <name type="person">Henry
                                    VIII</name></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="K" locusEnd="L">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Clause of the queen's commission for the reformation of cathedral churches granted in
                                the first year of her reign</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="1" locusEnd="96">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Delineatio generalis formae statutorum ecclesiarum cathedralium</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="7">
                            <quote>Vide numerum eorum qui sustentabuntur in singulis ecclesiis <name type="place"
                                    >Winton</name>. <name type="place">Eliens</name>. <name type="place">Wigorn</name>.
                                    <name type="place">Norwicens</name>. <name type="place">Petroburg</name>. <name
                                    type="place">Roff</name>. <name type="place">Bristol</name>. <name type="place"
                                    >Glocest</name>. <name type="place">Dunelm</name>. <name type="place"
                                >Carliol</name>.</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="31">
                            <quote>Stipendia decani et prebend. eccl. <name type="place">Cantuar</name>. <name
                                    type="place">Winton</name>. <name type="place">Eliens</name>. <name type="place"
                                    >Wigorn</name>. <name type="place">Petroburg</name>. <name type="place"
                                    >Norwicens</name>. <name type="place">Roff</name>. <name type="place"
                                >Bristol</name>. <name type="place">Glocest</name>. <name type="place">Dunelm</name>.
                                    <name type="place">Cestr</name>. <name type="place">Carliol</name>.</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="71">
                            <quote>Stipendia ministrorum eccl. <name type="place">Cantuar</name>. <name type="place"
                                    >Winton</name>. <name type="place">Eliens</name>. <name type="place">Wigorn</name>.
                                    <name type="place">Petroburg</name>. <name type="place">Roff</name>. <name
                                    type="place">Glocest</name>. <name type="place">Dunelm</name>. <name type="place"
                                    >Carliol</name>.</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Cf. <ref type="ms" target="CCC120">MS 120. II</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="97" locusEnd="100">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Stipends of the dean, prebends, etc. of the cathedral of <name type="place"
                                    >Canterbury</name></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="101" locusEnd="104">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Appearance of <name type="person">Thomas Goodwin dean of Canterbury</name> before the
                                commissioners Aug. 31, <date>1569</date>, when he delivered to them certain writings
                                belonging to the said church; and injunctions then given him by the
                                commissioners</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="105" locusEnd="116">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta permutationis de ecclesia cathedrali <name type="place">Cantuar</name>. per
                                    <name type="person">Henricum VIII</name>. 37<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr>
                                regni</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="117" locusEnd="124">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta fundationis ejusdem ecclesiae 32<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr>
                                <name type="person">Hen. VIII</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Cf. <ref type="ms" target="CCC120">MS 120. I</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="125" locusEnd="192">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta dotationis ejusdem ecclesiae 33<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr>
                                <name type="person">Hen. VIII</name></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="193" locusEnd="200">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Admissiones prebendariorum ejusdem ecclesiae ab anno <date>1546</date> ad annum
                                    <date>1560</date></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="201" locusEnd="204">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Order and names of the prebendaries since the erection <date>1546</date> [to
                                    <date>1566</date>]</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="205" locusEnd="286">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta dotationis [vel permutationis] ecclesiae cathedralis de <name type="place"
                                    >Wigorn</name>. 33<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr>
                                <name type="person">Hen. VIII</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Cf. <ref type="ms" target="CCC120">MS 120. 34</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="16" locusStart="287" locusEnd="294">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta permutationis ejusdem ecclesiae I <name type="person">Edw. VI</name></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="17" locusStart="295" locusEnd="309">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta fundationis ejusdem ecclesiae 33<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr>
                                <name type="person">Hen. VIII</name></title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>


                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: KW 6.11.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
