<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>


                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC355">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>355</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>2. 5</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>308</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">John Colet, Epistolae beati Pauli ad Romanos expositio, Geneseos expositio ad
                    Radulphum</head>

                <head type="James">John Colet in Romanos et in Genesim</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">285</height>
                        <width unit="mm">185</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">11.2 x 7.2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 112</extent>, <layout>22
                        lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xvi early</origDate>, <handNote>in a very fine Roman
                        hand</handNote>.</p>


                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>8</num>-m<num>8</num> | n<num>8</num> o<num>8</num></collation>.</p>


                <p function="Provenance">Written doubtless by <name type="person">Peter Meghen</name> the scribe of many
                    of <name type="author">Colet</name>'s works. The last two quires in another hand, <layout>20 lines
                        to a page</layout>. This book much resembles <ref type="ms" target="CEC245">Emmanuel College MS.
                        245</ref>, which contains <name type="author">Colet</name> on I Corinthians.</p>



                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iv + pp. 1-228 + ff. v-viii</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="3" locusEnd="194">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">John Colet</name>, <title>Epistolae beati Pauli ad Romanos
                                expositio</title></head>


                        <head type="James">
                            <name type="author">John Colet</name>
                            <title>in Romanos</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab locusNew="3">Title <handNote>in red in <name type="person">Bishop Tunstall</name>'s
                                hand</handNote></ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="3">Scripta <name type="author">Ioannis Colett</name> professoris theologie in
                            epistolam diui <name type="person">Pauli</name> ad Romanos</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="3">Marginal notes by a <name type="person">Parkerian scribe</name>:<lb/> Hic
                            titulus scriptus erat cum aliis insequentibus manu <name type="person">Cutheberti
                                Dunelm.</name> ep. ut testatur subscriptio eius in fine statutorum <name type="place"
                                >eccl. Dunelmensis</name>. et ut probari potest per scriptum suum in libro
                            miscellaneorum E. Pag. 58.<lb/> Hic liber scriptus manu amanuensis <name type="person"
                                >Iohannis Colett</name>, ut videre licet in libro magno duarum translationum <name
                                type="person">Matthaei</name> et <name type="person">Marci</name> script. manu <name
                                type="person">Petri Meghen</name> monoculi teutonis natione Brabantini. Vt ipsemet
                            testatur in fine <name type="person">Marci Euangelistae</name> Anno 1509. 8 Maij</ab>

                        <ab>The MS. of <name type="person">Matthew</name> and <name type="person">Mark</name> referred
                            to is in the <ref type="ms" target="CUL073">University Library Dd. 7. 3</ref>. It was given
                            by <name type="person">Parker</name></ab>
                        <ab>Text</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="3">In epistola quam apostolus <name type="person">Paulus</name> scripsit ad
                            Romanos hominibus illic christiani nominis</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Spaces are left for illuminated initials</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Ends imperfectly</ab>
                        <explicit locus="194">ad honestam et optandam emendationem malorum non</explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="194">Note by <name type="person">Tunstall</name>:<lb/> Supersunt multa ab eodem
                                <name type="author">Joanne Colet</name> scripta in diuum <name type="person"
                                >paulum</name> sed puerorum eius incuria perierunt</ab>

                        <ab>A complete copy of the Lectures is in the <ref type="ms" target="CUL426">University Library
                                Gg. 4. 26</ref> from which the text was edited with translation by <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Lupton 1873">J. H. Lupton, 1873</ref></ab>




                    </msItem>




                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="195" locusEnd="226">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">John Colet</name>, <title>Geneseos expositio ad
                                Radulphum</title></head>


                        <head type="James">
                            <name type="author">John Colet</name>
                            <title>in Genesim</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>Title by <name type="person">Tunstall</name></ab>
                        <rubric locus="195">Scripta <name type="author">Joannis Colet</name> professoris theologie
                            Decani <name type="place">sancti pauli London</name>. In principium geneseos</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="195">Miror sane te optime <name type="person">Radulphe</name> quum voluisti a
                            capite Biblie inchoare</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="199">fac nos te queso participes. Vale</explicit>
                        <incipit locus="199">Parumper de reliquis diebus uti petis in calce Epistole</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="207">me de tedio scribendi paululum leuauerim. Vale</explicit>
                        <incipit locus="207">Tercium nunc deinceps diem aggrediamur</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="222">nos in hiis rebus lucubrasse. Vale</explicit>



                        <incipit locus="222">Salue <name type="person">Radulphe</name> ac cum salute puto te
                            rediisse</incipit>
                        <ab>Ending imperfectly</ab>
                        <explicit locus="226">facere docet <name type="person">Macrobius</name> in Comentario
                            edito</explicit>
                        <ab>Edited by <ref type="bibl" target="Lupton 1876">J. H. Lupton in 1876</ref></ab>


                    </msItem>



                </msContents>



                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text:copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 01.06.2007</p>
                            <p>remarks: </p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>



            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
