<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>


                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC387">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>387</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>1. 1</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>305</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Richard Rolle of Hampole, Commentary on the Psalms</head>

                <head type="James">Hampole on the Psalms</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">440</height>
                        <width unit="mm">300</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">17.4 x 12</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 115 + 1</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 54 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv</origDate>, <handNote>very well
                        written</handNote>
                    <decoNote>with some beautiful English ornament</decoNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1<num>8</num>-14<num>8</num> 15 (1-3 left), 1 flyleaf</collation>.</p>



                <p function="Provenance">On the lower margin of f. <locus>2r</locus> in large letters is:<lb/> Iste
                    liber Constat dompno <name type="person">Johanni Colman</name> Abbati Monasterij de <name
                        type="place">lesnes</name> (an Augustinian priory near <name type="place">Woolwich</name>,
                    otherwise called <name type="place">Westwood</name>).<lb/> Also on <locus>82v</locus>: Iste liber
                    constat dompno <name type="person">Joh. Colman</name> Abbatis(!) monasterij de lesnes in Com.
                    Kanc.</p>

                <p function="Additions">On f. <locus>113r</locus> is scribbled Sum W. Eden (?).</p>

                <p function="Research">The commentary was edited in 1884 by <ref type="bibl" target="Bramley 1884">H. R.
                        Bramley</ref>, Oxford, from <ref type="ms" target="OUC064">MS. University College 64</ref>, and
                    another edition is being prepared for the Early English Text Society.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + 1-115 + i + c-d</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="enm">Latin and Middle English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="115v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Richard Rolle of Hampole</name>, <title>Commentary on the Psalms</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="James">
                            <title><name type="author">Hampole</name> on the Psalms</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="author">Richard Hampole</name>'s commentary on the Psalms</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <quote>The text is in Latin and the commentary in English: after the Psalms are the
                                following hymns with a like commentary, - Confitebor tibi Domine <name type="person"
                                    >Isaiah</name> XII. - Ego dixi in dimidio dierum meorum <name type="person"
                                    >Isaiah</name> XXXVIII. 10. - Exultavit cor meum I <name type="person">Sam.</name>
                                II. I. - Cantemus Domino Exod. XV. - Domine audivi auditionem <name type="person"
                                    >Hab.</name> III. - Audite coeli Deut. XXXII. - Te Deum laudamus. - Benedictus
                                Dominus <name type="person">Luke</name> I. 68. - Benedicite omnia opera. - Nunc dimittis
                                    <name type="person">Luke</name> II. 29. - Symbolum <name type="person"
                                    >Athanasii</name>. - Magnificat anima mea <name type="person">Luke</name> II. 46. -
                                Litania sive supplicatio sanctorum Anglice.</quote>
                        </ab>




                        <ab locus="1r">Prologue</ab>

                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Gret abundance of gostly comfort and ioie in god</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="1r">profitable to hym and to o&#254;ere mo. Here is ended &#254;e
                            prologe</explicit>
                        <ab><decoNote>Border of fine English work on 3 sides</decoNote>. <decoNote>Initial, head of
                                    <name type="person">David</name> crowned on black ground flourished with
                                gold</decoNote></ab>
                        <incipit locus="1v">Beatus uir, etc. In &#254;is psalme first he spekith of crist</incipit>
                        <ab><decoNote>Full border, of very good work</decoNote>.<lb/>
                            <decoNote>Initial, <name type="person">David</name> in blue seated harping, ground dark,
                                trellised with gold and patterned</decoNote>.<lb/>
                            <decoNote>At the lower angles lozenge-shaped medallions with two kings, one in light blue on
                                darker blue ground, the other pink on darker pink</decoNote>. <decoNote>Above on R. an
                                angel, blue on blue</decoNote>.</ab>


                        <rubric locus="21r">Dominus illuminatio</rubric>


                        <ab><decoNote>Fine border, the right portion torn off</decoNote>. <decoNote>Excellent initial,
                                pink on pink</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Other fine borders at ff. <locus>30v</locus>, <locus>40v</locus>,
                                    <locus>50r</locus>, <locus>62v</locus>, <locus>73r</locus>, <locus>83r</locus>,
                                    <locus>103r</locus> (the last to the Cantica)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The penwork of the subordinate initials is excellent</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>Ends with the Litany (in English)</ab>
                        <ab>Martyrs: <name type="person">Seint Richard</name>. Confessors: <name type="person">Seint
                                William</name>. Virgins: <name type="person">Pernel</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Radegunde</name>, <name type="person">Freswithe</name>, <name type="author"
                                >Audre</name></ab>


                        <ab>Ending</ab>

                        <explicit locus="115v">Pes be maad in &#254;i vertu. And plente in &#254;i
                            tours</explicit>

                        <ab>On the lower margin is written very neatly in red and black, the reverse way of the page, a
                            series of verses:<lb/>
                            <lg>
                                <l>Quid valet occeano multos inmittere pisces</l>
                                <l>Addere uel celo sidera stellifero</l>

                                <l>...</l>


                                <l>Quid valet ad summum nos attramenta papirus</l>
                                <l>Atque operam totam perdere quotidie</l>
                                <l>Quamuis multa tibi nonnuncquam carmina missem</l>
                                <l>Pro mercede tamen nulla latina michi</l>

                                <l>etc.</l>
                            </lg></ab>

                        <ab>A few late names and other scribbles on the flyleaf</ab>



                    </msItem>


                </msContents>





                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text:copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, CF 2nd</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 26.6.2007</p>
                            <p>remarks: </p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>



            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
