<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC408">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>408</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>V. 1</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>296</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">John Capgrave OESA, De illustribus Henricis</head>
                <head type="James">Joh. Capgrave de illustribus Henricis</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">213</height>
                        <width unit="mm">150</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">8.4 x 6</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 2 + 70</extent>,
                        <layout>28 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv</origDate>, <handNote>very clearly
                        written</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num>, 1<num>8</num>-6<num>8</num> (8 canc.) 7<num>8</num>-9<num>8</num> (8
                        canc.)</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">Very possibly from <name type="place">Bury</name>. On f. <locus>ir</locus> is
                    an old press-mark C. 4 which would suit the <name type="place">Bury</name> Library, but is more
                    roughly done than usual.</p>
                <p function="Additions">f. <locus>iiv</locus> has <name type="person">Parker</name>ian table of
                    contents.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-ii + pp. 1-140 + ff. c-d</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1" locusEnd="139">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">John Capgrave OESA</name>, <title>De illustribus Henricis</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title><name type="author">Joh. Capgrave</name> de illustribus Henricis</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Liber <name type="author">Ioannis Capgrave</name> de multis Henricis clarissimis ad
                                    <name type="person">Henricum VI. regem Angliae</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Prima pars complectitur vitas <name type="person">Henrici I</name>. <name
                                    type="person">Henrici II</name>. <name type="person">Henrici III</name>. <name
                                    type="person">Henrici IV</name>. <name type="person">Henrici V</name>. <name
                                    type="person">Henrici VI</name>. (imperatorum Allemaniae)</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>In secunda parte continentur vitae <name type="person">Henrici I</name>. <name
                                    type="person">Henrici II</name>. <name type="person">Henrici III</name>. <name
                                    type="person">Henrici IV</name>. <name type="person">Henrici V</name>. <name
                                    type="person">Henrici VI</name>. (regum Angliae)</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>In tertia parte habentur vitae <name type="person">Henrici regis Dacorum</name>.
                                    <name type="person">Henrici regis Franciae</name>. <name type="person">Henrici filii
                                    Ricardi imperatoris</name>. <name type="person">Henrici comitis Campaniae</name>.
                                    <name type="person">Henrici fratris Ludovici</name>. <name type="person">Henrici
                                    ducis Lancastriae</name>. <name type="person">Henrici Bown comitis
                                    Hertfordiae</name>. <name type="person">Henrici de Bello-Monte</name>. <name
                                    type="person">Henrici le Spenser episcopi Norwicensis</name>. <name type="person"
                                    >Henrici Huntindunensis</name>. <name type="person">Henrici de Gandauo</name>. <name
                                    type="person">Henrici doctoris Paris</name></quote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="1"><name type="person">Henrico</name> dei gratia regi anglie et
                            francie</incipit>
                        <ab locus="1">... frater <name type="author">iohannes</name>
                            <handNote>( <name type="author">capgrave</name> added later above line in what is said to be
                                    <name type="person">Bale</name>'s hand <hi rend="footnote"><ref type="bibl"
                                        target="Hingeston 1858a">Hingeston</ref> points out that the book once belonged
                                    to <name type="person">Bale</name></hi>)</handNote> doctor minimus, etc.</ab>
                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="139">et in puritate corporis et anime decedat. ad laudem domini nostri Ihesu
                            Christi qui cum deo patre et spiritu sancto viuit et regnat in secula seculorum.
                            amen</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="139">ffeliciter per <name type="author">Capgrave</name></rubric>

                        <ab>This is one of two extant copies of the book, the other being <ref type="ms" target="LBLTA8"
                                >Tiberius A. VIII</ref>. This one is the autograph of the author. The book was edited by
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Hingeston 1858a">F. C. Hingeston in 1858 for the Rolls Series.
                                He gives a full account of it on pp. li-liii of his introduction</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 10/4/08</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
