<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC048">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>48</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>E. 3</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>46</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Bible</head>
                <head type="James">Biblia</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">324</height>
                        <width unit="mm">212</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">12.7 x 8.3</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 276 + 3</extent>,
                        <layout>in double, triple and quadruple columns of 63 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xii
                        late</origDate>, <handNote>in very beautiful small hands</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>I<num>8</num>-VI<num>8</num> VII<num>10</num>-XXVIII<num>10</num> (+1) XXIX<num>10</num>
                        (wants 8-10), a<num>2</num> (+1)</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance" rend="withinContents">The presence of the tract of <name type="author">Senatus
                        Bravonius</name> in this Bible has always suggested the probability that it is a <name
                        type="place">Worcester</name> book. I would point out that there is a very great similarity in
                    size, arrangement of writing and contents, between this and a <ref type="ms" target="ETO026">Bible
                        at Eton College</ref> (<ref type="bibl" target="James 1895d">no. 26 in my catalogue</ref>). This
                    latter book is written in triple columns of 62 lines. Its contents are arranged in much the same
                    way, viz.:<lb/> Genesis - 2 Chron.<lb/>
                    <name type="person">Isaiah</name>, <name type="person">Jeremiah</name>, <name type="person"
                        >Baruch</name>, Lamentation (Hebrew alphabet precedes in red, blue and green). <!--James corrects in corrigenda--><lb/>
                    <name type="person">Ezekiel</name> - <name type="person">Malachi</name>.<lb/>
                    <name type="person">Job</name>.<lb/>
                    <name type="person">Ezra</name>, <name type="person">Nehemiah</name>, <name type="person"
                        >Esther</name>, 1 Esdr.<lb/> Proverbs - Ecclesisastes, Oratio <name type="person"
                        >Salomonis</name>.<lb/>
                    <name type="person">Tobit</name>, <name type="person">Judith</name>, 1, 2 Maccabees<lb/> Psalter
                    (triple, with much prefatory matter).<lb/> Table of Epistles and Gospels.<lb/> Eusebian Canons.<lb/>
                    Evv., Acts, Catholic Epistles, Apocalypse<lb/> Pauline Epistles (verses of <name type="person"
                        >Damasus</name>, and preface of <name type="person">Pelagius</name>).<lb/> Laodicean follows
                    Hebrew<lb/> The <ref type="ms" target="ETO026">Eton book</ref> was given to <name type="place">St
                        Albans</name> by <name type="person">Prior Mathias</name>. This is recorded at the top of f. 1r
                    and at the end of Proverbs. There was room for a like record at the top of f. <locus>1r</locus> of
                    the Corpus Bible, which has been removed. There is no direct proof that the <ref type="ms"
                        target="ETO026">Eton Bible</ref> was written at <name type="place">St Albans</name>, but my
                    belief is that it was a sister book to the Corpus Bible and that both belonged to <name type="place"
                        >St Albans</name>. <decoNote>The Corpus book is far more finely decorated</decoNote>.<lb/> A
                    third book closely connected with these two is a <ref type="ms" target="DTC051">2nd volume of a
                        Bible at Trinity College, Dublin (A. 2. 2: <ref type="bibl" target="Abbott 1900">no. 51 in
                            Abbott's Catalogue</ref>)</ref>. This has the prologue of <name type="author"
                    >Senatus</name>; the same prologues to the Pauline Epistles: the writing and ornament also agree
                    (note specially the mottled marble shafts in the framework of the Gospel Canons). It belonged in the
                        <date>xvth century</date> to <name type="place">Westdereham in Norfolk</name>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">In the cover <supplied agent="NJM">(f. <locus>av</locus>)</supplied> are pasted
                    two slips, one of vellum with a carefully written extract from <name type="author">Leland</name> on
                        <name type="author">Senatus Bravonius</name>, the other of paper with notes of some various
                    readings (<origDate>xvi</origDate>).</p>

                <p function="Additions">A slip has been cut from the top of f. <locus>1r</locus> and replaced by blank
                    vellum.</p>

                <p function="Additions" rend="withinContents">On the flyleaves at the end <supplied agent="NJM"
                            >(<locus>ir</locus>-<locus>ivv</locus>)</supplied>. A piece of parchment pasted on <supplied
                        agent="NJM">(<locus>iir</locus>)</supplied>, with a list of the contents of this Bible
                        (<origDate>xv</origDate>).<lb/> Verses and note on the Tribes <supplied agent="NJM"
                            >(<locus>iiir</locus>)</supplied>.<lb/> Classified list of the books <supplied agent="NJM"
                            >(<locus>ivr</locus>)</supplied> (<origDate>xvi early</origDate>).<lb/> Note to the effect
                    that there are 258 leaves in the book from Gen. i <supplied agent="NJM"
                        >(<locus>ivr</locus>)</supplied>.</p>

                <p function="Additions" rend="withinContents"><hi rend="italic">Decoration</hi>. <decoNote>The initials
                        in this book are exceedingly beautiful</decoNote>. I give a list of those which contain subjects
                    or are otherwise remarkable <supplied>(included within contents below)</supplied>.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + 1-276 + i-iv + c-d</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="276v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Bible</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locusNew="1r">
                            <layout>In double columns</layout>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">Prologue <name type="author">Jerome</name> ad <name type="person"
                                >Paulinum</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">
                            <decoNote>Prol. Initial in gold very delicately outlined in black </decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="2v">
                            <layout>In triple columns</layout>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="2v">Capitula of Genesis - Judges, 1 Regum - 2 Paralipomenom, Rest., <name
                                type="person">Tobit</name>, <name type="person">Judith</name>, 1, 2 Maccabees</ab>
                        <ab locus="7r">Pref. b. <name type="author">Ieronimi</name> presb. ad <name type="person"
                                >Desiderium</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="7r">
                            <decoNote>Prol. to Pentateuch, <name type="person">Jerome</name> as black monk nimbed,
                                writing, with knife and pen. In the tail of the letter a tonsured bust. Gold
                                ground.</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="7v">Genesis begins</ab>
                        <ab>Stichometric notes are given in most cases</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="7v">
                            <decoNote>Genesis. Magnificent initial, the height of the page. The general scheme is
                                ladderlike, with small white beasts: gold ground, edged with green. At top, quatrefoil:
                                gold ground. Christ half-length with scroll across, blessing</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="7v">
                            <decoNote>Six medallions, red frames:<lb/> a. Angels. 3 heads seen on L., 3 on R., one
                                half-length full-face in C.<lb/> b. Band of clouds above and blue lined water below.
                                Globe in C. marked HILE (&#965;&#788;&#769;&#955;&#951;).<lb/> c.
                                Red ground, clouds, earth with trees, water.<lb/> d. Sun and moon with faces, red stars
                                in blue sky, earth with trees, water.<lb/> e. Bird in clouds, birds (swans, storks,
                                etc.) on earth: whales in water.<lb/> f. Beasts on L. Christ in C. creates Eve (on
                                R.)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="7v">
                            <decoNote>Quatrefoil, gold ground. Christ half-length with scroll hands to Moses, nimbed,
                                below, the Tables delicately mottled in various hues to represent marble.</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The subsequent initials as far as <name type="person">Job</name> are decorative
                                and are of the most exquisite delicacy and brightness. Perhaps that to <name
                                    type="person">Zechariah</name> may be singled out as particularly marvellous for the
                                fineness of its white pattern on deep blue. The initials are uniformly edged with
                                green</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="47r">Jos. Prol.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="47r">Tandem finito</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="52r">Jud. Arg. (ex epistola beati <name type="person">Ieronimi</name> ad <name
                                type="person">Paulinum</name>). Short extract</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="57r">Similarly for <name type="person">Ruth</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="58r">1 Reg. Prol.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="58r">Viginti duas</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="84r">1 Par. Proll.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="84r">Si septuaginta</incipit>
                        <incipit locusNew="84r">Eusebius Ieron. Domnioni</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="84v">Argumentum ex epistola ad <name type="person">Paulinum</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="97r">2 Par. is followed by the Prophets</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="119r"><name type="person">Baruch</name> follows <name type="person"
                                >Jeremiah</name> and precedes Lamentations</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="121r">Lamentations is headed by a fine table of the Hebrew alphabet. <decoNote>The
                                Hebrew letters are well written in gold, and their names, in red and green capitals, are
                                twice given in the columns on R. with two sets of interpretations. At top are turrets
                                with shields hanging to them. Linen guards to initials survive in the case of some of
                                the minor prophets <supplied agent="NJM">(ff. <locus>138r</locus>, <locus>141v</locus>,
                                        <locus>142r</locus>)</supplied></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="148r">After <name type="person">Malachi</name> follow</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="149r">
                            <name type="person">Job</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="149r">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">Job</hi>. <name type="person">Job</name>'s wife on L. <name
                                    type="person">Job</name> on R. Scrolls inscribed in red: <hi rend="italic">Benedic
                                    deo et morere. Quasi una de stultis mulieribus locuta es</hi>. Red ground</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="154v">Prov., Eccl., Cant, (with the speakers indicated in the margin <supplied
                                agent="NJM">on f. <locus>160v</locus></supplied>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="160v">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">Cant</hi>. A crowned female seated, one hand to her face. A
                                curious cleft is managed in the initial so that the text (Osculetur) is directly
                                connected with her other hand. <name type="person">Esther</name>. Of singularly fine
                                execution</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="161r"><name type="person">Ezra</name>, <name type="person">Nehemiah</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="166v">(Followed by extract. <q>Hic post incensam a chaldeis iudeam</q>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="166v">
                            <name type="person">Hester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="167r">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">Esther</hi>. Of singularly fine execution</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="169v">Sap. (prol. Liber sapientie<lb/>Tres libros salamonis)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="173r">Ecclus. Oratio <name type="person">Salomonis</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="173r">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">Ecclus</hi>. A crowned white-bearded man, half-length, facing R.
                                A cleft in the initial (as above)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="182v">
                            <name type="person">Tobit</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="184r">
                            <name type="person">Judith</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="184r">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">
                                    <name type="person">Judith</name>
                                </hi>. Birds with necks intertwined on a fine red ground</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="187r">1, 2 Maccabees</ab>
                        <ab locus="199r">Epistola <name type="author">Eusebii</name> de canonibus euangeliorum</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="199r">
                            <name type="person">Eusebius Carpiano</name>
                        </incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="199r">Incipit tractatus magistri <name type="author">Senati
                                Wigorniensis</name> bibliothecharii de concordia et dispositione canonum
                            euangeliorum</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="199r">Dilecto amico suo et socio <name type="person">magistro
                                &#198;luredo</name> suus senatus wig(orniensis) ecclesie films salutem et si quid in
                            obsequio potest. Inter preciosa maiorum munera</incipit>
                        <ab>Ending</ab>
                        <explicit locus="200r">et omnia in quibus conuenientia cum aliis repperiri potest</explicit>
                        <ab>The opening of this, with the interesting reference to the Bible presented to <name
                                type="place">Worcester</name> by <name type="person">king Offa</name>, was printed by
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Martene and Durand 1717a">Martene and Durand, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Thes. Nov.</hi> I 484</ref>, from a manuscript then at <name type="place">Conches
                                (in Normandy)</name></ab>
                        <rubric locus="200r">Incipit epistola sancti ieronimi ad damasum</rubric>
                        <ab locus="200v">The Canons under arches</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="200v">
                            <decoNote>The Canons under coloured arches with coloured shafts. A delicately mottled marble
                                shaft (see on <hi rend="italic">Gen</hi>.) is very striking</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="201v">Distinctiones Canonum (beginnings of the sections)</ab>
                        <ab locus="203v">Capitula of the four Gospels</ab>

                        <ab locusNew="204v">
                            <layout>In quadruple columns</layout>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="204v">Prol. Plures fuisse</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="204v">The Arguments (<name type="person">Matheus</name> ex iudea etc.) in parallel
                            columns</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="205v">The Text of the Four Gospels in parallel columns</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="205v">
                            <decoNote>The initials to the Gospels (all on one page) contain the Evangelistic emblems and
                                make a noble appearance</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>The breadth of the column varies with the length of the text, <name type="person"
                                >Mark</name> being naturally the narrowest</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="233v">
                            <layout>In triple columns</layout>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="233v">Capitula to Acts, Cath. Epp., Apoc., Pauline Epp.</ab>
                        <ab>Followed by text of</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="236r">Acts, Cath. Epp., Apocalypse</ab>
                        <ab>Cath. Epp. have prologues</ab>

                        <ab locusNew="242v">
                            <name type="person">Jacobus</name>
                            <name type="person">Petrus</name>
                            <name type="person">Iohannes</name>
                            <name type="person">ludas</name>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="242v">Non ita est ordo</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <hi rend="italic">Jac.</hi>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="243r"><name type="person">Jacobum</name> qui appellatur</incipit>
                        <incipit locusNew="243r"><name type="person">Jacobus</name> apostolus sanctum instruit
                            clerum</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="243r">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">James</hi> and 1 <hi rend="italic">Peter</hi>
                                <supplied agent="NJM">(f. <locus>244r</locus>)</supplied> contain half-length figures of
                                the writers</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>1 <hi rend="italic">Pet</hi>.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="243v"><name type="person">Simon petrus</name> filius <name type="person"
                                >Iohannis</name></incipit>
                        <incipit locusNew="243v">Discipulos saluatoris inuicti</incipit>
                        <ab>2 <hi rend="italic">Pet</hi>.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="244v"><name type="person">Symon petrus</name> per fidem</incipit>
                        <ab>1 <hi rend="italic">Joh</hi>.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="245r"><name type="person">Johannes</name> apostolus et euangelista quem <name
                                type="person">Ihesus</name> amauit</incipit>
                        <incipit locusNew="245r">Racionem uerbi</incipit>
                        <ab>2 <hi rend="italic">Joh</hi>.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="246r">Usque adeo ad sanctam</incipit>
                        <ab>3 <hi rend="italic">Joh</hi>.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="246r">Gaium pietatis</incipit>
                        <ab><hi rend="italic">Jud</hi>.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="246r"><name type="person">Judas</name> frater iacobi</incipit>
                        <incipit locusNew="246r"><name type="person">Judas</name> apostolus fratres</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="246v">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">Apoc</hi>. Half-length figure of Christ with the sword (silver)
                                across His mouth: holding book</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>After <hi rend="italic">Apoc</hi>.</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="249v">Incipit prefatio <name type="author">pelagii</name> de corpore
                            epistolarum <name type="person">beati pauli apostoli</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="249v">Primum queritur quare post euangelia</incipit>
                        <ab>Alia prefatio Ieronimi</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="250r">Omnis textus uel numerus</incipit>
                        <ab>Argumentum in Rom.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="250r">Romani sunt qui</incipit>
                        <incipit locusNew="250v">Romani sunt in partes</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="250v">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">Rom</hi>. Half-length of <name type="person">Paul</name> with
                                scroll</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>The usual arguments to the other Epistles</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="263v">
                            <decoNote><hi rend="italic">Philem</hi>. A large blue nude man with red face and beard hangs
                                from the initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="263v">Heb. is followed by</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="266r">Incipit Epistola ad Laodicenses que non habetur in canone</rubric>
                        <ab>A smaller rubric says</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="266r">hec epistola non est emendata</rubric>
                        <ab>After the text</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="266r">Ex epistola ad Colosenses</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="266r">Cum lecta fuerit etc.</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="266r">Beatus <name type="person">Gregorius</name> in ultimo moralium</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="266r"><name type="person">Paulus</name> apostolus quamuis epistolas quindecim
                            etc.</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="266r">In the 2nd column another text of the Epistle, neatly written in
                                <origDate>cent. xvi</origDate></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="266r">In the 3rd column a copy of the Wycliffite version of the epistle written at
                            the same time</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="267r">
                            <layout>In quadruple columns</layout>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="267r">Interpretationes nominum</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="267r"><name type="person">Abel</name> ciuitas uel filius adam qui
                            interpretatur luctus etc.</incipit>
                        <ab>Ends (<name type="person">Zorobabel</name>)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="276r">Uel magister babylonis uel confusionis</explicit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The work maintains its excellence to the end</decoNote>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 20/08/08</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
