<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC487">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>487</idno>

                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Brock Rand, Material Relating to the Diocese of Ely</head>
                <head type="James">Rand's Collections</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">235</height>
                        <width unit="mm">184</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <extent>a quarto volume of about 500 leaves, of different sizes</extent>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xviii</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">The Collections of the <name type="person">Rev. Brock Rand, M.A.</name> (d.
                        <date>1753</date>), chaplain to <name type="person">Bishop Greene of Ely and Rector of
                        Leverington and Newton</name>, formerly of <name type="place">Corpus Christi College</name>:
                    concerning the <name type="place">Diocese of Ely</name>.</p>
                <p function="Additions">A notice of <name type="person">Mr Rand</name> and his book, from <ref
                        type="bibl" target="Watson 1827">Watson's <hi rend="italic">Hist. of Wisbech</hi></ref>, and a
                    copy of his epitaph at <name type="place">Leverington</name>, are in the volume.</p>
                <p function="Additions">In <name type="person">Lamb</name>'s time this volume was missing: see a letter
                    of <name type="person">Cole</name> and notes upon it in <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Lamb's edition of Masters's <hi rend="italic">History</hi></ref>,
                    p. 388.</p>
                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-ii + 1-469 + iii</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="eng" otherLangs="lat">English and Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="57v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Bishops of Ely to <name type="person">Thomas Greene</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>Bishops of Ely to <name type="person">Thomas Greene</name> (<date>1723</date>)</ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>ff. <locus>58r</locus>-<locus>59v</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="60r" locusEnd="366r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Parishes of <name type="place">Cambridgeshire</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Parishes of <name type="place">Cambridgeshire</name> in alphabetical order</ab>

                        <ab locus="61r">
                            <supplied>blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="86v">
                            <supplied>blank</supplied>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="366r" locusEnd="469r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Parishes in <name type="place">Ely diocese</name> outside <name type="place"
                                    >Cambridgeshire</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Parishes in <name type="place">Ely diocese</name> outside <name type="place"
                                >Cambridgeshire</name> in alphabetical order</ab>
                    </msItem>


                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC27.05.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks: </p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
