<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC542">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>542</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Prayer Book of Frances Parker</head>

                <p> This MS description is not part of the M. R. James catalogue.</p>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>
                    <measureGrp type="CCC">

                        <height unit="mm">68</height>
                        <width unit="mm">49</width>

                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">2.75 x 2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 82</extent>. Single
                    column of 13 lines. <handNote>Writing, in an italic hand, and decoration English</handNote>, c.
                        <origDate>1570-74</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Writing">The scribe, according to a note of <date>December 10th 1973</date> by <name
                        type="person">Berthold Wolpe</name> in the Parker Library copy of <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Vaughan and Fines 1960">Vaughan and Fines' 'Handlist'</ref>, was the Huguenot, <name
                        type="person">John de Beauchesne</name> (c. 1538-after 1610), who was working in <name
                        type="place">London</name> at the time. He was author of <hi rend="italic">A Booke containing
                        divers sortes of handes</hi>, London, 1570.</p>

                <p function="Binding">Contemporary binding embroidered with flowers and leaves.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">Made for <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name>, the second son of <name
                        type="person">Archbishop Matthew Parker</name>, and given by him to his wife, Frauncis (or
                    Frances), as a New Years gift. They had been married on the <date>29 December 1569</date>, and
                        <name type="person">Matthew</name> died prematurely in <date>December 1574</date>, thus enabling
                    a dating of the book <date>1570-74</date>. Purchased at the sale of the Huth manuscripts at
                    Sothebys <date>13 July 1917</date>, lot 5571. Inside the front cover is the bookplate Ex musaeo
                    Huth with a price of Ł24 noted. Given to the College by <name type="person">Almeric Hugh Paget,
                        First Baron Queenborough</name>, in <date>1923</date>.</p>

                <p function="Decoration">Illuminated borders and ornamental initials.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. 1-82. Partially imaged due to the extreme fragility of the binding: front cover
                        exterior and interior + ff. 1r-7v + back cover exterior only</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="eng">English.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="2r" locusEnd="82r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Book of Prayers and Meditations</title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="2r">A Booke wherein is conteined most necessary prayers and confortable
                            meditations to be used with ernest zeale often to be said of a godly and christian
                            person</rubric>

                        <ab><decoNote>This text is written in gold, red and black. There is an illuminated framed
                                border, decorated with flowers and leaves in the manner of Flemish sixteenth-century
                                Books of Hours. This border is somewhat rubbed and damaged</decoNote>, as also are the
                            final illegible words of the text in gold referring to the compilation of the texts</ab>

                        <ab locus="2v">A list of thirteen lines of advice, <decoNote>each beginning with a gold
                                capital</decoNote> which spell out the name of the owner, <name type="person">Francis
                                Parker</name>. <decoNote>The text block is framed with a thin line gold frame which is
                                used for almost all the text pages of the book</decoNote><lb/>
                            <lg>
                                <l>Feare God with true hart</l>
                                <l>Remember the ende</l>
                                <l>Acknowledge thy sinns</l>
                                <l>Never ceace praying</l>
                                <l>Condemne thy self</l>
                                <l>Imitate Christ</l>
                                <l>Serve God devoutly</l>
                                <l>Persist to do well</l>
                                <l>And reverence thy mate</l>
                                <l>Rejoye in his love</l>
                                <l>Kepe still thy good name</l>
                                <l>Embrace thou vertu</l>
                                <l>Remember thes sayings</l>
                            </lg></ab>
                        <rubric locus="3r">To his welbeloved wyf <name type="person">Frauncis Parker</name>
                            <name type="person">Mathew Parker</name> wisheth many happy new yeres with continu all
                            encrease of health</rubric>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>This text is written in gold, red and black, and is followed by a prayer with an
                                ornamental initial in gold set on a red ground. Similar gold initials on red, dark blue
                                or grey blue grounds are used at the beginning of all the prayers and
                                meditations</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="3r">Being desirous that above all thinges you should have greatest respect to
                            God</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="5r">eternall salvation in the worlde to come with God the father and his sonne
                            Iesu christ to whome be all honoure and glorye. AMEN. Your loving husband <name
                                type="person">Mathew</name></explicit>

                        <ab><locus>5v</locus>-<locus>6v</locus> blank</ab>
                        <rubric locus="7r">Meditation for the morning when one ariseth</rubric>
                        <incipit>Muse a while how muche the light and eye of the mind and soule is better then of the
                            body</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="7v">have eyes of the minde, and that such as godly wise</explicit>
                        <rubric>A prayer at the same tyme</rubric>
                        <incipit>O Almighty and most gracious God, we hartely thanke thee for the sweete sleepe and
                            confortable reste which thou have geven us this night past</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="8v">that may be found acceptable before thy divine maiestie through Jesus
                            Christe our Lord. So be it</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="8v">A Meditation when we go to bed and before we slepe</rubric>
                        <incipit>Thinke that as we do willingly put of(f) our garments</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="9r">shall receave them againe in the resurrection of the just</explicit>
                        <rubric>A prayer at the same tyme</rubric>
                        <incipit>The day nowe ended men give them selves to rest in the night</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="10r">I will lay me downe in pece and take my rest. Psal. 4</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="10v">A Confession of sinnes</rubric>
                        <incipit>O Eternall God and most mercifull father, we confesse and acknowledge here before thy
                            divine maiestie that we are miserable sinners</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="12v">be all honor and glory world without ende. So be it</explicit>
                        <rubric>A Meditation of the blessed state and felicitie of the lyfe to come</rubric>
                        <ab>This meditation is in three sections</ab>
                        <incipit>This body is but a prison wher in the soule is kept</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="17v">Oh God the creatour, Oh Lorde Iesu the redemer, O holy Spirite the
                            conforter</explicit>
                        <incipit>In recordation of this, oh how thy children rejoice: how conttemne they the pleasure of
                            this worlde</incipit>


                        <explicit locus="19v">Come ye blessed of my father posesse the kingdome prepared for you from
                            the beginning</explicit>
                        <incipit>Then shall they be lyke to thy Angels. Then shall they be lyke to the Sunne in thy
                            kingdom</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="20r">but see that immortable and incorruptible inheritance which they shall
                            enjoy for evermore. Amen</explicit>
                        <rubric>A prayer for the desire of the lyfe to come</rubric>
                        <incipit>This my bodye is the very darke and filthye prisone</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="21r">and most fervently desire the sweteness of thy familiaritye in the which
                            all goodnesse is conteined. To the(e) be glory for ever</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="21v">A prayer for present helpe in tentation</rubric>
                        <ab>This is in three sections</ab>
                        <incipit>Deare Father, to whom it is more easi to do all things then for me to thinke any one
                            good thing</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="22r">and thy holy spirite against my sinfull flesh and old man</explicit>
                        <incipit>Thou art faithfull O father who hast promised that I shall not be tempted further than
                            thou wilte make me able to beare</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="23v">and praise thy holy name for the victory through Iesus Christe our Lord.
                            Amen</explicit>
                        <incipit>My sonne if thou wilt come into the service of the Lord</incipit>
                        <explicit>and feare and prepare the soule to tentation. Eccles. 2</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="24r">A prayer for the peace of the Church</rubric>
                        <ab>This prayer greatly exceeds in length any other text in the book</ab>
                        <incipit>Lorde Iesus Christe which of thy almightinesse madest all creatures visible and
                            invisible</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="37r">which, after the most perfect example of concorde, be distincted in
                            property of persons and one in nature, to whom be prayse and glory eternally.
                            Amen</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="37v">A Psalme to be saide in the tyme of any common plague, sikness, or other
                            crosse and visitation of God</rubric>

                        <incipit>O come let us humble our selves and fall downe before the Lord with reverence and
                            feare</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="42r">and will always be shewing forth thy prayse from generation to generation.
                            Glory be to the Father ...... world without end. Amen</explicit>
                        <rubric>A Meditation of death and the commodities it bringeth</rubric>
                        <incipit>What other thing do we daily in this present life but heape sinne upon sinne</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="45r">into a much more large and faire place, even into heaven</explicit>
                        <rubric>A prayer at the houre of death</rubric>
                        <incipit>O Lord Iesus Christ which art the only health of all men living, and the everlasting
                            life of them</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="48r">Lord into thy hands I commend my soule, Lord receive my spirite</explicit>
                        <rubric>The Litany</rubric>
                        <incipit>O God the father of heaven have mercy upon us</incipit>
                        <ab locus="58v">The Litany ends</ab>
                        <ab locus="59r">Prayers following the Litany, ending <locus>67r</locus></ab>
                        <rubric locus="59r">A Prayer for the Queenes maiestie</rubric>
                        <incipit>O Lord our heavenly father, high and mighty King of Kings</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="60r">A Prayer for pastoures and ministers of the church</rubric>
                        <incipit>Almighty and everlasting God, which onely workest great marvailes, send down upon our
                            pastoures</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="60v">For rayne</rubric>
                        <incipit>O God heavenly father, which by the same Jesus Christ hath promised to all them that
                            seek thy kingdom</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="61r">For fair weather</rubric>
                        <incipit>O Lord God which for the sinne of men</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="62r">In the tyme of dearth and famine</rubric>

                        <rubric locus="62v">In the tyme of Warre</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="63v">A prayer for obtaining the Holy Ghost</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="64v">For the true knowledge of God and his worde and a life agreable to the
                            same</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="65r">A Prayer for the gift of faith</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="66r">For a godly life</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="66v">A Prayer for true perseverance and assured hope of eternall lyfe</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="67r">A Prayer of Chrisostome</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="68r">The maner of our redemption purchased by Jesus Christ</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="73r">A forme of thankes giving for our redemption</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="75r">A fruitful prayer to be said at all times</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="78r">Prayer for a maried woman</rubric>
                        <ab locus="80r">At the end of this prayer are the initials M.P., presumably for <name
                                type="person">Matthew Parker</name></ab>
                        <rubric locus="81r">A Table of this present Booke</rubric>
                        <ab>
                            <lg>
                                <l>A meditation for the morning when you arayse 1</l>
                                <l>A prayer for the same tyme 1</l>
                                <l>A meditation when we go to bed and before we slepe 2</l>
                                <l>A prayer at the same tyme 3</l>
                                <l>A confession of synnes 4</l>
                                <l>A meditation of the blessed state and felicite of the lyfe to come 6</l>
                                <l>A prayer for the desire of the lyfe to come 14</l>
                                <l>A prayer for present helpe in tentation 15</l>
                                <l>A prayer for the peace of the churche 18</l>
                                <l>A Psalme to be said in the tyme of any comon plague 31</l>
                                <l>A meditation on death and the comedities it bringeth 36</l>
                                <l>A prayer at the houre of death 39</l>
                                <l>The Litany 42</l>
                                <l>The maner of our redemption 62</l>
                                <l>A forme of thanksgiving for our redemption 67</l>
                                <l>A fruitful prayer to be sayd at all tyme 69</l>
                                <l>A prayer for a maried woman 71</l>
                            </lg>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><locus>82v</locus> blank</ab>



                    </msItem>


                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: NJM</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: SP</p>
                            <p>msCheck: SP</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
