<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC559">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>559</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Notes on French Legal Cases c. 1480</head>
                <p>
                    <supplied>This MS description is not part of the M. R. James catalogue; it is based in part on the
                        description given in <ref type="bibl" target="Vaughan and Fines 1960">Vaughan and Fines,
                            'Handlist', p. 117</ref>.</supplied>
                </p>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">257</height>
                        <width unit="mm">180</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">10 x 7</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 32</extent>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xv</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">It seems to have been collected and partly copied by <name type="person">Pierre
                        Assailly</name>, <hi rend="italic">examinateur</hi> at the Ch&#226;telet (but not in <ref
                        type="bibl" target="Dupont-Ferrier 1954">G. Dupont-Ferrier, <hi rend="italic">Gallia Regia</hi>,
                        IV (1954), pp. 336-40</ref>, list of <hi rend="italic">examinateurs</hi> at the
                    Ch&#226;telet), and he takes an active part in this capacity in at least one of the cases.
                    <lb/>Probably written in <name type="place">Paris</name> in <date>1480</date>. Removed in
                        <date>1952</date> from the boards of SP.16 <hi rend="italic">Epistole et varii tractatus Pii
                        Secundi Pontificis Maximi</hi>(Lyons, 1497), a small octavo book donated to the College by <name
                        type="person">Matthew Parker</name>.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i + 1-32 + ii</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="frm">Latin and Middle French.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="32v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Notes on French Legal Cases c. <date>1480</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Fragmentary material concerning legal cases: Maistres <name type="person">Pierre
                                Assailly</name> and <name type="person">Jehan Barbarin</name> v. <name type="person"
                                >Jehan l'Auxerroys</name>; <name type="person">Charles, seigneur de Gaucourt</name>,
                            etc., v. <name type="person">Jehan Dandines</name>, <date>1480</date>; <name type="place"
                                >Abbey of Notre-Dame</name>, <name type="place">Ivry-la-Bataille</name> (dioc. <name
                                type="place">Evreux</name>) v. <name type="person">Maistre Jehan Benoist</name>
                            (transcripts of documents, some 13th cent.), <date>1480</date>, etc. Much of it consists of
                            depositions of witnesses.</ab>
                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: typed from Vaughan and Fines 'Handlist' BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck:</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
