<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC582">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>582</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Statutes of Corpus Christi College, Cambridge (1548-9)</head>
                <p>
                    <supplied>This MS description is not part of the M. R. James catalogue; it is based in part on the
                        description given in <ref type="bibl" target="Vaughan and Fines 1960">Vaughan and Fines,
                            'Handlist', p. 120</ref>.</supplied>
                </p>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">265</height>
                        <width unit="mm">180</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">10.5 x 7.25</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 22</extent>.
                        <origDate>1574</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">Formerly known as the Black Book. The book was compiled by <name type="person"
                        >Parker</name>, probably in <origDate>1574</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Additions"><decoNote>Three painted leaves, <supplied>the first (a portrait of <name
                                type="person">Queen Elizabeth</name>) and last (a portrait of <name type="person"
                                >Matthew Parker</name>) now glued to the front (<locus>fib</locus>) and back
                                (<locus>bib</locus>) inner boards respectively</supplied></decoNote>.</p>

                <p function="Binding">Contemporary Lambeth binding, gilt-tooled (reproduced in <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Hobson 1929">G. D. Hobson, <hi rend="italic">Bindings in Cambridge Libraries</hi>
                        (1929), pl. xxxv</ref>).</p>
                <p function="Additions">Seal of the Court of High Commission, broken, formerly attached to the single
                    blue and silver sewing cord.</p>

                <p function="Research">Statutes printed by <ref type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">J. Lamb, <hi
                            rend="italic">Masters' History of Corpus Christi College</hi> (1831), pp. 279-93</ref>;
                    Edward's charter and Elizabeth's commission in <ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">J. Lamb, <hi
                            rend="italic">A collection of letters, statutes and other documents ... illustrative of the
                            history of the University of Cambridge during the period of the Reformation</hi> (1838), pp.
                        122-3 and 275-8</ref>; list of books and furniture for Norwich scholars, <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Stokes 1898">H. P. Stokes, <hi rend="italic">Corpus Christi</hi> (1898), pp. 68-9,
                        note</ref>.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i + 1-21</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="2v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Commission of <name type="person">Queen Elizabeth I</name> for the visitation of the
                                    <name type="place">University</name>, <date>20 June 1559</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="3r" locusEnd="3v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Grant of new arms to <name type="place">Corpus Christi College</name> by <name
                                    type="person">Robert Cook, Clarenceux King of Arms</name>, <date>23 December
                                    1570</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="4r" locusEnd="12r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Statutes of <name type="place">Corpus Christi College</name>
                                (<date>1548-9</date>)</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locusNew="4r">
                            <supplied>
                                <decoNote>Arms of the college</decoNote>
                            </supplied>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="12r">Confirmed and signed by the ecclesiastical commissioners, <date>30 and 31
                                January 1573/4</date></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="12v" locusEnd="12v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title><name type="person">Richard Billingford</name>'s statute concerning the Master of
                                    <name type="place">Corpus Christi College</name>, <date>1416</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="13r" locusEnd="13v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Charter of <name type="person">Edward VI</name> introducing new statutes for <name
                                    type="place">Cambridge University</name>, <date>8 April 1549/1550</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="14r" locusEnd="21r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Testimony of the gifts of Matthew Parker</title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locusNew="14r">The testimony of the guiftes of <name type="person">Matthue Archb. of
                                Cant.</name></rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="14r"><supplied>The testimony was</supplied> drawn up by the Masters and Fellows of
                                <name type="place">Corpus Christi College</name>, <name type="place">Gonville and Caius
                                College</name> and <name type="place">Trinity Hall</name>, recording <name type="person"
                                >Parker</name>'s gifts and good deeds to themselves and others, and listing the books he
                            gave to the <name type="place">University Library</name>, the books and furniture he gave to
                            Corpus Christi College for the use of the Norwich scholars, etc.</ab>
                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: typed from Vaughan and Fines 'Handlist' BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck:</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
