<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC006">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>6</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Under B. 2</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>347</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">John of Tynemouth, Historia aurea, Part II</head>
                <head type="James">Joh. Tynemouth. Historia Aurea II</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">515</height>
                        <width unit="mm">360</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">19.8 x 13.8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 299 + 4</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 65-66 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv</origDate>, <handNote>in the
                        same hand or hands as <ref type="ms" target="CCC005">MS 5</ref></handNote>, of which it is the
                    continuation. At each end, two leaves of the Antiphoner as in <ref type="ms" target="CCC005">MS
                        5</ref>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1<num>8</num>-5<num>8</num> 6<num>6</num> (wants 6) | 7<num>8</num>-10<num>8</num> (wants
                        3-8) 11<num>8</num>-16<num>8</num> 17<num>6</num> 18<num>8</num> 19<num>8</num> 20<num>6</num>
                            21<num>8</num>-26<num>8</num> (wants 6-8) 27<num>8</num> (wants 1, 2) 28<num>8</num>
                            29<num>8</num> 30<num>6</num> 31<num>8</num>-39<num>8</num> [40<num>1</num>]
                        41<num>6</num></collation>.</p>
                <p function="Provenance">At top of f. <locus>1r</locus>
                    <decoNote>in red</decoNote>
                    <q>Hic est liber <name type="place">S. Albani</name> de libraria conuentus</q>. A long inscription
                    in large letters, no doubt referring to <name type="person">Wyntreshull</name> and very probably a
                    duplicate of that in <ref type="ms" target="CCC005">MS 5</ref>, has been erased from the R. margin
                    of f. <locus>1r</locus>.</p>

                <p function="Additions"><decoNote>Fine initials and partial borders to the several books</decoNote>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-c + i-ii + 1-299 + iii-iv + d-f</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="299r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author" key="JohnofTy-001">John of Tynemouth</name>, <title>Historia aurea, Part
                                II</title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="1r">Incipit Liber 12 Cronicarum <name type="author">Johannis</name>. De <name
                                type="person">Sancto Mauricio</name> cum sociis suis c. i</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="1r"><name type="person">Dioclicianus</name> incepit regnare</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="45r">c. 124</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="45r">De <name type="person">Sancto petro alexandrino</name></rubric>
                        <ab locus="47r" locusNew="46r">Liber XIII. c. i</ab>
                        <rubric locus="47r" locusNew="46r">De <name type="person">S. katerina virgine</name></rubric>
                        <ab>c. 58</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="70r">De <name type="person">S. florencio</name></rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="70v">At the end <handNote>in a <origDate>xvith cent.</origDate>
                            hand</handNote></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="70v">
                            <q>Hic Inc. 2<abbr rend="superscript">us</abbr> Tomus ut ibi scribitur <name type="author"
                                    >Johannis Anglici</name></q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="71v" locusNew="70v">Liber XIV. c. i</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="70v">De gestis illius temporis</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="70v">Romanorum igitur tricesimus quintus regnauit <name type="person"
                                >constantinus</name></incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="113v">c. (124). Death of <name type="person">Theodosius</name></ab>
                        <ab>Rubrics and numbers of chapters gradually cease to be added</ab>
                        <ab>Much of this book is from <hi rend="italic">Vitae Patrum</hi></ab>
                        <ab locus="72v" locusNew="71v">Most of cc. 4-22 are wanting after f. <locus locusNew="71v"
                                >72v</locus></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="113v">Liber XV. c. i. <name type="person">Arcadius</name> and <name type="person"
                                >Honorius</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="152r" locusNew="145r"><hi rend="italic">Prophecy of Merlin</hi> in verse</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="145r">Cumque peragratis sub multis regibus annis</incipit>
                        <ab locus="199v" locusNew="192v">Five leaves are gone after f. <locus locusNew="192v"
                                >199v</locus></ab>
                        <ab locus="267r" locusNew="256r">
                            <decoNote>There is a clever unfinished pencil sketch of a Mongol or Tartar on the
                                margin</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>No beginning of a fresh book is marked after f. <locus locusNew="113v">120v</locus>. The
                            narrative is continued to f. <locus locusNew="292v">303v</locus>, the year being
                                <date>1343</date></ab>
                        <ab>It breaks off in the <q>literae <name type="person">Edwardi</name> delegatis pape et
                                vicecomitibus suis</q> (<ref type="bibl" target="Hearne 1731d">Hearne, Hemingford II
                                371</ref>) with the words</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="292v">Nos ad instantiam (catchword) requisicionem</explicit>
                        <ab locus="304r" locusNew="293r">a leaf added by <name type="person">Parker</name>'s scribes,
                            and on it they have written the end of the chapter and continue</ab>
                        <rubric locus="304r" locusNew="293r">Scripsit quoque rex vicecomitibus pro eodem sub hac
                            forma</rubric>
                        <ab>The text of this is given. Then follow heads of chapters, no text being given</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">Qualiter papa scripsit regi <name type="person">Edwardo</name> quod nuntios
                            ut condictum fuerat non misit ad Curiam</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">Qualiter rex Angliae asserit treugas per <name type="person">Philippum de
                                Valesio</name> a parte violatas, et ipsum monet de observatione illarum</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">Litera <name type="person">Philippi regis francie</name> missa reg. Scotorum
                            ante transitum regis Angliae in Normanniam</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">Litera regis fran. missa reg. Scotie statim post aduentum regis Angliae in
                            Normanniam</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">Litera missa <name type="person">Edwardo reg. Ang.</name> ante bellum de
                                <name type="place">Cressi</name> per <name type="person">Philippum</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">Responsio <name type="person">Edwardi</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">De victoria <name type="person">regis Edwardi</name> habita apud <name
                                type="place">Cressy</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">De bello fact. apud <name type="place">Dunelm</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">De victoria contra Gallicos <name type="person">Thome de Dagworth</name>
                            diuinitus collata</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">Qualiter papa post victoriam regi Ang. scripsit</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">De captione <name type="person">Caroli de Blois</name> et qualiter deuictus
                            est</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="293r">Hec omnia clare scribuntur in libro <name type="person">M<abbr
                                    rend="superscript">ri</abbr> Price</name> ( = <ref type="ms" target="OBL469">Bodl.
                                240</ref>) et sequuntur multa de <name type="author">Johannis Anglici</name> de vitis
                            sanctorum ut habetur in martirologio suo et in sanctilogio suo et aliis libris</ab>
                        <ab locus="304v" locusNew="293v">blank</ab>
                        <ab>Then follows a quire <handNote>in one of the hands of the earlier part of the MS.</handNote>
                            containing a chronicle from <date>1343</date> to <date>1377</date> which is said (by <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Horstmann 1901a">Horstmann</ref>) to be the source both of the <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Thompson 1874"><hi rend="italic">Chron. Angliae</hi> ed. E. M.
                                Thompson</ref> and of <name type="person">Tho. Walsingham</name> from <date>1343</date>.
                            It begins</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="294r"><date>18(th year of Ed. III)</date>. Sub eodem tempore missi sunt ex
                            parte Regis Angl. procuratores ad curiam romanam. Dominus <name type="person">Henricus de
                                lancastria</name> etc.</incipit>
                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="310r" locusNew="299r">que famam eius indicibiliter minuerunt</explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="299r">In the lower margin in pencil is</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="299r">In spacio sequenti scribatur de prole et naturali progenie dicti regis /
                            Item cathololgus virorum forcium etc. prelatorum et deuotorum virorum vid<abbr
                                rend="superscript">lt</abbr> domino principe etc. De rege scottorum (??) de cant.
                            archiep. et / de armachano etc. De <name type="person">Ric. heremita</name>
                            <abbr rend="superscript">priore</abbr> ... de <name type="place">beligtan (?
                                berlington)</name> etc./ Item de ffundaco mon. cisterciens. apud <name type="place"
                                >turrim (??) london.</name> et minorissarum<lb/>ffratrum predicatorum apud <name
                                type="place">langeley</name>. sororum eiusdem ordinis apud <name type="place">darteford
                                sutheg' (?)</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="299r">In the remaining line the 4th word seems to be <name type="place"
                                >Westminstre</name></ab>


                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 06/02/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
