<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC078">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>78</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>C. 2</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>24</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Domenico di Bandino, Fons memorabilium uniuersi (book 5, De uiris claris)</head>
                <head type="James">Dominicus de Bandino Aretinus de Viris Claris</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper and Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">408</height>
                        <width unit="mm">287</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">16 x 11.5</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 236 + 2</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 57 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv</origDate>, <handNote>in a clear
                        ugly rather sloping hand</handNote>. <decoNote>Initials in plain red and blue</decoNote>.</p>

                <p>
                    <label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1 vellum flyleaf, 1<num>12</num> (wants 1, 2) 2<num>12</num>-19<num>12</num>
                            20<num>10</num>, 1 vellum flyleaf</collation>
                </p>



                <p function="Additions">On the first flyleaf <supplied>(f. <locus>iv</locus>)</supplied>
                        (<origDate>xv</origDate>):<lb/>
                    <q>de partibus humani corporis<lb/> de etatibus hominum.</q></p>

                <p function="Additions">On the last <supplied>(f. <locus>iir</locus>)</supplied>:<lb/>
                    <q>Sensus miratur que racio dicere nescit <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">J. &#8478;. 1462.</hi> Quomodo Virgo parit et homo factus deus extat<lb/>
                        Desere quod sentis verum mirabile credas <lb/> Namque fides prestat fidei tua racio cedit <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Vel.</hi> Desere persuasum credens mirabile verum<lb/> Namque fides prestat
                        fidei quoque racio cedit.</q>
                    <lb/>
                    <q>Witt hath wunder that reson ne tell can <lb/> hogh maiden is moder and god is i made man<lb/>
                        Leve thi reson and beleve the wunder <lb/> for bileve is above and reson is vnder.</q></p>

                <p function="Additions"><decoNote>In red</decoNote> at bottom of <locus>236v</locus>:<lb/>
                    <q>con(?)taui istos xx fafuos sabbato Jnuoca me 4<abbr rend="superscript">or</abbr>
                    temporum.</q></p>

                <p function="Additions">The headline throughout is <hi rend="italic">De viris claris</hi>.</p>

                <p function="Research">The work is a portion of the Fons Memorabilium Universi of <name type="author"
                        key="Domenico-001">Domenico di Bandino d' Arezzo</name> (d. circa <date>1413</date>): a huge
                    compilation in five parts, of which this is the fifth: never printed. See <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Tiraboschi 1787-94">Tiraboschi VI 713 <supplied>(763)</supplied></ref>.</p>
                <p function="Additions"><supplied>(ff. <locus>aar</locus>-<locus>aav</locus>)</supplied> In the book is
                    a rough draft of a letter to a <name type="person">Dominus Johannes</name>, dated <q>ex <name
                            type="place">granata</name> ciuitate florentissima ydibus sextilibus</q> by <q>tuus <name
                            type="person">Ihouanes pagol</name>.</q> The writer of it has heard that he has been
                    reported dead, and begs that the rumour may be contradicted.</p>
                <p function="Additions">The last article is on <name type="person" key="Wulfstan-001">Lupus
                        episcopus</name>.</p>
                <p function="Research">An article which suffices to identify the work is that on <name type="person"
                        >Bandinus of Arezzo</name>, the author's father. A long account of the work is given by <ref
                        type="bibl" target="Mehus 1759">L. Mehus, <hi rend="italic">Ambrosii Camaldulensis Epp</hi>.
                        etc., I cxxx sqq.</ref> Other characteristic articles are on:<lb/>
                    <q><name type="person">Acursius</name>, <name type="person">Azo marchio Estensis</name>, <name
                            type="person">Barlaham Calaber</name>, <name type="person">Blanchi</name>, <name
                            type="person">Boccacius Joh.</name>, <name type="person">Bonifacius Octauus</name>, <name
                            type="person">Bonifacius (Fazio degli Uberti)</name>, <name type="person">Brunettus
                            Latinus</name>, <name type="person">Caham</name>, <name type="person">Castrucius</name>,
                            <name type="person">Cimabue</name>, <name type="person">Collucius Pyerius</name>, <name
                            type="person">Dantes</name> (who, with <name type="person">Boccaccio</name> and <name
                            type="person">Petrarch</name>, is frequently quoted), <name type="person">Dinus de
                            Garbo</name>, <name type="person" key="Domenico-001">Dominicus</name> (the author: qui
                        longis lugubratiunculis plurium annorum curriculo laborauit limpidum facere fontem haustu
                        reficientem sapido sicientes), <name type="person">Farinata</name>, <name type="person">Franc.
                            Petrarcha</name>, <name type="person">Gebellinus</name>, <name type="person">Giottus</name>,
                            <name type="person">Gonella petri</name>, <name type="person">Guido Cavalcanti</name>, <name
                            type="person">Guido Guerra</name>, <name type="person">Guido de Monte feltro</name>, <name
                            type="person">Ioh. Boccatius</name>.</q><lb/> The authorities quoted include <name
                        type="person">Moyses Anglicus</name> (metrical <hi rend="italic">Hist. Troiana</hi>), <name
                        type="person">Lactantius</name> on the Thebais of <name type="person">Statius</name>, <name
                        type="person">Marco Polo</name>, <name type="person">Plutarch</name>, <name type="person"
                        >Tacitus</name>, <name type="person">Caesar</name>, <name type="person">Livy</name>, <name
                        type="person">Eutropius</name>, <name type="person">Florus</name>, <name type="person">Val.
                        Max.</name>, <name type="person">Frontinus</name>, <name type="person">Statius</name>, <name
                        type="person">Virgil</name>, <name type="person">Ovid</name>, (<name type="person"
                    >Burley</name>) de vita et moribus philosophorum, <name type="person">Gellius</name>, <name
                        type="person">John of Salisbury</name>, (<name type="person">Alani</name>) <name type="person"
                        >Anticlaudianus</name>, etc.<lb/>
                    <name type="person">Tacitus</name> is mentioned on f. <locus>106v</locus> as frequently citing <name
                        type="person">Cluvius</name>.<lb/> The text is very incorrectly written.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i + 1-236 + ii + c-d</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="enm">Latin with Middle English note on flyleaf.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="236v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Domenico di Bandino</name>, <title>Fons memorabilium uniuersi (book 5,
                                De uiris claris)</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>Begins imperfectly in an account of man in general.<lb/> (De partibus humani corporis)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Differt a muliere. Quia sexus non uariat speciem</incipit>
                        <ab>The next sections are on Vir, Natura, Corpus, and on all parts of the body ending with
                            Plante</ab>
                        <ab locus="4r">
                            <hi rend="italic">De etatibus hominis</hi>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="4r">Decursis hominum partibus contra etates ponende sunt</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="5r">Nunc ia(m) incepturus scribere particulares uiros inopiam (incipiam) ab
                            inicio dolorum ac misseriarum gencium Primo (?) ab inicio peccati prothoparentum, seruato
                            tamen ordine alphabeti, dicam igitur deo duce</explicit>
                        <incipit locusNew="5r">Abacuc propheta ut scribit Jeronimus in prefatione Abacuc</incipit>
                        <ab>The writer makes constant reference to other compilations of his own: de montibus, de
                            ciuitatibus, de sectis hereticorum, de sectis philosophorum, de arboribus, de lapidibus et
                            gemmis etc. etc.</ab>

                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck:</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
