<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC092">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>92</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>C. 7</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>28</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">John of Worcester OSB ('Florence of Worcester'), Chronica chronicarum</head>
                <head type="James">Florentius Wigorniensis</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">375</height>
                        <width unit="mm">270</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">15 x 10.2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 204 + 3</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 44 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xii late, xiii and xiv
                        early</origDate>, <handNote>finely written</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>2 flyleaves, 1<num>8</num> (1 canc.) 2<num>8</num> (7, 8 canc.) 3<num>10</num>
                            4<num>8</num>-16<num>8</num> 17<num>10</num> (8 canc.) 18<num>8</num>-22<num>8</num> (7, 8
                        canc.) | 23<num>12</num> 24<num>12</num> 25 (six), one flyleaf</collation>.</p>
                <p function="Provenance">At top of f. <locus>1r</locus>:<lb/>
                    <q>Liber Abbatis et conuentus de <name type="place">Burgo sancti Petri (i.e.
                        Peterborough)</name></q>.<lb/> Just below this <name type="person">Parker</name> has written
                        <decoNote>in red</decoNote>: <q>hic liber olim cenobii <name type="place">S. Edmundi</name></q>,
                    the result of confusion between <name type="person">Burgo</name> and <name type="person"
                    >Bury</name>.</p>
                <p function="Additions">Flyleaves from a large Missal of cent. <origDate>xiv</origDate> in double
                    columns containing part of the office for Palm Sunday.</p>
                <p function="Research">This copy was used for the text from <date>450</date> to <date>1066</date> in
                        <ref type="bibl" target="Petrie 1848">
                        <hi rend="italic">Monumenta Historica Britannica</hi> 522 sqq.</ref>: cf. <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Hardy 1865">Hardy II 129, 246</ref>.</p>





                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-ii + 1-204 + iii + c-d</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="203r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">John of Worcester OSB ('Florence of Worcester')</name>, <title>Chronica
                                chronicarum</title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locus="1r"><name type="person">Adam</name> centum xxx annorum genuit <name
                                type="person">Seth</name>. Et postea uixit</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">Genealogy of the descendants of <name type="person">Noah</name>'s sons: and,
                            in central column, of <name type="person">Schef</name> (i. garba) to <name type="person"
                                >Woden</name>: with two <origDate>xiiith cent.</origDate> notes on <name type="person"
                                >Schef</name> and <name type="person">Woden</name></ab>
                        <incipit locus="1v">Angli saxones imperatoris martiani tempore a brittonibus inuitati</incipit>
                        <ab>Ed. <ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1848">Thorpe I p. 258</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Petrie 1848">MHB 635</ref></ab>
                        <ab locus="1v">Genealogies occupy the central column</ab>
                        <ab locus="5r">List of kings, continued <handNote>in later hand</handNote> (after <name
                                type="person">Henry III</name>) to <name type="person">Edward III</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="5v">blank</ab>
                        <incipit locus="6r">Anno dominice incarnatione secundum dionisium d. xix. <name type="person"
                                >Cerdic</name> et <name type="person">Kinric</name> filius eius secundum anglicam
                            cronicam</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1848">Thorpe I 271</ref>)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="7r">coronam regni sicut ei iuratum fuerat adeptus est</explicit>
                        <ab locus="7v">blank</ab>
                        <rubric locus="8r">Nomina lxx duorum discipulorum Christi (see below)</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="8r">Nomina Hebreorum pontificum</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="8r">(<name type="person">Aaron</name> to '<name type="person"
                            >Pisanus</name>')</ab>
                        <ab locus="8r">Continuing with Bishops of Jerusalem (<name type="person">Jacobus frater
                                domini</name> to <name type="person">Cirillus</name>)</ab>

                        <ab>The list of the Seventy on f. <locus>8r</locus> is essentially the same as that in <ref
                                type="ms" target="CCC183">MS 183</ref> and <ref type="ms" target="LBLVB6">Vesp. B.
                                VI</ref>. It has I believe never been printed. <supplied>(James presents the list in two
                                columns; see the Original James Record (PDF) for this manuscript)</supplied></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">List of the Seventy Disciples: see <ref type="bibl"
                                    target="James 1910b">a paper by the present writer in <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                                        Theol. Studies</hi> 1910, f. 459</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="8r">Nomina lxx duorum discipulorum Christi:<lb/>
                            <name type="person">Iacob iustus</name>, <name type="person">Mathias</name>, <name
                                type="person">Ioseph</name>, <name type="person">Ioseph alius</name>, <name
                                type="person">Marchus euuangelista</name>, <name type="person">Barnabas</name>, <name
                                type="person">Lucas euuangelista</name>, <name type="person">Cleophas</name>, <name
                                type="person">Seneca</name>, <name type="person">Symeon</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Lucius</name>, <name type="person">Manain</name>, <name type="person">Sostenes</name>,
                                <name type="person">Cephas</name>, <name type="person">Taddeus</name>, <name
                                type="person">Ermen qui et pastor</name>, <name type="person">Andronicus</name>, <name
                                type="person">Iohannes</name>, <name type="person">Amplias</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Urbanus</name>, <name type="person">Erodion</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Asyncritis</name>, <name type="person">Nason</name>, <name type="person">Stephanus
                                prothomartyr</name>, <name type="person">Philippus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Prochorus</name>, <name type="person">Nicanor</name>, <name type="person">Symon</name>,
                                <name type="person">Parmena</name>, <name type="person">Aquila</name>, <name
                                type="person">Iudas</name>, <name type="person">Hilas</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Siluanus</name>, <name type="person">Symon cleophe</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Iason</name>, <name type="person">Agabus</name>, <name type="person">Ananias</name>,
                                <name type="person">Ignatius</name>, <name type="person">Symon cirenensis</name>, <name
                                type="person">Alexander</name>, <name type="person">Rufus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Nathanael</name>, <name type="person">Nichodemus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Cleophas</name>, <name type="person">Symon</name>, <name type="person">Iudas</name>,
                                <name type="person">Iacobus</name>, <name type="person">Symon</name>, <name
                                type="person">Symon coriarius</name>, <name type="person">Lucas</name>, <name
                                type="person">Barnabas</name>, <name type="person">Iohannes</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Barnabas</name>, <name type="person">Stephanus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Chorisius</name>, <name type="person">Hilichus</name>, <name type="person"
                            >Gaius</name>, <name type="person">Flegonta</name>, <name type="person">Ermen</name>, <name
                                type="person">Apellen probabilis</name>, <name type="person">Dionisius
                            ariopagita</name>, <name type="person">Aepenctus</name>, <name type="person">Iesus qui
                                dicitur iustus</name>, <name type="person">Stachin</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Ponplius</name>, <name type="person">Aristobolus</name>, <name type="person">Stephanus
                                corinthiensis</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="8r"><name type="person">Erodius</name>, <name type="person">Rufus</name>, <name
                                type="person">Olimpus</name>, <name type="person">Titus</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Phelemon</name>: hii sunt qui electi fuerunt ab apostolis in ordinem pro his qui
                            recesserant </ab>

                        <ab locus="9r">Nomina Romanorum pontificum</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="9r">To <name type="person">Alexander III</name>, continued <handNote>by two
                                hands</handNote> to <name type="person">Alexander IV</name></ab>
                        <ab>These lists are not printed by <ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1848">Thorpe</ref></ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="9v">Cantia: Nomina Archiepiscoporum dororenensis (!) ecclesie </rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="9v">(<ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1848">Thorpe I 231</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Petrie 1848">Monumenta Historica Britannica 616</ref>) to <name type="person"
                                >Ricardus</name>: continued to <name type="person">Bonifacius</name></ab>
                        <ab>Lists of English bishops (see below)</ab>
                        <ab>On the lists of Bishops (see <ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1848">Thorpe I 231 sqq.</ref>)
                            it may be remarked that their extent is as follows in this copy (the extinct sees not
                            noted). <supplied>(James presents this material in three columns, separated here by colons.
                                For the columnar format see the Original James Record (PDF) for this
                                manuscript)</supplied></ab>
                        <ab><name type="place">Canterbury</name>: original to <name type="person">Ricardus</name>
                                (<date>1174</date>): continued to <name type="person">Bonifacius</name>
                                (<date>1245</date>)<lb/>
                            <name type="place">Rochester</name>: original to <name type="person">Arnulfus</name>
                            <date>1076</date>: continued to <name type="person">Gilebertus</name>
                            <date>1185</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">London</name>: original to <name type="person">Gilebertus (I)</name>
                            <date>1128</date>: continued to <name type="person">Willelmus (II)</name>
                            <date>1199</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">East Angles</name>: original to <name type="person">Eouerardus</name>
                            <date>1121</date>: continued to <name type="person">Johannes (II)</name>
                            <date>1200</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Chichester</name>: <name type="person">Stigand</name> to <name
                                type="person">Saffredus</name>
                            <date>1125</date>: continued to <name type="person">Symon</name>
                            <date>1204</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Winchester</name>: original to <name type="person">Henricus</name>
                            <date>1129</date>: continued to <name type="person">Petrus</name>
                            <date>1206</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Salisbury</name>: original to <name type="person">Gocelinus</name>
                            <date>1142</date>: continued to <name type="person">Herebertus</name>
                            <date>1194</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Wells</name>: original to <name type="person">Godefridus</name>
                            <date>1123</date>: continued to <name type="person">Jocelinus</name>
                            <date>1206</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Exeter</name>: original to <name type="person">Willelmus</name>
                            <date>1107-38</date>: continued to <name type="person">Henricus</name>
                            <date>1194</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Lichfield</name>: original to <name type="person">Rotbertus (II)</name>
                            <date>1121</date>: continued to <name type="person">Galfridus</name>
                            <date>1198</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Hereford</name>: original to <name type="person">Ricardus</name>
                            <date>1120</date>: continued to <name type="person">Egidius</name>
                            <date>1200</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Worcester</name>: original to <name type="person">Theouulfus</name>
                            <date>1115-23</date>: continued to <name type="person">(M)augerus</name>
                            <date>1200</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Leicester (Loegerenses)</name>: original to <name type="person">Rotbertus
                                (II)</name>: continued to <name type="person">Hugo</name><lb/>
                            <name type="place">York</name>: original to <name type="person">Turstanus</name>
                            <date>1119</date>: continued to <name type="person">Galfridus</name>
                            <date>1191</date><lb/>
                            <name type="place">Durham</name>: original to <name type="person">Randulfus</name>
                            <date>1099-1133</date>: continued to <name type="person">Philippus</name>
                            <date>1197</date></ab>

                        <ab locus="12v">Paragraphs on the seven kingdoms, ending with one <q>De sedibus episcoporum in
                                concilio</q> (<ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1848">Thorpe I 280</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>ff. <locus>13r</locus>-<locus>14v</locus> blank</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="15r">Primus liber incipit ab <name type="person">Adam</name> usque ad
                            Christum</rubric>
                        <ab>(ed. <ref type="bibl" target="Howard 1592">Howard 1592</ref>: not in <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Petrie 1848">MHB</ref> or <ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1848"
                            >Thorpe</ref>)</ab>
                        <rubric locus="15r">Incipit Epistola <name type="person">Dionisii</name> exigui ad <name
                                type="person">petronium episcopum</name> de ratione paschali</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="15r">Domino beatissimo etc.</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="15r">
                            <decoNote>A pretty initial in pale colours</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="19r"><name type="person">Adam</name> centum xxx annorum</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="19r">
                            <decoNote>Another pretty initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Marginal additions occur: chiefly laudes of Emperors</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>90v</locus> begins</ab>
                        <incipit locus="90v">Angli saxones martiani principis tempore <name type="person">Beda</name>
                            teste</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1848">Thorpe I 1</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Petrie 1848">MHB 522</ref>)</ab>
                        <incipit locus="150v">Adueniente quadragesima</incipit>
                        <ab>(<date>1067</date>: <ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1849">Thorpe II 1</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="175r">
                            <handNote>The hand changes very distinctly at f. <locus>175r</locus>. The hand of the
                                portion after f. <locus>175r</locus> is of the same character as that of the
                                (Peterborough) Chronicle and Bestiary in <ref type="ms" target="CCC053">MS
                                53</ref></handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>175v</locus> (anno <date>1152</date>)</ab>
                        <rubric locus="175v"><name type="person">Conrado imperatori</name> successit <name type="person"
                                >Fridericus imperator</name></rubric>
                        <ab>(<decoNote>in red</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="175v">Celebratum est diuorcium inter <name type="person"
                            >lodowicum</name></incipit>
                        <ab>(This is the continuation, preserved in this MS. only, <ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1849"
                                >Thorpe II 136</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>Ends (<date>1295</date>)</ab>
                        <explicit locus="203r">ad debellandum inimicos suos</explicit>
                        <ab locus="203v">blank</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>204r</locus> are numbers</ab>
                        <ab>on f. <locus>204v</locus> pencil notes, partly obliterated, of events going down to <date>18
                                Edward I</date></ab>

                        <ab>The continuation really begins at <date>1118</date> (<ref type="bibl" target="Thorpe 1849"
                                >Thorpe II 71</ref>). From <date>1131</date> to <date>1152</date> it is merely a copy of
                                <name type="author">Henry of Huntingdon</name>
                            <hi rend="footnote">p. 253, l. 1 to p. 291, l. 29 collocatus (<ref type="bibl"
                                    target="Arnold 1879">Rolls Series</ref>)</hi>, and <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Thorpe 1849">Thorpe</ref> does not print it</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote/>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, SP</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 14/10/08</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
