<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC093">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>93</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>C. 6</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>26</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Ordinal and Martyrology of Exeter</head>
                <head type="James">Ioh. de Grandisson Ordinale et Martyrologium Exoniense</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">365</height>
                        <width unit="mm">250</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">14.6 x 9.8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 178 (176)</extent>,
                        <layout>mostly in double columns of 40 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv early</origDate>,
                        <handNote>very well written</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1<num>4</num> (1 stuck to cover, 2 cut out) 2<num>8</num> (1, 2 cut out)
                            3<num>8</num>-23<num>8</num> (wants 8)</collation>.</p>


                <p><name type="person">Mr Bradshaw</name> has foliated the book and noted the defects.</p>
                <p>On the flyleaf <supplied>(f. <locus>3r</locus>)</supplied> (<origDate>xvi</origDate>): <q>This ys
                            <name type="person">Walter Babington</name> his booke recorde of <name type="person">James
                            pollard</name> and of <name type="person">henry pollarde</name> and off <name type="person"
                            >Anthonye Ashe ham</name> and many more</q>. At the end <supplied>(f.
                        <locus>178v</locus>)</supplied> a similar note, ending: <q>record of <name type="person"
                            >Thamasyn</name> his wyffe</q>, etc.</p>

                <p rend="afterContents">The volume <q>may thus be described as an <name type="place">Exeter
                            Cathedral</name> Ordinale for choir and missal services (with a kalendar and 31 chapters of
                        cathedral customs prefixed) drawn up from Exeter and Sarum uses by <name type="person">Bishop
                            John de Grandisson</name> in <date>1337</date> and with a Martyrology ... adapted by the
                        same prelate. Thus the book corresponds in contents, so far as the Ordinale goes, with a MS. in
                        Exeter Cathedral Library (<ref type="ms" target="ECL502">3502</ref>) eighty leaves of which,
                        corresponding with ff. 7-105 of the C. C. C. MS., were printed by the<ref type="bibl"
                            target="Reynolds 1891"> Rev. H. E. Reynolds</ref> (fol. 1884) and (possibly) with the
                        Martyrology (<date>xii</date>th cent, with local additions) in the same library (<ref type="ms"
                            target="ECL518">3518</ref>). The Parker MS. has a brief supplement (also composed by <name
                            type="person">Bishop Grandisson</name>) for the use of <name type="place">Exeter Lady
                            Chapel</name>, which is said to be wanting in the MS. at <name type="place"
                        >Exeter</name>.</q></p>

                <p rend="afterContents">The whole <hi rend="italic">Ordinale Exoniense</hi> has since been printed from
                    this and other MSS. by the <ref type="bibl" target="Dalton 1909">Rev. J. N. Dalton, Canon of Windsor
                        (Henry Bradshaw Society, 1909)</ref>. The description in his introduction supersedes mine.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. 1v (paste-down) (2 missing) + 3-4 (5-6 missing) + 7-64 + 64a +
                    65-178</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="7r" locusEnd="176r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Ordinal and Martyrology of <name type="place">Exeter</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title><name type="author">Iohannes de Grandisson</name> Ordinale et Martyrologium <name
                                    type="place">Exoniense</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The following list of the contents, drawn up by the <name type="person">Rev. Chr.
                                Wordsworth</name> in <date>1896</date>, will be of interest. I add some details to
                            it</ab>

                        <ab>ff. <locus>7r</locus>-<locus>12v</locus>. Kalendar of <name type="place">Exeter</name> use
                                (<decoNote>in blue, red and black</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <ab>In the Kalendar I note</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="7r"><hi rend="bold">January</hi><lb/> 7. <name type="person">Brannoci Abbatis
                                C.</name></ab>

                        <ab locusNew="8r"><hi rend="bold">March</hi><lb/> 1. <name type="person">David, Episcopi
                                Exoniensis</name><lb/> 2. <name type="person">Cedde Episcopi</name><lb/> 5. <name
                                type="person">Kerani Exoniensis</name></ab>

                        <ab locusNew="9r"><hi rend="bold">May</hi><lb/> 7. <name type="person">Iohannis de
                                beuerlaco</name></ab>

                        <ab locusNew="9v"><hi rend="bold">June</hi><lb/> 4. <name type="person">Petroci
                                Confessoris</name><lb/> 16. Translatio <name type="person">S. Richardi Episcopi</name>
                            [a later note: <q>Exon. nihil set SS. <name type="person">Ciriaci</name> et <name
                                    type="person">Iulitte</name> MM.</q>]</ab>


                        <ab locusNew="10r"><hi rend="bold">July</hi><lb/> 1. Octava <name type="person">Sancti Johannis
                                Baptiste</name> Memoria tantum Exoniensis<lb/> 2. Visitatio <name type="person">beate
                                marie virginis</name>
                            <decoNote>in red</decoNote><lb/> 7. Translation of <name type="person">Thomas</name>
                            erased<lb/> 15. Translatio <name type="person">Sancti Swithuni Episcopi</name> ix lectiones
                            unius episcopi et confessoris non plurimorum ut <name type="place">Sarum</name> propter
                                <name type="place">Wodebury</name></ab>
                        <ab>I find no entry of <name type="person">S. Sativola</name>, but she is mentioned on f.
                                <locus>18r</locus>, col. 2 between <name type="person">Margaret</name> and Invention of
                                <name type="person">Stephen</name>, and in the Martyrology f. <locus>154v</locus> on 2
                            August</ab>


                        <ab locusNew="11r">
                            <hi rend="bold">September</hi>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric>7. Prima feria secunde istius mensis fiat festum <name type="person">S. Gabrielis
                                Archangeli</name> maius duplex</rubric>


                        <ab locusNew="11v"><hi rend="bold">October</hi><lb/> 1. <name type="person">Melori</name><lb/>
                            2. <name type="person">Thome Herfordensis Episcopi</name><lb/> 5. <name type="person"
                                >Raphaelis</name>
                            <decoNote>in red</decoNote></ab>


                        <ab locusNew="12r"><hi rend="bold">November</hi><lb/> 3. <name type="person">Wenefrede</name>
                            added<lb/> 21. Dedicatio <name type="place">ecclesie beati Petri Exoniensis</name> maius
                            duplex; <decoNote>in blue</decoNote> with octave</ab>

                        <ab locusNew="12v"><hi rend="bold">December</hi><lb/> 4. Depositio <name type="person">S.
                                Osmundi Episcopi</name><lb/> 29. <name type="person">Thomas of Canterbury</name>
                            erased</ab>

                        <ab>ff. <locus>13r</locus>-<locus>20r</locus> Consuetudines generales of <name type="place"
                                >Exeter Cathedral Church</name> (relating to Dean, Precentor, Chancellor, Treasurer,
                            Archdeacons, Succentor, Sub-treasurer, Clerk of <name type="place">St Mary's</name>,
                            Residence, Priest-vicars, Choristers, Behaviour, Colours of vestments, Rulers of Choir,
                            Books: cap. I-XXXI)</ab>

                        <ab>f. <locus>13r</locus> has <decoNote>initial and feather-ornament</decoNote>. A note of
                            Parker's time is at the foot of the page, giving an extract from <name type="person">Bishop
                                Grandisson</name>'s will</ab>
                        <ab>f. <locus>20v</locus> blank</ab>

                        <ab locus="21r">
                            <name type="place">Exeter</name> ordinale diuini officii (choir service) </ab>
                        <ab locus="21r">de Tempore</ab>
                        <ab>(Advent, etc.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="21r"><decoNote>f. <locus>21r</locus> is fully bordered. Portions of the
                                decoration, consisting of roses and other flowers, in a bright hard style, seem to me to
                                have been added late in cent. <origDate>xv</origDate>. At each angle is a monogram
                                (original) of the letters <q>WS</q></decoNote>. These may stand for <name type="person"
                                >William Steele</name>, who was Archdeacon of Totnes about <date>1370</date> (<ref
                                type="bibl" target="Oliver 1861">Oliver, <hi rend="italic">Lives of Bishops of
                                    Exeter</hi>, p. 291</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="74v">de Dedicatione Ecclesie</ab>
                        <ab>(Anniversary)</ab>
                        <ab locus="75r">de proprio Sanctorum</ab>
                        <ab>(<name type="person">St Andrew</name>, etc.)</ab>
                        <ab locus="102v">de communi sanctorum</ab>
                        <!--<ab locusNew="102v">Music, square chant notation on 4 line stave.  2x: "Tristes erant apostoli" and 2x: "Claro paschali gaudio"</ab>-->

                        <ab>
                            <name type="place">Exeter</name> ordinale </ab>
                        <rubric locus="106r">de Missa</rubric>
                        <ab>(Altar service)</ab>
                        <ab locus="106r">de Tempore</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="106r">
                            <decoNote>f. <locus>106r</locus> has border on three sides</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="121r">de Dedicatione Ecclesie</ab>
                        <ab locus="121r">de Proprio Sanctorum</ab>
                        <ab locus="129r">de Communi Sanctorum</ab>
                        <ab locus="130r">de Commemoracione <name type="person">Beate Marie</name> [hebdomadali]</ab>
                        <ab locus="130v">de Commemoracione Sancti Crucis [hebdomadali]</ab>
                        <ab locus="130v">Missa salus populi pro fratribus et sororibus [votiua]</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="130v">Missa Da pacem pro pace</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="130v">Missa pro serenitate aeris</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="130v">Missa in quacumque tribulacione</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="130v">De Alleluya in pleno seruicio <name type="person">Beate Marie</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="131r" locusNew="130v">Misse pro Defunctis</ab>

                        <ab locus="132r"> Martilogium ad usum Exoniensem per <name type="person">Johannem de
                                Grandisson</name> dispositum </ab>
                        <ab>It does not contain the <name type="place">Exeter</name> obits</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="132r">
                            <decoNote>f. <locus>132r</locus>, full border with monogram of <q>WS</q> at each
                                corner</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="172r">Ad sciendum quod (quando?) Kyrie uel Gloria in excelsis uel Sanctus uel
                            Agnus debent dici in choro</incipit>
                        <!--<ab locusNew="172v">Music, as before.  Incipit to a kyrie and to an agnus dei</ab>-->

                        <rubric locus="174v">Incipit ordinale officiorum <name type="person">Beate Virginis Marie</name>
                            in capella</rubric>
                        <ab>(arranged by <name type="person">Grandisson</name> in order to keep a weekly memory of the
                            Seven Joys)</ab>
                        <ab locus="175r">Benedicciones dicende [ad lecciones]</ab>
                        <ab>ff. <locus locusNew="176v">176r</locus>-<locus>178v</locus> blank</ab>


                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 19.06.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
