<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC097">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>97</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. 4,5</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Certificates and Returns of Livings of the Province of Canterbury</head>

                <head type="James">Certificates</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">315</height>
                        <width unit="mm">413</width>
                    </measureGrp>, oblong folio, <measureGrp type="James">12.7 x 16.8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff.
                        249</extent>. <supplied>Cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate></supplied>.</p>

                <p function="Research">The Certificates described by Nasmith <supplied>(see <ref type="ms"
                            target="CCC122">MS 122</ref>)</supplied> were partly in book-form, partly on rolls. All are
                    now bound in book-form. The present order of contents <supplied>for this volume</supplied> is
                        <supplied>given below</supplied>.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-ii + (1 missing) 2-39 + 39a + 40-127 + 127a-b + 128-249 + iii-iv</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="eng" otherLangs="lat">English and Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="2r" locusEnd="28v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Rental etc. of <name type="place">Merton College Oxford</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Rentale et status collegii [de <name type="place">Merton Oxon.</name>]</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="2">Roll cut up and bound; the beginning is fragmentary. Rental etc. of <name
                                type="place">Merton College, Oxford</name></ab>
                        <ab>(Marked as missing in <ref type="ms" target="CCC575">Parker's Register</ref>)</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="29r" locusEnd="33v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Returns for Archdeaconry of <name type="place">Coventry</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Certificatoria singulorum episcoporum <name type="place">provinciae Cantuar.</name>
                                de statu ecclesiastico diceces. suarum, ubi notantur nomina omnium rectorum vicariorum
                                et curatorum, utrum sint conjugati, docti vel indocti, residentes vel non residentes,
                                utrum praedicent, vel sint hospitales, et quot beneficia habent: facta A. D.
                                    <date>1560</date>, et seq.</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="29r">Returns for Archdeaconry of <name type="place">Coventry</name>, giving the
                            Deaneries of <name type="place">Stonley</name>, <name type="place">Marton</name>, <name
                                type="place">Coventry</name>, <name type="place">Arden</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="34r" locusEnd="48v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Charter of <name type="person">Elizabeth I</name> confirming the <name type="place"
                                    >University of Cambridge</name>'s priviliges</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Carta <name type="person">reginae Elisabethae</name> de privilegiis academiae
                                Cantab.</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="34r">Carta <name type="person">Elizabethae</name> de privilegiis Cantabr.</ab>
                        <ab>(Marked as missing in <ref type="ms" target="CCC575">Parker's Register</ref>)</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="49r" locusEnd="249r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Certificates and returns of livings of the <name type="place">Province of
                                    Canterbury</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Certificatoria singulorum episcoporum <name type="place">provinciae Cantuar.</name>
                                de statu ecclesiastico diceces. suarum, ubi notantur nomina omnium rectorum vicariorum
                                et curatorum, utrum sint conjugati, docti vel indocti, residentes vel non residentes,
                                utrum praedicent, vel sint hospitales, et quot beneficia habent: facta A. D.
                                    <date>1560</date>, et seq.</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="49r">Returns for <name type="place">Lincoln</name> diocese</ab>
                        <ab locus="96r">Deaneries of <name type="place">Pagham</name> and <name type="place">South
                                Malling</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="97r"><supplied>Deaneries</supplied> of the arches <name type="place"
                            >London</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="98v">Diocese of <name type="place">Llandaff</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="104v">
                            <supplied>Diocese of</supplied>
                            <name type="place">Gloucester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="116r">
                            <supplied>Diocese of</supplied>
                            <name type="place">Wells</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="124r">Diocese of <name type="place">Bangor</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="128r">
                            <supplied>Diocese of</supplied>
                            <name type="place">Worcester</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="133r">
                            <supplied>Diocese of</supplied>
                            <name type="place">Bristol</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="149r">
                            <supplied>Diocese of </supplied>
                            <name type="place">Hereford</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="156r">
                            <supplied>Diocese of</supplied>
                            <name type="place">Exeter</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="184r">
                            <supplied>Diocese of </supplied>
                            <name type="place">Sarum</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="198r"><supplied>Diocese of</supplied>
                            <name type="place">Norwich</name>
                            <locus>198r</locus>-<locus>249r</locus></ab>
                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Frere 1904">Frere, <hi rend="italic">Hist. Engl. Church, Eliz.
                                    and James</hi> 103</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: KAW 21.4.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
