<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC105" n="MS 105">
                <p>Matthew Parker's manuscript collection naturally reflects his interest in Reformation theology and a
                    large part of the material bound together in MS 105 reflects this interest. This volume contains a
                    copy of Philip Melanchthon (1497-1560), <title>De libro Coloniensis</title> and tracts on issues
                    such as marriage to the sister of a deceased wife, the removal of images from churches and in
                    defence of the English Reformation. However this manuscript also includes evidence of other aspects
                    of Parker's career and interests. There are numerous documents and accounts relating to the uneasy
                    relations between England and Scotland at the start of Elizabeth's reign, a result of Parker's
                    involvement with Elizabeth's rule. There is also an Anglo-Saxon wordlist, a reflection of Parker's
                    interest in the church in Anglo-Saxon England. The volume also includes accounts of the coronation
                    of king Edward VI, the baptism of Elizabeth I and excerpts from the Croyland continuation of Peter
                    of Blois regarding the foundation of the University of Cambridge. The manuscript dates to the third
                    quarter of the sixteenth century.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
