<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC111" n="MS 111">
                <p>This large composite volume contains much important documentary material from Anglo-Saxon England, in
                    both medieval and antiquarian copies. Pp. 1-132 relate to Bath Abbey; some of this material was
                    previously bound with <ref type="ms" target="CCC140">CCCC MS 140</ref>, the Bath Old English Gospel
                    Book. This section starts with an Old English relic-list of Bath and some Old English manumissions,
                    which were written into <ref type="ms" target="CCC140">CCCC MS 140</ref> to emphasise their legal
                    and religious importance. These are followed by a short twelfth-century gospel lectionary. There is
                    also the unique manuscript of the pilgrimage of Sæwulf to Jerusalem in 1102-1103, and an important
                    post-Conquest Old English confraternity agreement between various western religious houses,
                    predominantly Chertsey, Bath, Pershore, Evesham, Winchcombe, Gloucester and Worcester, with the
                    names of some of the monks. On p. 57 starts the Bath Cartulary proper, an important twelfth-century
                    record of Bath Abbey's archives. This contains a large number of Anglo-Saxon charters, which have
                    recently been definitively edited by Susan Kelly, and more charters from the post-Conquest period
                    into the reign of Henry II. It also contains an important Domesday satellite survey, probably part
                    of the material drawn up to be used in the creation of Domesday Book proper. Pp. 139-78 constitute a
                    very important set of transcripts by Robert Talbot (c. 1505-1558) predominantly of original
                    Anglo-Saxon charters from the archives of Abingdon Abbey in the possession of Dr George Owen (d.
                    1558). These documents have since been lost making this the only witness to their text. This
                    collection was acquired early by Parker, who added some material. Pp. 187-317, which have their own
                    pagination showing that they were once a separate volume, contain another collection of
                    sixteenth-century antiquarian transcripts of medieval charters. This compilation is descended from
                    the 'Prise-Say' collection of monastic foundation charters, made by William Say at the request of
                    Sir John Prise in 1535, during the dissolution of the monasteries. This section of CCCC MS 111
                    starts with accounts of the foundations of monastic houses with a note saying it was compiled by the
                    antiquary John Stow (c. 1525-1605) in September 1566, clearly using the Prise-Say register. There
                    are also copies of charters from the Prise-Say collection (which survives in a manuscript at
                    Winchester Cathedral) and miscellaneous supplementary material from a different but related source.
                    The manuscript concludes with material largely relating to the dissolution of the monasteries.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
