<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC140" n="MS 140">
                <p>CCCC MS 140 contains the four gospels in Old English, specifically in West-Saxon Old English, written
                    in the second half of the eleventh century at Bath Abbey in Somerset. Each of the gospels was
                    written by a different scribe in codicologically separate sections, but this was probably for speed
                    of production rather than because the gospels were originally kept separately. The scribe of Matthew
                    ended with a colophon naming himself as one Ælfric, and stating that he wrote at Bath for the
                    benefit of a certain Brihtwold. The manuscript attracted early additions, especially of documents,
                    in the manner typical of Latin gospel books, suggesting that its language gave it no lower status.
                    These include many manumissions of slaves and an agreement between the prior of Bath and some
                    townspeople. Some of MS 140 was moved by Parker into <ref type="ms" target="CCC111">CCCC MS
                        111</ref>, which contains among other things the twelfth-century Bath cartulary, presumably to
                    keep the Bath documents together; these leaves now constitute pp. 7-8 and 55-56 of <ref type="ms"
                        target="CCC111">MS 111</ref>, and contain further manumissions and two lists of Bath's
                    relic-collections. These displaced pages also include a very interesting agreement of confraternity
                    between various West Country houses including Bath, dating from the time of Bishop Wulfstan II
                    (1062-1095).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
