<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC163" n="MS 163">
                <p>CCCC MS 163 contains a Pontifical of the Romano-Germanic type. It was written in the second half of
                    the eleventh century, probably at Worcester, although the Old Minster and the Nunnaminster at
                    Winchester have both also been suggested. In text it is closely related to London, BL MS Cotton
                    Vitellius E. XII, and may even have been directly copied from it. The Romano-Germanic Pontifical
                    originated in Germany in the tenth century and spread rapidly because it brought together a
                    comprehensive set of texts for performing the duties of a bishop. These two English copies seem to
                    descend from a Cologne manuscript, and it has been suggested that the line of transmission was
                    Bishop Ealdred's visit to Cologne in 1054. Ealdred, bishop of Worcester and later archbishop of
                    Canterbury, was sent by Edward the Confessor on a diplomatic mission to Henry III, probably leading
                    to the return to England of Edward the Exile in 1057, and it seems likely that he acquired a text of
                    the Romano-Germanic pontifical on this occasion. MS 163 contains four ordines for the consecration
                    of women while omitting all those for abbots and monks, and may therefore have some connection with
                    a nunnery.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
