<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC173" n="MS 173">
                <p>In CCCC MS 173 is found the Parker Chronicle, one of the most important manuscripts for our
                    understanding of Anglo-Saxon history. The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle, the earliest history written in
                    English, seems to have originated under the impetus of Alfred the Great's educational reforms, and a
                    core set of annals was composed which were then augmented variously over the years in different
                    places. Every version of the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle is therefore different and has its own
                    complicated transmission history. The Parker Chronicle, also known as the A-version, is the oldest
                    manuscript surviving. It was started in the late ninth century and continued into the eleventh. It
                    originated somewhere in Wessex, probably Winchester where it has mid tenth-century provenance, but
                    had moved to the cathedral priory of Christ Church, Canterbury by the end of the eleventh century.
                    Although the Chronicle is the most famous part of the manuscript, it also contains other very
                    important material. In the same section as the Chronicle there are important early texts of the Old
                    English laws of Alfred the Great and the late seventh-century laws of his distant predecessor on the
                    throne of Wessex, King Ine (d. in or after 726), as well as a list of bishops and popes. A second
                    volume was already bound with the Chronicle manuscript in the Middle Ages: this contains works by
                    the late Antique poet Sedulius (fl. first half of the fifth century), in particular his
                        <title>Carmen paschale</title>, a retelling of the gospels in bombastic Virgilian Latin verse.
                    This part of the manuscript is older than the Chronicle, probably dating to the third quarter of the
                    eighth century, and is an important witness to English scholarship before the disruption caused in
                    the ninth century by Viking attacks. It seems to have the name of Frithestan, bishop of Winchester
                    909-31, on f. 57r. The volume was greatly valued by Parker and his circle; Parker brought the list
                    of archbishops of Canterbury up to date to include own name. It was also used in the earliest
                    printed book in Old English, Parker's <title>Testimonie of Antiquitie</title>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
