<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC176" n="MS 176">
                <p>CCCC "MS" 176 consists of three printed books bound together and, although the policy of the Parker
                    on the Web project was not to image printed material, an exception was made in this instance because
                    of the particular interest of the first and last items. All three parts were printed in 1574 and
                    were edited by (or under the auspices of) Archbishop Matthew Parker from his own manuscript
                    collections. Two were printed by the famous evangelical printer John Day (d. 1584), who produced
                    Parker's most important publications, and one by John Bynneman (d. 1583), who was also patronised by
                    Parker. Part A is Parker's important <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> of Asser's <title>Life
                        of Alfred</title>, containing parallel Latin and Old English material, printed in a special
                    Insular typeface. Because the only medieval manuscript of this work was completely destroyed in the
                    Cottonian fire of 1731, modern editions have had to depend on transcripts and the early printed
                    editions, most of which descend in some way from Parker's work. Parker interpolated Asser's life
                    with material from the Annals of St Neots, and thus popularised the famous story of Alfred burning
                    the cakes while hiding in the Somerset marshes. This book was an important part of the early modern
                    cult of Alfred the Great. Parts B and C are Thomas of Walsingham's <title>Historia breuis</title>,
                    and the <title>Ypodigma Neustriae</title> also often attributed to him. The latter is taken from the
                    unique surviving copy in <ref type="ms" target="CCC240">CCCC MS 240</ref>, which cannot be
                    completely digitised due to the delicate state of its early modern binding. It consists of a
                    chronicle of events in Normandy and England from 911 AD to 1416 AD and written, perhaps, as a
                    flattery to Henry V's successful conquests in France. This book is mentioned in the Parker register
                    and came to Corpus with the majority of Parker's collection. The three sections are also found bound
                    together in the Cambridge University Library copy, in the three British Library copies, and in
                    another which came into the possession of Corpus in the nineteenth century, suggesting that Parker
                    had the three texts circulated together. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
