<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC178" n="MS 178">
                <p>CCCC MS 178 consists of two Anglo-Saxon manuscripts bound together. The first is a collection of Old
                    English homilies, mostly by Ælfric OSB (d. c. 1010) but with some anonymous and composite material.
                    It was written in the first half of the eleventh century, probably towards the end of that period. A
                    colophon lays out the compiler's intentions: twelve sermons are given which may be preached at any
                    time, and another twelve for specific occasions; twenty-two of these are taken exactly from an
                    exemplar but two have been augmented; the sermons for specific days are by Ælfric. This colophon
                    seems more or less accurate when compared to the manuscript as it survives. It was at Worcester by
                    the end of the eleventh century, when it was annotated by the scribe Coleman, probably the chaplain
                    of Wulfstan, bishop of Worcester (d. 1095). Parker removed some leaves of this part of MS 178 into
                        <ref type="ms" target="CCC162">CCCC MS 162</ref>. The second Anglo-Saxon manuscript is a copy of
                    the bilingual Benedictine Rule, with each chapter in Latin followed by its translation into Old
                    English. It contains some feminine forms but seems to represent a stage in the transmission of the
                    text where it was being changed from nuns' to monks' use. It was written in the first half of the
                    eleventh century. It was certainly at Worcester, and probably already associated with the homily
                    manuscript, in the thirteenth century when both were annotated by the famous 'Worcester Tremulous
                    Hand'.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
