<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC183" n="MS 183">
                <p>CCCC MS 183 is one of several manuscripts associated with Æthelstan, King of the English (924/5-39),
                    but the only one of these written in England in his reign. He seems to have commissioned it for
                    presentation to the community of St Cuthbert, which at this point was at Chester-le-Street in
                    Country Durham, having fled Lindisfarne to escape Viking attacks but not yet settled in its eventual
                    home at Durham. The famous presentation picture shows Æthelstan, with bowed head, presenting the
                    book to St Cuthbert himself, and is a very important example of the revival of figure art in
                    manuscript painting during Æthelstan's reign. It was written between 934 and 939, the year of
                    Æthelstan's death, by a scribe who also appears in London, BL MS Royal 7. D. XXIV, perhaps at
                    Glastonbury, but certainly somewhere in the south of England. It contains Bede's two Lives of St
                    Cuthbert, the first in prose and the second metrical, and a mass and office for Cuthbert's feast
                    day, as well as lists of popes, bishops, and kings, and a record of Æthelstan's other gifts to the
                    community. Its production can be linked to Æthelstan's political activities in the North.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
