<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC197B" n="MS 197B">
                <p>This manuscript constitutes the surviving portion of the 'Cotton-Corpus' Gospels; the larger part,
                    now London, BL MS Cotton Otho C. V, was badly damaged in the Cottonian fire of 1731 and only burnt
                    fragments remain. A bifolium of canon tables, probably also from this manuscript, survives as
                    London, BL MS Royal 7. C. XII, ff. 2-3. The original manuscript was a lavish Insular Gospel Book
                    with elaborate decoration; in the Corpus part the eagle symbol of St John the evangelist still
                    survives, and elaborate decorative initials incorporating a range of interlace and other ornament.
                    It belongs in a group with the Durham Gospels, the Echternach Gospels, and the Lindisfarne Gospels.
                    Both Parker and Cotton recorded on their respective parts of the original book that it was believed
                    to have been owned by St Augustine, first archbishop of Canterbury, who was sent by Pope Gregory the
                    Great to England in 597. The date of the manuscript rules this out: it seems to be from late
                    seventh- or early eighth-century Northumbria. However it is possible that this tradition arose in
                    the Middle Ages, as one of the volumes which Thomas Elmham (d. c. 1427) recorded among those revered
                    as sent from Gregory to Augustine was probably an early Insular Gospel-book of this type. The same
                    provenance was attributed anachronistically to other early Anglo-Saxon manuscripts at St
                    Augustine's, Canterbury.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
