<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC201" n="MS 201">
                <p>CCCC MS 201 is a composite volume which can be divided chronologically into three parts, probably
                    first bound together by Parker. Pp. 1-7 and 161-7 are the oldest, written in the early eleventh
                    century; they contain a fragment of the Old English <title>Regularis concordia</title>, the code of
                    monastic observance, and some Old English religious poems, most notably <title>Judgement Day
                        II</title>, a translation of Bede's <title>De die iudicii</title>. The rest of the volume up to
                    p. 178 was written probably in the first half or middle of the eleventh century, and contains a
                    large number of sermons by Archbishop Wulfstan (d. 1023), as well as a collection of ecclesiastical
                    material, mostly in the vernacular. It has been interpreted as a version of Archbishop Wulfstan's
                    Handbook. It contains several law codes, predominantly the work of Wulfstan himself, the Old English
                    tract on the resting places of saints, and the Old English romance <title>Apollonius of
                    Tyre</title>. Bishop identified a scribe in this section of the book as working at the New Minster,
                    Winchester, but a Worcester or York association has also been suggested, since these were the main
                    seats of Wulfstan himself. The third part was written at Exeter in the time of Bishop Leofric
                    (1050-72) and was probably once part of <ref type="ms" target="CCC196">CCCC MS 196</ref>. It
                    contains the bilingual version of Theodulf of Orléans (d. 821), <title>Capitula</title>, a homily,
                    and part of the Martyrology of Usuard (fl. 841-58). This manuscript did not come to Corpus Christi
                    with the rest of the Corpus Parkerian collection in 1575, and is not included in the Parker
                    Register; instead it was one of the large number of books which Archbishop Parker gave to his son
                    John Parker, who played an active role in his father's circle of scholarship. It had arrived at
                    Corpus by 1600, before the later financial troubles which probably led to the majority of John
                    Parker's books travelling to Trinity College via the gift of Neville. The manuscript later acquired
                    a contents-list by the great Anglo-Saxonist Abraham Wheelock (d. 1653).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
