<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC023" n="MS 23">
                <p>CCCC MS 23 consists of two volumes bound together. The first is a famous illustrated manuscript of
                    works by Prudentius (fl. 384-410), most significantly his <title>Psychomachia</title>, a poem about
                    spiritual warfare between personifications of the vices and virtues. Many line drawings in coloured
                    ink illustrate events in the text. It was made in England probably in the late tenth century, and it
                    shares an artist with Bodleian Library MS Junius 11, the Junius manuscript of Old English poetry.
                    Art-historical evidence has tended to link the production of part one of CCCC MS 23 with Canterbury,
                    but a presentation inscription gives the manuscript provenance at Malmesbury, and it has also been
                    suggested that it could have been made there. In the eleventh century Old English captions were
                    added to the pictures. The second volume is a copy of Orosius, <title>Historia adversus
                        paganos</title> of 417-18, written by six scribes working at Dover in the second quarter of the
                    twelfth century. One of these scribes is also found in <ref type="ms" target="CCC462">CCCC MS
                        462</ref>. The two manuscripts were probably bound together by Parker.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
