<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC270" n="MS 270">
                <p>This Missal is written in the beautiful round script particularly associated with St Augustine's
                    Abbey, Canterbury, in the second half of the eleventh century. We know that this manuscript was
                    written after 1091 because it contains a mass for the translation of St Augustine in this year. As
                    such it shows the typical English script of the eleventh century being written well after the Norman
                    Conquest, in contrast to the spiky script written at nearby Christ Church at this time. T. A. M.
                    Bishop identified the work of some of CCCC MS 270's scribes in other manuscripts from St
                    Augustine's, Canterbury. Arguments on textual grounds that the manuscript must have been written
                    before 1100 are unconvincing in themselves, but this style of script would not be expected to have
                    lasted very long into the twelfth century. The manuscript has flyleaves written in late eleventh- or
                    twelfth-century script, containing text from Bede's <title>Historia ecclesiastica</title>. It is
                    possible that these leaves were not taken from a dismantled copy of Bede's work, but were rather
                    leaves rejected during the production of a manuscript, and if so then they may have been used in the
                    binding of MS 270 at an early date.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
