<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC272" n="MS 272">
                <p>This manuscript is known as the 'Achadeus Psalter' because of an inscription after Psalm 150
                    recording that Count Achadeus ordered it to be made. This need not imply, however, that Achadeus
                    owned the book, or had any closer connection with it than simply paying for its materials. As well
                    as the psalms and canticles the manuscript contains Psalter collects, a litany, and prayers. The
                    litany includes mention of Pope Marinus (882-4), King Carloman (882-3), and Fulk, bishop of Rheims
                    (883-900), and has on these grounds been dated to 883/4; the mention of Bishop Fulk and of local
                    saints locates its use to Rheims. Although not necessarily made in the city itself, it seems to be
                    from that region of France. CCCC MS 272 contains extensive marginal glosses largely taken from
                    Cassiodorus' <title>Expositio psalmorum</title>. They are written in that form of English Caroline
                    minuscule which developed in the first quarter of the eleventh century and continued in use until
                    after the Norman Conquest. Consequently it seems that the manuscript was in England in the eleventh
                    century; it has been suggested that it was brought over earlier than that, perhaps even by Grimbald
                    of Saint-Bertin, who was sent to England by Fulk of Rheims in order to assist King Alfred the Great
                    with his revival of English learning. If so the manuscript must have left Rheims relatively soon
                    after it was made, as Grimbald was at Winchester by 887, and doubt has been expressed over whether a
                    manuscript sponsored by an important count would have been lightly alienated. The manuscript has
                    illumination in gold and colours and originally had large illuminated initials at the liturgical
                    divisions of the Psalter, although all save that for Psalm 97 have been cut out. The Litany has
                    elaborate arched column frames, and at the beginning of the Psalter a large B ornamental initial for
                    the first psalm from an English early thirteenth-century Psalter has been inserted. MS 272 was
                    certainly at Canterbury in the later middle ages, where parts of account rolls of Christ Church
                    Canterbury are used as its endleaves.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
