<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC286" n="MS 286">
                <p>CCCC MS 286 is the famous manuscript known as the St Augustine Gospels. This is a late sixth-century
                    gospelbook which has for centuries been held to have been sent by Pope Gregory the Great with
                    Augustine of Canterbury (d. 604) when he arrived to christianise the English in 597. Certainly the
                    manuscript was in Canterbury by the end of the seventh century, and various additions were made
                    there, including some tenth-century Anglo-Saxon charters written between the gospels of Matthew and
                    Mark. Whether owned by Augustine himself, it almost certainly came to England with one of the early
                    waves of Roman missionaries; on occasion it has also been associated with St Mellitus (d. 624), and
                    with Minster-in-Thanet (Kent). CCCC MS 286 is the earliest surviving Gospel Book with figure
                    illumination: although most of it has been lost, with only a picture of Luke as a scribe under an
                    arcade, and a page of gospel images in a grid. Unfortunately, only these two of the probably eight
                    full-page pictures which the book contained have survived. These images seem to have been highly
                    influential on later English art; a number of Anglo-Saxon and Romanesque manuscripts seem to owe a
                    debt to its imagery, as does a famous scene in the Bayeux Tapestry. In the later Middle Ages this
                    manuscript was probably kept on the altar at St Augustine's, Canterbury, where Thomas of Elmham
                    describes a number of manuscripts associated with Augustine being kept. Unfortunately, most of these
                    are demonstrably later than Augustine's time. Parker may have been unaware of its assocation with
                    the Gregorian mission. In recent years it has continued to play a role outside the library: since
                    the Second World War it has been used in the enthronement of archbishops of Canterbury, and in 1982
                    it was put in the place of honour between Pope John Paul II and Archbishop Robert Runcie during the
                    first papal visit to England since the Reformation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
