<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC291" n="MS 291">
                <p>CCCC MS 291 is a compilation of material concerning the reckoning of time, written at St Augustine's,
                    Canterbury in the late eleventh or early twelfth century. The calculation of the date of Easter,
                    known as computus, is both very complex and very important to the church year; this compilation
                    explains the theoretical calculations as well as providing relevant tables. Bede's <title>De
                        temporum ratione</title>, the main text in the book, was a very popular work in the Middle Ages,
                    and remains a useful guide to computus; but there is an interesting disparity between Bede's
                    insistence that one should be able to divide by nineteen in one's head, and the table on f. 137
                    which lays out addition, subtraction and multiplication starting with 1 + 1 is 2. At the end the
                    manuscript contains a full Easter table for 1064 to 1595, a complete Dionysiac Great Paschal Cycle
                    (532 years, the product of the 19-year lunar cycle and the 28-year cycle of days of the week). The
                    book is written throughout in late Anglo-Caroline minuscule, although the decorated initials show
                    Norman influence; this gives an interesting insight into the cultural influences at work at St
                    Augustine's Abbey after the Norman Conquest.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
