<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC002II" n="MS 2II">
                <p>This great Bible, CCCC MS 2, one of the most famous of the books in the Parker Library, is now bound
                    in three volumes (2I, 2II, 2III), although once was a single volume. 2I contains ff. 1r-121v with
                    Jerome’s Prologue and the books from Genesis to Joshua; 2II contains ff. 122r-241v with the books
                    from Judges to Isaiah; 2III contains ff. 242r-357v with the books from Jeremiah to Job. The single
                    volume thus contained the books of the Old Testament from Genesis to Job, and the second volume with
                    the remainder of the Bible has not survived. It can be identified with a Bible commissioned by
                    Hervey, the sacrist, for his brother, Talbot, prior of Bury St Edmunds Abbey, c. 1135-8, which was
                    illuminated by Master Hugo. The miniatures and some of the illuminated initials are painted on
                    separate pieces of vellum stuck to the page, and the description of the Bible in the <title>Gesta
                        Sacristarum</title> attests that master Hugo 'was unable to find any suitable calf-hide in these
                    parts' and had to purchase parchment from Ireland. Six large full-page or half-page miniatures
                    preface some of the books, whereas the others have historiated or ornamental initials. Six of the
                    large pictures have been removed from the book and are lost. It is a prime example of the very large
                    luxury Bibles made in the twelfth century for monastic houses. The artist, Master Hugo, was
                    influenced by Byzantine painting, and may have seen either illuminated manuscripts opr
                    wall-paintings, such as those of Asinou in Cyprus which most closely resemble his style. The faces
                    are modelled with shading in green and grey, and the folds are divided into sections reflecting the
                    position of the limbs. This has been called the 'damp-fold' style and influenced many other artists
                    working in England in the period c. 1140-70 at Canterbury, Winchester and elsewhere. After the
                    dissolution of the abbey of Bury St Edmunds at the Reformation the Bible eventually came into the
                    hands of Matthew Parker.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
