<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC003" n="MS 3">
                <p>CCCC MSS 3-4 are a two-volume Bible made for Dover Priory, a dependency of Christ Church cathedral
                    priory, Canterbury. Like the Bury Bible, <ref type="ms" target="CCC002I">CCCC MS 2</ref>, it is of
                    very large size and typical of twelfth-century luxury monastic Bibles. This first volume contains
                    the Old Testament from Genesis to the Minor Prophets. There is no firm evidence for dating, although
                    a date c. 1150 is generally accepted. The script is close to the Eadwine Psalter (Cambridge, Trinity
                    College MS R.17.1) and dated charters produced at Canterbury in the 1150s. It seems fairly certain
                    that the mother house provided its dependency, Dover Priory, with the book, although at what date it
                    came to Dover is not known. It appears first in the 1389 catalogue of their books. There are
                    historiated or decorated initials at the beginning of the biblical books, illuminated by several
                    artists working in different styles. The artists of this first volume work in a Byzantinising style,
                    but different from that of Master Hugo in the Bury Bible, <ref type="ms" target="CCC002I">CCCC MS
                        2</ref>. Although it is also a version of the 'damp-fold' style, the folds are patterned in a
                    way closer to that of Byzantine artists. This artist of the Dover Bible may have travelled to Sicily
                    and was influenced by the style of mosaics such as those of the Cappella Palatina, Palermo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
