<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC326" n="MS 326">
                <p>CCCC MS 326 is an interesting manuscript which attests to Latin learning at the cathedral priory of
                    Christ Church, Canterbury at the end of the tenth century and the beginning of the eleventh. It
                    contains the unique text of the macaronic poem <title>Aldhelm</title>, which switches from Latin
                    (with Greek vocabulary) to Old English, phrase by phrase; but its main contents are two particularly
                    difficult Latin texts with glosses. The prose <title>De laudibus uirginitatis</title> by Aldhelm (d.
                    709), and the third book of <title>Bella Parisiacae urbis</title> by Abbo of Saint-Germain-des-Prés
                    (d. 921), were both very influential on the so-called hermeneutic style of Anglo-Latin, which arose
                    in the second half of the tenth century in association with the Benedictine Reform Movement. The
                    manuscript also contains a poem in the shape of a wheel. Provenance at Christ Church, Canterbury is
                    assured by the two surviving classmarks of that house, and the identification of this manuscript in
                    the early fourteenth-century Christ Church catalogue of Henry of Eastry OSB. An origin at the same
                    house seems certain since T. A. M. Bishop identified the scribe as one of those from his large
                    network of Canterbury manuscripts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
