<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC367" n="MS 367">
                <p>CCCC MS 367 consists of five small volumes bound together, probably because Parker wished to protect
                    a number of small items by placing them between covers. The first contains two chronicles, copied in
                    the fifteenth century, an epitome of the <title>Polychronicon</title> by Ranulf Higden OSB (d.
                    1364), and a chronicle attributed to Thomas Harpsfield. The second consists of a number of fragments
                    of Old English material, copied in the second half of the eleventh or the early twelfth century, and
                    probably to be associated with Worcester: they contain the <title>De temporibus anni</title> by
                    Ælfric of Eynsham OSB (d. 1010), and some homiletic fragments, now out of order. The third volume is
                    a thirteenth- or fourteenth-century copy of Robert Kilwardby OP (d. 1279), <title>De natura
                        relationis</title>. The fourth is a thirteenth-century copy of the <title>Apocalypsis
                        Goliae</title>, a satirical Latin poem sometimes associated with Walter Map (c. 1140-1210), but
                    best considered anonymous. The fifth contains an eleventh-century copy of the <title>Vita
                        breuior</title> of St Kenelm, with a short booklist which has been associated with Worcester,
                    and an Old English account of a vision had by Earl Leofric.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
