<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC389" n="MS 389">
                <p>CCCC MS 389 was written at St Augustine's, Canterbury in the late tenth century, and contains
                    Jerome's <title>Life of St Paul the First Hermit</title> and the <title>Life of St Guthlac</title>
                    by Felix of Crowland (eighth century). These are two very important texts for the anchoritic
                    tradition: Jerome's <title>Life of St Paul</title> provided a model both for subsequent hermits and
                    for those who wrote their <title>uitae</title>; while Guthlac was the original English hermit,
                    pursuing his vocation in the wilderness of the fens rather than in the middle-eastern desert. This
                    manuscript therefore shows an interest in the eremitical way of life at Canterbury at this time,
                    further emphasised by the marking up of the Guthlac text into nine lections to be used on his feast
                    day. It was written in late Square minuscule, the last type of Insular script to be used for Latin
                    texts in England, and contains wonderful initials of Wormald's "Type II", with interlace work and
                    grasping beast heads outlined in ink. In the second half of the eleventh century, perhaps circa
                    1070, an author portrait of St Jerome was added at the start of the manuscript in a late Anglo-Saxon
                    style. The manuscript has a St Augustine's, Canterbury classmark, but is not included in the
                    surviving catalogue.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
