<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC411" n="MS 411">
                <p>This Psalter gives interesting evidence of relations between England and the Continent in the late
                    tenth century. It has some very Franco-Saxon decoration, but seems to have been written by the
                    English scribe also responsible for <ref type="ms" target="CCC214">CCCC MS 214</ref>, and has a
                    line-drawing of a standing man (David?) in a very English style, perhaps an early addition to
                    provide a frontispiece, in one of its Franco-Saxon frames. The Franco-Saxon style of illumination
                    draws heavily on earlier Insular decoration, particularly in its use of interlace and beast heads,
                    but was developed on the Continent rather than in any part of the original Insular homelands. This
                    manuscript probably attests to Continental influence on English book-production at Christ Church,
                    Canterbury in the late tenth century, but it has alternatively been supposed that it was made
                    abroad, perhaps at Tours, and imported early into England. English additions were made to the book
                    in the eleventh century, including a second litany and the drawing of the standing man. An early
                    modern note claims that the book, once decorated with silver gilt and jewels, was owned by two
                    archbishops of Canterbury including Thomas Becket (d. 1170). Parker does not seem to have celebrated
                    the association with this saint, whose influence on English affairs he is unlikely to have
                    considered positive.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
