<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC473" n="MS 473">
                <p>This small sized book, CCCC MS 473, is commonly known as <title>The Winchester Troper</title>;
                    together with Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Bodley 775 (sometimes also called by this name) it
                    attests to the musical repertory of the Old Minster Winchester in the eleventh century. It contains
                    some of the oldest polyphonic music in the West. As well as 'tropes', musical phrases which were
                    added as embellishments to the standard chant for the liturgical texts, it also contains sequences
                    and other music. It would have been used by a precentor, whose job it was to lead the music at mass
                    and the divine office. There are many signs that it comes from the Old Minster Winchester, including
                    texts for the feasts of the Winchester saints Swithhun, Æthelwold, Justus of Beauvais, Hædde (Hedda)
                    and Birinus. Datings from the script have varied from circa 1000 to the second quarter of the
                    eleventh century; the earlier dating has led people to associate this manuscript with Wulfstan of
                    Winchester OSB (fl. late tenth century), also known as Wulfstan Cantor, who was precentor of the Old
                    Minster Winchester at around that date, and who wrote saints' lives and hagiographical poetry. A
                    later dating, perhaps 1020s-1030s, now seems probable, but it is still likely that at least some of
                    the material it contains is his work. Material was added to the manuscript serially over the course
                    of the eleventh century.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
