<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC501" n="MS 501">
                <p>This book is in an extremely fragile condition and it has not been possible for much of it to be
                    imaged, save for a few images of its cover and select pages. As a result of this fragility only the
                    exterior and interior of the front cover, the first gathering recto and verso foliated ff. a-l, and
                    the final page of the book with the explicit <hi>confessionale Johannis theotunici</hi>, foliated as
                    f. m, have been imaged. The paper is disintegrating and cannot be stabilised, so it has not even
                    been possible to foliate the manuscript throughout. . CCCC MS 501 was made in Bohemia, probably in
                    Prague, in the fifteenth century. It contains four texts on theological, devotional and penitential
                    subjects: a commentary on the <title>Sentences</title> of Peter Lombard (c. 1095-1160) by Gregory of
                    Rimini OESA (d. 1358), Pseudo-Augustine, <title>Soliloquium animae ad Deum</title>, James of Milan
                    OFM (fl. c. 1296), <title>Stimulus amoris</title>, and John of Freiburg OP (d. 1314),
                        <title>Confessionale</title>. This volume is part of the Elbing collection; a group of
                    manuscripts which belonged to a Brigittine convent at Elbing (Elblag), near Gdansk. The collection
                    was donated to Corpus Christi College by either Richard Pernham (1583?-1628) or his wife Mary, whose
                    name is in many of these books.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
