<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC503" n="MS 503">
                <p>MS 503, a miscellany, contains diverse material copied in the period c. 1390-1430 in both Germany and
                    Bohemia. The volume includes copies of Stephan of Roudnice’s expanded version of <title>Aureum
                        confessorum</title> by Willelmus Durandus the Elder (c. 1237-1296), a tract on penitence, the
                        <title>Apparatus Decretorum</title> by the canon lawyer Iohannes de Deo (c. 1190-1267), the
                    Statutes of Arnestus (Ernest), Archbishop of Prague (or Ernest of Pardubice (1297-1364),
                        <title>Inhibitiones sacramenti eucharistiae</title>, dated 1394, by Iohannes de Missa (Misna),
                    the Pseudo-Bernard of Clairvaux, <title>Speculum peccatoris</title>, Peter of Poitiers
                    (c.1130-1215), <title>Genealogia historiarum</title> (illustrated with diagrams and drawings),
                        <title>Quaestiones in De anima</title> by John Buridan (1295-1358), <title>Speculum
                        historiale</title> (extract of the <title>Historia de Joseph et Aseneth</title>) by Vincent of
                    Beauvais (d. c. 1264), a map of the Holy Land, a list of Emperors and Popes, and notes on the
                    foundation of religious houses in Gdansk and Marienburg (Malbork). This volume is part of the Elbing
                    collection; a group of manuscripts which belonged to a Brigittine convent at Elbing (Elblag), near
                    Gdansk. The collection was donated to Corpus Christi College by Richard Pernham (1583?-1628) or his
                    wife Mary, whose signature is in several of the books.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
