<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC509" n="MS 509">
                <p>CCC MS 509, made in Germany, is a miscellany combining three volumes with texts with no obvious
                    unifying theme, containing saints’ lives of Dorothy of Montau - Dorothea of Prussia (d. 1394) and
                    Gall, tracts on penance and confession and a few sermons. The first text is the long
                        <title>Septitlilium uenerabilis dominae Dorotheae</title> by Johannes Marienwerder (1343-1417),
                    canon of the Teutonic Order at the cathedral of Marienwerder (modern Kwidzyn, Poland). The
                        <title>Confessiones</title> of Dorothea of Prussia which form part of this work are in German.
                    The next part of the book includes Henricus de Odendorp (c. 1350-99), <title>Tractatus super
                        decretalem de penitenciis et remissionibus</title>. He was professor of canon law at the
                    university of Vienna, and this is a treatise on the canon of the Fourth Lateran Council stipulating
                    annual confession. The life of St Gall in the third section is by Walahfrid Strabo (d. 849). This
                    volume is part of the Elbing collection; a group of manuscripts which belonged to a Brigittine
                    convent at Elbing (Elblag), near Gdansk. The collection was donated to Corpus Christi College by
                    either Richard Pernham (1583?-1628) or his wife Mary, whose name is in many of these books.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
