<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC511" n="MS 511">
                <p>CCCC MS 511 is a late thirteenth-century collection of medical tracts and recipes which M. R. James
                    considered might have been written in England. It is among the few medical manusripts in the Parker
                    Library. The volume includes Constantinus Africanus (d. 1087) <title>Viaticum</title>, the
                        <title>Anatomia uiuorum</title> by Pseudo-Galen, Giles of Corbeil (c. 1140-1224) <title>De
                        urinis</title> with the Commentary of Gilbertus Anglicus (d. c. 1250), <title>Modus
                        medendi</title> attributed to Archimatheus Salernitanus (Matthaeus de Platea - fl. mid-twelfth
                    century), a translation by Constantinus Africanus or Gerard of Cremona (c. 1114-87) of <title>De
                        dietis uniuersalibus et particularibus</title> by Isaac Iudaeus (Ishaq Ibn Suleiman, d. c. 955),
                    an incomplete copy of John of Saint-Paul (Johannes de Sancto Paulo, fl. twelfth century or early
                    13th), <title>Breuiarium de signis morborum</title> and his <title>De simplicium medicinarum
                        uirtutibus</title>. There is also another tract entitled <title>De urinis</title> and several
                    medical recipes. Although in sequence with the collection from Elbing, there is no evidence that
                    this was part of Richard Pernham's donation, and it is not known how the book came to Corpus Christi
                    College.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
