<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC519" n="MS 519">
                <p>CCCC 519 is a Bohemian manuscript, written in the late fourteenth or early fifteenth century,
                    probably originating at Charles University in Prague. It contains a <title>Tractatus de septem
                        sacramentis</title> which has been attributed to the legal and theological scholar Nicholas
                    Wigandi of Krakow, a student of Henricus Totting of Oyta (c. 1330-97), who received his doctoral
                    degree at Prague in 1387. This text is known in only one other manuscript, Budapest, University
                    Library MS 53. The next text in the manuscript is a short tract by Matthew of Krakow (1330/35-1410)
                    with an explicit signed by the scribe 'Wenczeslay Sporiczeri de Chomuthaw'. The final text is the
                        <title>De exterioris et interioris hominis compositione</title> by David of Augsburg OFM (d.
                    1272), also in <ref type="ms" target="CCC256">CCCC MS 256</ref>. This volume is part of the Elbing
                    collection, a group of manuscripts associated with the Brigittine convent at Elbing (Elblag), near
                    Gdansk which was founded in 1458 and deserted in 1521. Almost all the Elbing manuscripts contain the
                    ownership inscription of Mary Pernham, wife of Richard Pernham (d. 1628), Fellow of the college and
                        <hi rend="italic">pastor Anglicus</hi> of St Marien church in Elbing from 1618-24. The book
                    retains its original binding with an inscription providing evidence of Elbing ownership.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
