<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC526" n="MS 526">
                <p>This book is in an extremely fragile condition and it has not been possible for it to be imaged
                    completely, save for the front and back cover exteriors, and ff. 1-211v, 250v, 251r. The binding is
                    very tight in parts of the book and for some pages there has been some loss of focus in the deep
                    gutter. CCCC MS 526 is part of the Elbing Collection brought back from the abandoned Brigittine
                    monastery at what is now Eblag in Poland by Richard Pernham in the early 1620s and donated to Corpus
                    Christi either by himself or by his wife Mary, whose name is inscribed in many books of the
                    collection. This volume is closely dated by the presence of a scribal colophon recording the year
                    1431 in one of the items (a letter by Jan van Ruusbroec), which date the rest of the manuscript must
                    more or less share. Among the many devotional and theological texts in the manuscript are Henricus
                    Suso OP (Heinrich Seuse, 1295-1366) <title>Horologium sapientiae</title> and <title>Cursus de
                        aeterna sapientia</title>, Jan van Ruusbroec's (1293-1381) <title>De Calculo</title>
                        (<title>Tractatus de perfectione filiorum Dei</title>) and <title>De ornatu spiritualium
                        nuptiarum</title>, both in the translation of Willem Jordaens, Hugo de Balma OCarth (fl.
                    1289-1304) <title>Theologia mystica</title> (<title>De triplici uia</title>), Thomas Aquinas OP (c.
                    1225-74) <title>De perfectione spiritualis uitae</title> and the <title>De uita solitaria</title> of
                    Francesco Petrarca (1304-74). The 'kochemeister' mentioned on the back cover is possibly Michael
                    Kuchmeister (fl. 1414-22) mentioned in Elbing records.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
