<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC053" n="MS 53">
                <p>CCCC MS 53 contains three separate sections, a psalter, a chronicle of England and Peterborough
                    Abbey, and finally a bestiary. It is called the Peterborough Psalter and Bestiary because the
                    Psalter was adapted for the use of of that abbey, at which time the chronicle was added. The
                    Bestiary, which has been cut down to match the page size of the Psalter, was probably added to the
                    book at some later date. The dating of the Bestiary to c. 1300-10 is earlier by a decade or so than
                    that of the Psalter which is considered to be of c. 1310-20. Both are elaborately illuminated but by
                    quite different artists. The Psalter was originally intended for a patron in the diocese of Norwich
                    as evidenced by the original calendar to which Peterborough entries were added. The original patron,
                    perhaps Oliver de Wisset, was evidently connected with John de Warenne, Earl of Surrey (d. 1304),
                    whose obit is added in the original hand of the calendar. Perhaps during the production of the book
                    the patronage was taken over by Peterborough Abbey because the calendar was adapted to their use and
                    their Litany and Office of the Dead were added to the text, as was a chronicle of the abbey. It was
                    owned by the prior, Hugh de Stukeley, whose name is at the beginning of the book. The Psalter is
                    lavishly illustrated with twenty full page pictures of the Life of Christ, saints, prophets and
                    apostles preceding the Psalter text, some fully painted with gold grounds and others in coloured
                    drawing. The Psalter itself has historiated initials at the liturgical divisions, and many
                    decorative ornamental initials and borders. The artist of the fully painted pictures belongs to a
                    group of artists called the Queen Mary Psalter group after their main work, the Psalter, London, BL
                    MS Royal 2. B. VII. The Bestiary, by a different artist, who also worked on a psalter, Oxford, Jesus
                    College MS D.40, has 101 framed illustrations set in its text.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
