<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC542" n="MS 542">
                <p>CCCC MS 542 is a tiny prayerbook which Archbishop Parker’s second son, Matthew, gave to his wife
                    Frances as a New Year’s gift at some point between their marriage in 1569 and his early death in
                    1574. It contains an acrostic on her name, as well as a number of “most necessary prayers and
                    comfortable meditations”, and the opening page has an illuminated border containing flowers like
                    those found in earlier sixteenth-century Books of Hours. Simpler gold borders are on several other
                    pages. Only the first few pages have been imaged because of the great fragility of the contemporary
                    binding, which is embroidered with pansies and chrysanthemums, in a similar style to the decoration
                    within. Frances was a renowned embroiderer, so may have made the binding herself. As a result of the
                    fragility of this binding it has only been possible to image the exterior and interior of the front
                    cover, the exterior of the back cover, and part of the text pages, ff. 1r-7v. The manuscript later
                    belonged to the Huth library, founded by Henry Huth (d. 1878) and continued by his son Alfred. It
                    was sold at auction in 1917, and was bought by Lord Queenborough (1861-1949) to give to Corpus
                    Christi College, perhaps at the instigation of the then librarian, Sir Geoffrey Butler. Frances was
                    the daughter of William Barlow, bishop of Chichester, who had assisted in Archbishop Parker’s
                    enthronement. At the time of her husband’s death Frances was pregnant with a child who did not
                    survive infancy. In 1578 she married Tobie Matthew, later Archbishop of York. She later founded York
                    Minster library with the books of her second husband, and was renowned for her views on girls’
                    education.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
