<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC079" n="MS 79">
                <p>CCCC MS 79, dating from c. 1400 and c. 1410, is the most elaborate decorated Pontifical to survive
                    from medieval England. The text contains the church services particular to bishops, and is a
                    specifically English version rather than the Durandus edition of the Pontifical widely used
                    throughout Europe at this time. Its ownership can be determined from the heraldry on some of its
                    pages, and it seems to have passed through the hands of three bishops who made additions to the text
                    and illumination. The original patron of the book seems to have been Guy de Mohun, bishop of St
                    Davids (1397-1407), and it then passes first to Richard Clifford, bishop of Worcester (1401-1407)
                    and bishop of London (1407-1421) who had further illumination done, and finally to Philip Morgan,
                    bishop of Worcester (1419-1426) and bishop of Ely (1426-1435) who added a section of text. By 1489
                    the Pontifical was at St Paul's Cathedral because on ff. 1v-2 are added the texts for the ceremony
                    held there in that year of the presentation of the papal sword and cap to Henry VII by Pope Innocent
                    VIII's nuncio. Small framed miniatures and historiated initials illustrate the various pontifical
                    offices, and many pages have elaborate gilded borders and ornamental initials. The book was probably
                    made in London because its artists in their ornament and figure style derive from the illuminators
                    who made the Litlyngton Missal (Westminster Abbey MS 37) in 1383-1384.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
