<TEI>



    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summaries</title>
                <author>
                    <hi>Multiple authors</hi>
                </author>
                <editor>
                    <hi>NJM</hi>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Corpus Christi College Cambridge</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>From typescript (MS-Word document)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">converted from wordfile document</change>
            <change when="2009-06-01" who="CF and SP">basic TEI-P5 markup added (teiLite schema)</change>
            <change when="2008-07-01" who="GDB">display/print support added (cccAbs.xsl)</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="CCC009" n="MS 9">
                <p>MS 9 is one of two volumes which together constitute 'The Cotton–Corpus Legendary'; the other is
                    London, BL MS Cotton Nero E. I. CCCC MS 9 contains saints' lives pertaining to the months of
                    October, November and December, as well as a calendar which may once have been part of a separate
                    volume. The book is important because it is part of the earliest surviving multi-volume legendary
                    from England. An earlier version of the same legendary, compiled on the Continent, was in England by
                    the late tenth century, where it was extensively used by Ælfric in writing his Old English
                        <title>Lives of Saints</title>. It is therefore a very important witness to the knowledge of the
                    saints' lives in late Anglo-Saxon England, and has implications for our understanding of the
                    interactions between vernacular and Latin literature. The manuscript contains work by known
                    Worcester scribes, including one who wrote a charter for 1058. The calendar and computistical
                    material found at the start of MS 9 include a Easter tables for the years 1032-62 and 1063-94, and
                    the manuscript was probably therefore written before 1062. It contains later additions of a
                    hagiographical nature also made at Worcester.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
