<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC102">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>102</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. C</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">The Writings of Martin Bucer and others</head>
                <head type="James">Buceri et aliorum scripta</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">315</height>
                        <width unit="mm">220</width>
                    </measureGrp>
                    <measureGrp type="James">12.9 x 8.3</measureGrp>, <extent>pp. 541 numbered</extent>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xvi</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">Flyleaf <supplied>(f. <locus>iiir</locus>)</supplied> from a handsome
                    service-book of cent. <origDate>xv</origDate> with music on red four-line stave: office of <name
                        type="person">St Stephen</name>.</p>
                <p>On p. <locus>1</locus> lined through: notes from <name type="person">Augustine</name> contra <name
                        type="person">Julianum</name>, <name type="person">Basil</name>, etc. </p>
                <p>On p. <locus>2</locus> pasted a note from <name type="person">Jo. Yong</name>, returning a book which
                    neither <q>
                        <name type="person">Sedgwickus</name>
                    </q> nor he himself has time to read.</p>
                <p>On p. <locus>3</locus> pasted a letter from <name type="author">Bucer</name>(?) to <name
                        type="person">Parker</name>(?) with reference to his meeting with <name type="person"
                        >Yong</name>. No date.</p>



                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iii + pp. 1-60 (61-68 missing) + 69-298 (299-300 missing) + 301-406 (407-408
                        missing) + 409-542 + ff. iv-v</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="5" locusEnd="60">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Public disputation held in <name type="place">Cambridge</name> between <name
                                    type="person">Martin Bucer</name> and masters <name type="person">Young</name>,
                                    <name type="person">Sedgewick</name> and <name type="person">Perne</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Disputatio publica habita <name type="place">Cantabrigiae</name> inter <name
                                    type="person">M. Bucerum</name> respondentem et magistros <name type="person"
                                    >Yungum</name>
                                <name type="person">Sedgwicum</name> et <name type="person">Pernum</name> opponentes de
                                his propositis, <q>Canonici libri decent soli abunde renatos, quae sint saluti
                                    omnia.</q>
                                <q>Nulla est in terris ecclesia, quae non erret tam in fide quam in moribus.</q>
                                <q>Ita gratis justificamur a Deo, ut ante justificationem re vera peccatum sit, iramque
                                    Dei in nos provocet, quicquid boni operis facere videamur: justificati autem bona
                                    opera facimus necessario.</q></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Huic disputationi praefixa est, <q>Epistola <name type="person">Buceri</name> ad
                                    Lectorem, data <date>3 Id. Augusti 1550</date></q></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>At top is noted</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="5">Manus <name type="person">Johannis bradford</name></rubric>
                        <ab>For these documents cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Hubert 1577"><hi rend="italic">Buceri
                                    Scripta Anglicana</hi> Conr. Hubert. Basel, 1577 p. 797 sqq.</ref>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Cooper and Cooper 1858">Cooper, <hi rend="italic">Athenae
                                    Cantabrigienses</hi> I 427</ref></ab>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="69" locusEnd="80">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Martin Bucer</name> to a certain bishop concerning the
                                doctrine of <name type="person">John Young</name> on justification</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola [<name type="author">Buceri</name> ad quendam episcopum] de dogmate <name
                                    type="person">Magistri Yunge</name> circa justificationem</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="81" locusEnd="82">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of the vice-chancellor, doctors and fellows to the visitors of <name
                                    type="place">Cambridge University</name> petitioning for permission for a
                                disputation to be held between <name type="person">Martin Bucer</name> and <name
                                    type="person">John Young</name> on the doctrine of justification</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola vice-cancellarii doctorum et reliquorum collegiorum praepositorum [ad
                                visitatores academiae] in qua petunt concilium utrum expediret permittere disputationem
                                inter <name type="person">Bucerum</name> et <name type="person">Yungum</name> de
                                justificatione habendam</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="83" locusEnd="90">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Response of <name type="person">John Young</name> in the disputation between him and
                                    <name type="person">Martin Bucer</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Disputatio inter eos habita respondente <name type="person">Magistro Yungo</name>,
                                cujus thesis erat, <q>Hominem nondum justificatum, nondum fide justificante donatum,
                                    posse facere opera bona acceptaque Deo, quae peccata non sunt, esseque in quodam
                                    medio statu inter omnino impios et plane probos</q></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>pp. <locus locusNew="88">89</locus>, <locus locusNew="89">90</locus>, <locus>90</locus>
                            blank</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="91" locusEnd="94">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Peter Martyr</name> to <name type="person">Martin
                                    Bucer</name> concerning the cause and argument of <name type="person">John
                                    Young</name>, dated at <name type="place">Oxford</name>
                                <date>31 August 1550</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Petri Martiri</name> ad <name type="person"
                                    >Bucerum</name> de causa et argumentis <name type="person">Magistri Yungi</name>,
                                data <name type="place">Oxonie</name>
                                <date>31 Augusti 1550</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Autograph</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">Printed in <ref type="bibl"
                                    target="Gorham, Gorham and Bird 1857">G. C. Gorham's <hi rend="italic">Reformation
                                        Gleanings</hi> (1857, p. 168)</ref> in English, as are all the documents there
                                published</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="95" locusEnd="102">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Peter Martyr</name> to a certain bishop concerning
                                questions of divorce and remarriage, dated <date>17 February 1542</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola [<name type="author">Martiri</name> ad quendam episcopum] ubi multis
                                argumentis contra <name type="person">Augustinum</name> probat, quod post justum
                                divortium utrisque licet altero superstite matrimonium denuo contrahere, data <date>17
                                    Februarii 1542</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="103" locusEnd="106">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Peter Martyr</name> to <name type="person">Martin
                                    Bucer</name> of the condition of <name type="place">Germany</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola [<name type="author">Martiri</name>] ad <name type="person">Bucerum</name>
                                de statu <name type="place">Germaniae</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Gorham, Gorham and Bird 1857">Gorham, p. 97</ref>
                            </supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="107" locusEnd="110">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Peter Martyr</name> to <name type="person">Martin
                                    Bucer</name> consoling him for the illness and other adversities which have been
                                afflicting him, dated at <name type="place">Oxford</name>
                                <date>18 December</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Martiri</name> ad <name type="person">Bucerum</name>
                                consolatoria de morbis et aliis adversis quae <name type="person">Bucero</name>
                                acciderant, data <name type="place">Oxonie</name>
                                <date>18 Decembris</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Autograph</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Gorham, Gorham and Bird 1857">Gorham, p. 123</ref>
                            </supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="111" locusEnd="150">


                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Christopher Carlile</name>, <title>A treatise concerning
                                the immediate going to heaven of the souls of the faithful fathers before Christ, and
                                that Christ did not descend into hell</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A treatise concerning the immediate going to heaven of the souls of the faithful
                                fathers before Christ, and that Christ did not descend into hell, written by <name
                                    type="author">Christopher Carlile</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>
                                <q>Hic tractatus editus per ... <name type="author">Carlil</name>, olim per eum in
                                    comitiis <name type="place">Cantabrigiae</name> defensus sed reprobatus.</q>
                            </quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>
                                <q>Memorandum, this booke exhibited and delivered <date>the xx daye of August
                                        1563</date> to the most reverend father in God, the lorde <name type="person"
                                        >Matthu archbishopp of Cant.</name> by me the within written <name type="person"
                                        >Thomas Tailor</name>, whiche was delyvered unto me the said Thomas by <name
                                        type="author">Mr. Carlel</name> of <name type="place">Horton</name> in the
                                    countie of <name type="place">Kente</name>. The doctrine whereof I neither allowe
                                    nor approve, nor intende by Gods grace to teache or publishe the same either
                                    privatly or openlye. To the testification whereof I have subscribed my name with my
                                    own hand the daye and yere first above written.<lb/> By me <name type="person"
                                        >Thomas Tayler</name></q>
                            </quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>Printed <ref type="bibl" target="Carlile 1582">London 1582</ref>. <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Cooper and Cooper 1861">Cooper, <hi rend="italic">Athenae Cantabrigienses</hi>
                                II 34</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="151" locusEnd="246">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Collected wriings from patristic writers on the sacraments in diverse hands, with a
                                vernacular tract on the same matter</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Collectanea ex patribus de re sacramentaria, diversis manibus scripta, inter quae
                                inseritur tractatus vernacula lingua de eodem proposito</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The tract in English occupies pp. <locus>195</locus>-<locus>204</locus> and begins</ab>
                        <incipit locus="195">fforasmuche as the high misteries of Christes bodie and bludd</incipit>
                        <ab>pp. <locus>205</locus>-<locus>207</locus>
                            <handNote>in another hand</handNote>, in Latin</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="205">Eucharistie vel cene dominice legitima administratio</incipit>
                        <ab>pp. <locus>213</locus>-<locus>245</locus> are <handNote>in a small good hand, perhaps <name
                                    type="person">Peter Martyr</name>'s</handNote></ab>
                        <ab>On p. <locus>246</locus> otherwise blank, in red:<lb/> Nosse deum radix immortalitatis<lb/>
                            Alexander atrebatensis i.e. <name type="person">Petrus Alexander</name> (see <ref type="ms"
                                target="CCC115">MS 115</ref>).</ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="247" locusEnd="252">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Disputation between <name type="person">Dr Stokes</name> of <name type="place"
                                    >Lynn</name> and <name type="person">Mr. Saunderson, preacher of Lynn</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Conference had the <date>28th of June</date> between <name type="person">doctor
                                    Stokes</name> of <name type="place">Lenne</name> and <name type="person">Mr.
                                    Saunderson Master of Arts and preacher of Lenne</name> uppon occasion offerid in the
                                pulpit by Mr. Saunderson the <date>24th of June</date> in the presence of <name
                                    type="person">John Bacster</name> and <name type="person">Richard Mason</name>,
                                Scole-masters of <name type="place">Lenne</name> [upon the sacrament,]</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Cooper and Cooper 1861">Cooper, <hi rend="italic">Athenae
                                    Cantabrigienses</hi> II 79</ref>. Not printed</ab>
                        <ab>p. <locus>249</locus> has passages from the Fathers on the Eucharist</ab>
                        <ab>pp. <locus>250</locus>-<locus>252</locus> blank</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="253" locusEnd="258">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Minutes of a debate held on <date>23 November 1551</date> in the chamber of <name
                                    type="person">Lord Cecil</name> the king's secretary, on the sacraments</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Summa collocutionis habitae <date>25 Novembris 1551</date> in aedibus <name
                                    type="person">D. Cicelli</name> secretarii regii de re sacramentaria</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Presentes, <name type="person">D. Russel</name>, <name type="person">D.
                                Hayles</name>, <name type="person">D. Wroth</name>, <name type="person">D. Ant.
                                    Coke</name>, <name type="person">Mr. Trogmartin</name>, <name type="person">Mr.
                                    Knolles</name>, <name type="person">Mr. Harrington</name><lb/> Colloquutores, <name
                                    type="person">D. Cicellus</name>, <name type="person">D. Checus</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Mr. Horne decanus Dunelmensis</name>, <name type="person">Mr.
                                    Whitehead</name> et <name type="person">Mr. Gryndall</name>, <name type="person">Mr.
                                    Fecknam</name> et <name type="person">Mr. Yonge</name></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694">Strype, <hi rend="italic">Cranmer</hi> I
                            385</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="259" locusEnd="270">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Minutes of a debate on the sacraments held on <date>3 December 1551</date> in the
                                chamber of <name type="person">Sir Richard Morrison</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Alia collocutio de eadem re habita <date>3 Decembris 1551</date>, in aedibus <name
                                    type="person">D. Morisini</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Presentes, <name type="person">D. Marchio Northampton</name>, <name type="person">D.
                                    Comes Rutland</name>, <name type="person">D. Russel</name> et prius nominati cum
                                    <name type="person">Magistro Watson</name></quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694">Strype, <hi rend="italic">Cranmer</hi> I
                            385</ref></ab>
                        <ab>pp. <locus>267</locus>-<locus>270</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="271" locusEnd="276">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Thoughts of <name type="author">Luther</name> on the sacrament</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Cogitationes <name type="author">Lutheri</name> de sacramento</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>
                                <handNote>scriptae manu propria</handNote>
                            </quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>The autograph is preceded by a copy on one leaf. It begins</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="271">Cogitationes mee sunt</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="271">Primo ut nullo modo concedamus</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">Last in <ref type="bibl" target="Enders 1903">Enders' <hi
                                        rend="italic">Luther's Briefwechsel</hi> X 92</ref>: to be reprinted from the
                                MS. in <ref type="bibl" target="Knaake 1883">the Weimar edition</ref>. <ref type="bibl"
                                    target="Pocock 1865f">Burnet, <hi rend="italic">Hist. Ref</hi>., ed. Pocock VI
                                    279</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="277" locusEnd="280">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Oswald Myconius</name> on the origin of the
                                disagreement with <name type="person">Luther</name> on the eucharist</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Miconii</name> de dissensione cum <name type="person"
                                    >Luthero</name> orta circa eucharistiam</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="16" locusStart="281" locusEnd="286">


                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">John Calvin</name>, <title>Consensus
                            Tigurinus</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Formula confessionis de eucharistia inter fratres Tigurinos et ...</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The title seems to be</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="281">formula Confessionis de eucharistia inter fratres Tigurinos et Geuenates
                            (or Geneuates)</rubric>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="17" locusStart="287" locusEnd="288">


                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Wolfgang Musculus</name>, <title>De sacramento corporis et
                                sanguinis Domini</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De sacramento corporis et sanguinis Domini, <name type="author">W. Musculi</name>
                                explicatio</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Gorham, Gorham and Bird 1857">Gorham, p. 108</ref>
                            </supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="18" locusStart="289" locusEnd="296">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Answer of <name type="author">Martin Bucer</name> to <name type="person">John
                                    Calvin</name> on the Consensus Tigurinus</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Responsio <name type="author">Martini Buceri</name> ad <name type="person"
                                    >Calvinum</name> de forma concordiae cum Tigurinis</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <handNote>In two hands</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda"><ref type="bibl" target="Gorham, Gorham and Bird 1857"
                                    >Gorham, p. 99</ref>. <ref type="bibl" target="Baum, Cunitz and Reuss 1863">Calvin,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Opp</hi>. ed. Baum etc. no. 1240</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="19" locusStart="297" locusEnd="302">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">John Calvin</name> to <name type="person">Martin
                                    Bucer</name> congratulating him on his arrival in <name type="place">England</name>
                                and describing the Consensus Tigurinus</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Calvini</name> ad <name type="person">Bucerum</name>:
                                gratulatur ei de felice ejus in <name type="place">Angliam</name> adventu. Multa narrat
                                de rebus suis et amicorum, et mittit exemplar formulae praedictae</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>? Autograph</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="297">Litere tue mihi serius reddite fuerunt</incipit>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda"><ref type="bibl" target="Gorham, Gorham and Bird 1857"
                                    >Gorham, p. 92</ref>. <ref type="bibl" target="Baum, Cunitz and Reuss 1863">Calvin,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Opp</hi>. ed. Baum etc. no. 4154</ref></supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="20" locusStart="303" locusEnd="306">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter to the <name type="place">college of Strassburg</name> concerning certain
                                things to be reformed</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola ... [ad collegium <name type="place">Argentinense</name>] de quibusdam in
                                statutis emendandis</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="21" locusStart="307" locusEnd="312">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Sermons of the errors of the Roman Church</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Sermo in errores ecclesiae Romanae</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="22" locusStart="313" locusEnd="316">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Excerpts from scholastic authors on original sin</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Excerpta ex autoribus scholasticis de peccato originali</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="23" locusStart="317" locusEnd="320">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Excerpts from patristic authors on the eucharist</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Quod mali non edunt corpus Domini, ex patribus</title>
                        </head>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="24" locusStart="321" locusEnd="322">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">John Cheke</name>, <title>De ueritate corporis et sanguinis
                                Domini in eucharistia ex patribus</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De veritate corporis et sanguinis Domini in eucharistia ex patribus, a domino <name
                                    type="author">Ioanne Cheke</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>propria manu</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>
                                <q>Haec est sanctorum patrum <name type="person">Hilarii</name>, <name type="person"
                                        >Chrisostomi</name>, <name type="person">Augustini</name>, <name type="person"
                                        >Cyrilli</name> de veritate corporis et sanguinis Domini in eucharistia
                                    sententia, in qua me quoque esse profiteor, non modo quia propter authoritatem
                                    doctrinae et vitae sanctitatem digni sunt quos sequamur, sed quia catholicae Christi
                                    ecclesiae eadem sit sententia: itaque in hac causa et in reliquis omnibus idem me
                                    profiteor dicere et sentire quod sancta Christi et catholica tenet ecclesia</q>
                            </quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1705">Strype, Cheke, pp. 111, 112</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="25" locusStart="323" locusEnd="323">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">John Cheke</name> to <name type="person">Cardinal
                                    Pole</name> praying to be received back into the church, dated at the <name
                                    type="place">tower of London</name>
                                <date>15 July 1556</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Ioannis Cheke</name> [ad <name type="person">cardinalem
                                    Polum</name>] orans ut sibi in gremium ecclesiae jam reduci sit benignus, data ex
                                    <name type="place">Turri Londinensi</name>
                                <date>15 Julii 1556</date></title>
                        </head>


                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1705">Strype, Cheke, pp. 111, 112</ref>. Printed by <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Goodwin 1843">J. Goodwin, <hi rend="italic">Appendix to Cheke's
                                    Gospel of St Matthew</hi> 1843</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="26" locusStart="324" locusEnd="324">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">John Cheke</name> to <name type="person">Mary I</name>
                                petitioning for his liberty, dated at the <name type="place">tower of London</name>
                                <date>15 July 1556</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same to the queen petitioning for his liberty, dated from the <name
                                    type="place">Tower</name>
                                <date>July 15, 1556</date></title>
                        </head>


                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1705">Strype, Cheke, pp. 111, 112</ref>. Printed by <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Goodwin 1843">J. Goodwin, <hi rend="italic">Appendix to Cheke's
                                    Gospel of St Matthew</hi> 1843</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="27" locusStart="325" locusEnd="336">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Dialogue between the king and his people</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Cox 1846">Parker Society, Cranmer II 163</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="28" locusStart="337" locusEnd="408">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Thomas Cranmer</name>, <title>An answer to the articles of
                                the Devonshire men</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>An answer to the articles of the Devonshire men, by <name type="person">archbishop
                                    Cranmer</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Original</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>These articles were published by the Devonshire men in their insurrection
                                    <date>1549</date>: to which event the preceding dialogue also relates, in which the
                                king is introduced expostulating with his subjects, and upbraiding them with their
                                ingratitude for the many blessings they enjoyed under his reign</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Cox 1846">Parker Society, Cranmer II 163</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="29" locusStart="409" locusEnd="482">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>A sermon concerning the time of rebellion translated from the Latin of <name
                                    type="person">Peter Martyr</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A sermon concernynge the tyme of rebellion translated from the Latin of <name
                                    type="person">Peter Martyr</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Cox 1846">Parker Society, Cranmer II 190</ref>. See <ref
                                type="ms" target="CCC340">MS 340. 4</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="30" locusStart="483" locusEnd="508">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A prayer to be used in times of tumult and sedition</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>Another copy occurs on p. <locus>525</locus></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Both copies appear to have been written by <name type="person">Cranmer</name></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>pp. <locus>500</locus>-<locus>508</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="31" locusStart="509" locusEnd="512">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The thoughts of <name type="author">Peter Martyr</name> against sedition</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Cogitationes <name type="author">Petri Martyris</name> contra seditionem</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Autograph</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="32" locusStart="513" locusEnd="528">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The thoughts of <name type="author">Martin Bucer</name> against sedition</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Cogitationes <name type="author">Martini Buceri</name> de eadem re</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Autograph</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="33" locusStart="529" locusEnd="529">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Thomas Cranmer</name>, <title>Texts of scripture against
                                sedition</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Texts of scripture against sedition</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Autograph</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Cox 1846">Parker Society, Cranmer II 188</ref>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="34" locusStart="530" locusEnd="534">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Heads of a discourse against rebellion</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="35" locusStart="535" locusEnd="538">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Excerpts from holy Scripture concerning war</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Ex sacris scripturis de bello, &amp;c.</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="36" locusStart="539" locusEnd="542">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Why is it never licit to take up arms against the magistrate</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Quod nulla causa licet subditis arma sumere contra magistratum</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: 18.11.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
