<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC104">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>104</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. D</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">The Writings of Martin Bucer, Pierre Alexandre and others</head>
                <head type="James">M. Buceri, Petri Alexandri et aliorum scripta</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">315</height>
                        <width unit="mm">215</width>
                    </measureGrp>
                    <measureGrp type="James">12 x 8.5</measureGrp>, <extent>pp. 595</extent>, Cent.
                        <origDate>xvi</origDate>, <handNote>many hands</handNote>. </p>
                <p function="Additions">Flyleaf from the same service-book as in <ref type="ms" target="CCC102">MS
                        102</ref>, pasted over. <supplied>(ff. <locus>iiir</locus>-<locus>iiiv</locus>)</supplied></p>
                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iv + pp. 1-36 + 36a-37a + 37-40 + 40a-41a + 41-96 + 96a-97a + 97-274 (275-276
                        missing) + 277-596 + ff. v-vi</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1" locusEnd="144">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Martin Bucer</name>, <title>Commentary on the gospel of St
                                Matthew</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Annotationes <name type="author">Martini Buceri</name> in octo priora capita
                                evangelii secundum <name type="person">Matthaeum</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Partly autograph: has some titles etc. written by <name type="person">Cranmer</name>. <lb/>
                            A comment by <name type="author">Bucer</name> on the Gospels was printed by <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bucer 1530">Stephanus in 1530</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="Bucer 1536"
                                >1536</ref> etc.: but it differs from this</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="145" locusEnd="196">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">John Cheke</name>, <title>English translation of St Matthew's
                                gospel</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Translation of the gospell of <name type="person">St. Matthew</name> and part of the
                                first chapter of <name type="person">St. Mark</name> into English by <name type="person"
                                    >sir John Cheek</name> with marginal notes</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Printed by <ref type="bibl" target="Goodwin 1843">Goodwin 1843</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="197" locusEnd="238">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Pierre Alexandre</name>, <title>Commentary on the gospel of
                                St Mark</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Annotationes <name type="author">Petri Alexandri</name> in quinque priora capita
                                evangelii secundum <name type="person">Marcum</name> una cum versione Latina</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Title by <name type="person">Cranmer</name> (?)</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="239" locusEnd="240">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Matthew Parker</name>, <title>Notes on the governance of
                                the churches in <name type="place">France</name> and <name type="place"
                                >Belgium</name></title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Breves notae de regulis ecclesiae Gallicanae, et Belgicae prescribendis a <name
                                    type="author">Matthaeo Parkero</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Printed <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, Parker, Appendix 8</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="241" locusEnd="272">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Thomas Cranmer</name>, <title>Annotations to 'institutions
                                of a Christian man'</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Annotations upon the kings book [by <name type="author">archbishop
                                Cranmer</name>]</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>By the king's book is meant, the <hi rend="italic">Erudition of a Christian man</hi>
                                published by <name type="person">Henry VIII</name></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Cox 1846">Parker Society, Cranmer II 83</ref>. <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Strype 1694">Strype, Cranmer I 137</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="273" locusEnd="298">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Edmund Gheast</name>, <title>A sermon on Mark 1. 15,
                                'Repent and believe the gospel'</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A sermon on Mark 1. 15, 'Repent and believe the gospel' by <name type="author">Gheast
                                    bishop of Rochester</name>, preached [probably at court] <date>1560</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Dugdale 1840">H. G. Dugdale's <hi rend="italic">Life of
                                    Bishop Gheast</hi> 1840, Appendix VII</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="299" locusEnd="309">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Thomas Cranmer</name>, <title>Of the consolation of
                                christian men against the fear of death taken from the fathers</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Of the consolation of christian men against the fear of death taken from the fathers,
                                by <name type="author">archbishop Cranmer</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Autograph. See <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694">Strype, Cranmer, Appendix
                            XXXII</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="310" locusEnd="313">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Thomas Cranmer</name>, <title>An exhortation to take
                                sickness well and adversity patiently, drawn out of <name type="person"
                                >Ciprian</name></title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>An exhortation to take sickness well and adversity patiently, drawn out of <name
                                    type="person">Ciprian</name>, by the same</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Autograph. See <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694">Strype, Cranmer, Appendix
                            XXXII</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="314" locusEnd="318">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Thomas Cranmer</name>, <title>An exhortation to take the
                                paynes of sickness patiently, translated out of <name type="person">Augustin</name>
                                liber I, 'de visitatione infirmorum'</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>An exhortation to take the paynes of sickness patiently, translated out of <name
                                    type="person">Augustin</name> liber I, 'de visitatione infirmorum' by the
                                same</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Autograph. See <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694">Strype, Cranmer, Appendix
                            XXXII</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="319" locusEnd="338">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Nicholas Robinson</name>, <title>A sermon on the character
                                of <name type="person">Cain</name></title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A sermon of <name type="author">M. Robinson</name> on the character of <name
                                    type="person">Cain</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><name type="person">Nicholas Robinson Bishop of Bangor</name>: extract in <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Strype 1711">Strype, Parker I 465</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="339" locusEnd="360">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Hugh Latimer</name>, <title>Homily delivered before King
                                    <name type="person">Edward V</name> on the qualities to be displayed by a
                                king</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Homelia quaedam <name type="author">Hugonis Latymeri</name> habita coram <name
                                    type="person">rege Edwardo</name>, in qua qualis rex esse debeat ostenditur, Latine
                                versa per <name type="person">Magistrum Banks</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>This is the first of <name type="author">Latimer</name>'s sermons before the king. <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Corrie 1844">Parker Society, <hi rend="italic">Sermons of
                                    Latimer</hi>, p. 85</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="361" locusEnd="380">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="person">Urbanus Rhegius</name>, <title>Whether a heretical
                                magistrate is to be obeyed translated by <name type="person">Jacobus Gislenus
                                    Thalassius</name></title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Num in hereticos jure magistratuum gravius animadvertere liceat, decisio <name
                                    type="author">Urbani Rhegii</name>, interprete <name type="person">Jacobo Gisleno
                                    Thalassio</name>, <date>1539</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <handNote><supplied>Articles</supplied> 12-15 are in one hand: a curious upright script. It
                                recurs in <ref type="ms" target="CCC109">MS 109, article 12</ref></handNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Rhegius 1562"><name type="author">Urbanus Regius</name>' works were
                                printed in <date>1562</date> at <name type="place">Nuremberg</name></ref>
                        </ab>

                        <incipit locusNew="363">Quom ex sententia pauli manifestum sit</incipit>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="381" locusEnd="528">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Urbanus Rhegius (attrib.)</name>, <title>De conciliis et
                                ecclesiis</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Ejusdem autoris de conciliis et ecclesiis tractatus</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <handNote><supplied>Articles</supplied> 12-15 are in one hand: a curious upright script. It
                                recurs in <ref type="ms" target="CCC109">MS 109, article 12</ref></handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Rhegius 1562"><name type="author">Urbanus Regius</name>' works were
                                printed in <date>1562</date> at <name type="place">Nuremberg</name></ref>
                        </ab>

                        <incipit locusNew="381">Non sine cachinno vidi saepius adolescens cani famelico panem ostentari
                            sed eius loco verbera fuisse exhibita</incipit>
                        <ab>Marginalia by <name type="person">Cranmer</name></ab>
                        <ab>Ends p. <locus>518</locus></ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>519</locus>-<locus>528</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="529" locusEnd="564">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>History of the Hussites</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Historia Hussica liber iii, incerto autore</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <quote>Doctrinae reformatae se maxime infensum ostendit, et <name type="person"
                                    >Hussum</name> juste fuisse crematum asserit: Stylum et mentem hujus autoris satis
                                cognoscet lector ex sequenti sententia quam ex sermone <name type="person">episcopi
                                    Laudensis</name> cum laude citat. <q>Hi duo <name type="person">Huss</name> et <name
                                        type="person">Hieronimus</name> patriae pestes fuerunt... quorum matres si
                                    unquam peccaverunt, certe nullum flagitium gravius committere potuerunt quam quod
                                    ubera talibus labiis sugenda prebuere.</q> Non recte adscribitur haec historia <name
                                    type="person">Urbano Rhegio</name> a <name type="person">Cl. Stanley</name></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <handNote><supplied>Articles</supplied> 12-15 are in one hand: a curious upright script. It
                                recurs in <ref type="ms" target="CCC109">MS 109, article 12</ref></handNote>
                        </ab>

                        <incipit locusNew="529">Paulo ante tempora <name type="person">Ioannis husz</name> regnauit in
                                <name type="place">bohemia</name>
                            <name type="person">carolus quartus</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="564">nec ipsi bohemi de hussii sanctitate multum gloriantur, quandoquidem
                            rem ipsam iuxta mecum intelligunt</explicit>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="565" locusEnd="596">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Sermon of consolation to the Germans</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Sermo consolationis ad Germanos</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <handNote><supplied>Articles</supplied> 12-15 are in one hand: a curious upright script. It
                                recurs in <ref type="ms" target="CCC109">MS 109, article 12</ref></handNote>
                        </ab>

                        <incipit locusNew="565">Vulgo iactatum est prouerbium. difficulter nolenti subuenitur. Audiuimus
                            germani multis iam annis dulce illud et saluberrimum verbum dei</incipit>
                        <ab>Much against the <name type="person">Electors of Mainz and Brandenburg</name></ab>
                        <ab>Ends p. <locus>592</locus></ab>

                        <ab>On p. <locus>595</locus> is written <handNote>in the same hand</handNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="595"><q>forma orandi deum aduersus turcam. M : Lut :</q> (<name type="person"
                                >Lutheri</name>)</ab>
                        <ab>and below</ab>
                        <ab locus="595"><q>la : g : tha : inter : <date>1542</date></q> (i.e. <name type="person">Jacobo
                                Gisleno Thalassio</name> interprete)</ab>

                    </msItem>


                </msContents>



                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF, BA, CF 2nd</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 18.11.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
