<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC114B">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>114B</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. I</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Matthew Parker's Correspondence, Volume 2</head>
                <head type="James">Parker's Correspondence</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">312</height>
                        <width unit="mm">218</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">12.5 x 8.5</measureGrp>, <extent>pp. 966 numbered</extent>.
                    Bound in two volumes.<lb/> 114A, containing nos. 1-176, pp. 1-498.<lb/>114B, containing nos.
                    177-342, pp. 499-966.</p>

                <p rend="afterContents">N. B. All the letters in this volume, except where mention is made of the
                    contrary, were written to <name type="person">Dr. Parker</name> after his promotion to the see of
                    Canterbury.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-ii + pp. 499-672 + 672a-673a + 673-686 (687-688 missing) + 689-692 (693-694
                        missing) + 695-708 + 708a-709a + 709-830 (831-840 missing / transposed) + 841-844 + 844a-t +
                        845-852 + 855-858 + 853-854 + 859-928 (929-930 missing) + 931-966 + ff. iii-iv</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="eng" otherLangs="lat gre">English, Latin and Greek.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="177" locusStart="499" locusEnd="500">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Nicholas Robinson</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Robinson bishop of Bangor</name>, desiring the
                                archbishop to confirm a lease he had granted of the parsonage of <name type="place"
                                    >Witney</name>, dated <name type="place">Bangor</name>
                                <date>12 June, 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>500</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="178" locusStart="501" locusEnd="502">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Rowland Merrick</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Merick bishop of Bangor</name>, that he had sent the
                                archbishop a book with the names, &amp;c. of every beneficed person within his
                                diocese, dated <name type="place">Bangor</name>
                                <date>7 May, 1561</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, Parker I p. 508 ch. XVIII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>502</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="179" locusStart="503" locusEnd="504">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Nicholas Robinson</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Robinson bishop of Bangor</name>, that he had sent
                                the archbishop a copy of part of <name type="person">Eadmerus</name>' history, and hoped
                                shortly to have the remaining part transcribed for him: he also acquaints his grace that
                                there are no faithful monuments of antiquity to be found in <name type="place"
                                    >Wales</name>, and desires him to recommend the son of <name type="person">Mr.
                                    Fletcher</name> his principal register to <name type="place">All-Soul's college
                                    Oxford</name>, dated <name type="place">Bangor</name>
                                <date>7 October 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, Parker I p. 509 ch. XVIII</ref>. See <ref
                                type="ms" target="CCC341">MS 341</ref></ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>504</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="180" locusStart="505" locusEnd="505">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Cheney</name> to <name type="person">William
                                    Cecil</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">R. Cheney</name> to <name type="person">Mr. secretary
                                    Cecill</name>; óhe desires that more preachers might be sent abroad, and complains
                                of the queen's takers [purveyors] who had seized a quarter of his wheat; and gives an
                                account of a dispute about the pronunciation of Greek, concerning which he tells a
                                pleasant story, dated <name type="place">Halford</name> in <name type="place"
                                    >Warwickshire</name>
                                <date>April 16, 1561</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Correspondence</hi> XCVIII note</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="181" locusStart="506" locusEnd="506">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Cecil</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">secretary Cecill</name>, recommending <name
                                    type="person">Dr. Cheney</name> to the archbishop</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence XCVIII</ref>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="182" locusStart="506" locusEnd="506">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Cheney</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Cheney bishop of Gloucester</name>, recommending the
                                son of <name type="person">sir John Baskerville</name>, dated <name type="place"
                                    >Gloucester</name>
                                <date>3 February</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="183" locusStart="507" locusEnd="508">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>What rents profits and commodities every bishop of <name type="place"
                                    >Gloucester</name> have received</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="184" locusStart="509" locusEnd="510">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Declaration of <name type="person">Anthony Kitchin</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A writing signed by <name type="person">Kitchin bishop of Landaff</name>, in which he
                                promises to maintain the established religion, and to tender the oath of supremacy to
                                all persons receiving office ecclesiastical or temporal within his diocese, which oath
                                the queen had allowed him longer time to consider of, before he should be required to
                                take it, dated <date>18 July, I Elizabethae</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>510</locus> sender</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="185" locusStart="511" locusEnd="512">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Hugh Curwen</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Curwin bishop of Oxford</name>, thanking the
                                archbishop for giving up his option, dated <name type="place">Bainton</name>
                                <date>22 November 1567</date></title>


                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>512</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="186" locusStart="513" locusEnd="514">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Hugh Jones</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Jones bishop of Landaff</name>, requesting that he
                                may be permitted to appear by proxy in convocation and parliament, dated <name
                                    type="place">Matharne</name>
                                <date>20 September 1566</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>514</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="187" locusStart="515" locusEnd="516">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Davies</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Davies bishop of St. Asaph</name>, excusing his not
                                coming to town about his translation on account of his bad health, dated <name
                                    type="place">Wryxham</name>
                                <date>18 April 1561</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence XCVII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>516</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="188" locusStart="517" locusEnd="518">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Davies</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">T. Davies bishop of St. Asaph's</name>, desiring to
                                have a dispensation to hold the rectories of <name type="place">Eston</name> and <name
                                    type="place">Crome</name> in commendam, dated <name type="place">St. Asaph's</name>
                                <date>ultima Augusti 1566</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="189" locusStart="519" locusEnd="520">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">James Pilkington</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Pilkington bishop of Durham</name>, recommending
                                    <name type="person">George Hargreves</name> and <name type="person">Wight of St.
                                    John's</name>, as proper persons either of them to have the vicarage of <name
                                    type="place">Rachedale</name>, and complaining of many things in the diocese which
                                wanted reformation</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLXVIII</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="190" locusStart="520" locusEnd="522">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">James Pilkington</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, recommending a person to the archbishop, dated <name
                                    type="place">Awklam</name>
                                <date>23 August 1563</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>521</locus> blank</supplied>

                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>522</locus> address</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="191" locusStart="523" locusEnd="524">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Downham</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Downham bishop-elect of Chester</name>, desiring the
                                archbishop to grant his chaplain <name type="person">William Pascho</name> a
                                dispensation to hold two livings, dated from the court <date>2 May, 1561</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>524</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="192" locusStart="525" locusEnd="526">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Downham</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, desiring the archbishop to grant a dispensation to <name
                                    type="person">Ralf Vincent</name> to hold the rectory of <name type="place"
                                    >Smeton</name>, tho' not in orders, dated <name type="place">Chester</name>
                                <date>26 March, 1565</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>526</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="193" locusStart="527" locusEnd="528">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Best</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Best bishop of Carlisle</name>, desiring the
                                archbishop to renew his dispensation for holding <name type="place">Rumald church</name>
                                in commendam, dated <date>April 9, 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, Parker I p. 509 ch. XVIII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>528</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="194" locusStart="529" locusEnd="529">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Edmund Grindal</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Grindall bishop of London</name>, desiring the
                                archbishop to grant a licence for non-residence to <name type="person">Thomas
                                    Walker</name> parson of <name type="place">Shadwell</name> in <name type="place"
                                    >Essex</name>, dated <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>23 February 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Nicholson 1843">Parker Society, Grindall, no. XLVII</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="195" locusStart="530" locusEnd="530">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Edmund Grindal</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, requesting the same favour for <name type="person">John
                                    Woolton</name>, dated <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>2 July, 1568</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Nicholson 1843">Parker Society, Grindall, no. L</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="196" locusStart="531" locusEnd="532">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Dispensation granted to <name type="person">W. Martin</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Dispensatio concessa <name type="person">W. Martin</name> ad tenendam rectoriam de
                                    <name type="place">Shilbrooke</name> in diocesi <name type="place">Exon.</name> per
                                quinquennium <date>i Decembris 1564</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>532</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="197" locusStart="533" locusEnd="536">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Dispensation granted to <name type="person">Thomas Williams</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Dispensatio concessa <name type="person">Thomas Williams</name> notho ad beneficia
                                ecclesiastica de <name type="place">Lan Edy</name> et <name type="place">Llan
                                    Lowghin</name> retinenda vel quaevis alia accipienda <date>21 Septembris
                                1561</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>536</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="198" locusStart="537" locusEnd="346">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Foxe</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae <name type="author">Ioannis Foxii</name>, ut concedatur ei quadragesimalis
                                vescendi licentia, data <name type="place">Londini</name>
                                <date>7 Februarii</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLXXII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>538</locus> - <locus>546</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="199" locusStart="547" locusEnd="548">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Cecil</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Mr. secretary Cecill</name>, that it is her majesties
                                pleasure, that the archbishop should grant a dispensation to the scholars of <name
                                    type="place">Winchester</name> touching the observation of Wednesday as a fish-day,
                                dated <name type="place">Westminster</name>
                                <date>March 14, 1564</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLXXVII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>548</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="200" locusStart="549" locusEnd="550">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Dispensation granted to <name type="place">Cambridge University</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Talis dispensatio concessa academiae <name type="place">Cantabrigiensi</name></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="201" locusStart="550" locusEnd="551">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Confirmation of dispensation granted to <name type="place">Cambridge
                                    University</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Confirmatio ejusdem per reginam</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="202" locusStart="552" locusEnd="552">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of thanks to <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name> for dispensation
                                granted to <name type="place">Cambridge University</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Literae academiae, in quibus gratias agunt academici pro dispensatione sibi concessa,
                                datae <date>11 kalendas Decembris 1564</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence p. 235 note</ref>,
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype Appendix 32</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="203" locusStart="553" locusEnd="553">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Downham</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Downham bishop of Chester</name>, recommending the
                                son of <name type="person">sir Thomas Gerrard</name> of Lancashire to the archbishop for
                                a dispensation to hold a living, dated <name type="place">Chester</name>
                                <date>4 October 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="204" locusStart="554" locusEnd="554">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Alley</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Alley bishop of Exeter</name>, desiring the
                                archbishop to grant a like dispensation for four years to <name type="person">William
                                    Germyn</name> a scholar of <name type="place">Oxford</name>, dated <name
                                    type="place">Exeter</name>
                                <date>9 April 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="205" locusStart="555" locusEnd="556">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Parkhurst</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Parkhurst bishop of Norwich</name> that he had
                                received the archbishop's commission to proceed upon the articles exhibited by the
                                parson of <name type="place">Heningham</name> and his parishioners; ó that several
                                persons in his diocese who had taken dispensations from the faculties for orders had
                                altered the words non suffraganei to vel suffraganei particularly one <name
                                    type="person">Simpson</name> of <name type="place">Norwich</name>; ó that <name
                                    type="person">Tredar</name> late vicar of <name type="place">Wesenham</name> wanted
                                to resume a benefice which he had resigned by proxy, and which he [the bishop] had
                                conferred on <name type="person">Kindersley</name> of <name type="place">Norwich</name>,
                                he therefore prays that the proxy then in the hands of an officer of the arches may be
                                sent down to him: dated <name type="place">Norwich</name>
                                <date>29 January 1568</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="206" locusStart="557" locusEnd="559">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Dispensation granted to <name type="person">Gilbert Berkeley</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Dispensatio concessa <name type="person">Gilberto Barkely episcopo Bathon. et
                                    Wellen.</name> ad tenend. beneficium ecclesiasticum in commendam</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="207" locusStart="560" locusEnd="560">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Certificatio medici quod <name type="person">Ioannis Martin</name> propter infirmam
                                suam valetudinem piscibus vesci non possit</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="208" locusStart="561" locusEnd="566">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Dispensation granted to <name type="person">William Simpson</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Dispensatio concessa <name type="person">Willelmo Simpson</name> ad sacros ordines
                                suscipiendas</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>562</locus> - <locus>566</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="209" locusStart="567" locusEnd="568">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Spottiswoode</name>, <name type="author">John
                                    Knox</name> and <name type="author">John Craig</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name> and <name type="person">Thomas Young</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Mr. John Spottiswood</name> superintendant of the
                                Lowthean, <name type="author">Mr. John Knox</name> and <name type="author">Mr. John
                                    Craig</name> ministers of Edinburgh to the archbishops of Canterbury and York,
                                desiring them to publish a citation in their respective provinces for <name
                                    type="person">Anne Gordane</name> to appear before the session of <name type="place"
                                    >Edinburgh</name>, dated <name type="place">Edinburgh</name>
                                <date>February 10, 1563</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLVII</ref>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="210" locusStart="569" locusEnd="570">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Act of the general assembly of the kirk of <name type="place">Scotland</name>, dated
                                    <date>29 December 1563</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Act of the general assembly of the kirk of <name type="place">Scotland</name> to the
                                same purpose, dated <date>29 December 1563</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLVII note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>570</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="211" locusStart="571" locusEnd="574">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="person">William
                                    Cecil</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the archbishop to <name type="person">Mr. secretary Cecill</name>,
                                desiring his advice as to what regard should be paid to the above request of the general
                                assembly, dated <date>April 14</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLIX (note)</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>572</locus> - <locus>574</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="212" locusStart="575" locusEnd="576">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Cecil</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">secretary Cecill</name>, that he had sent the
                                archbishop a form of prayer drawn up by the bishop of London, and that orders had been
                                dispatched to the <name type="person">earl of Warwick</name> to surrender <name
                                    type="place">New-Haven</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CXXXVI</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>576</locus> address</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="213" locusStart="577" locusEnd="578">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Cecil</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, recommending <name type="person">sir Henry Lee</name> to the
                                archbishop, dated <name type="place">Wyndsor</name>
                                <date>24 September 1569</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCLXXII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>578</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="214" locusStart="579" locusEnd="580">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir William Petre</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir William Petres</name>, that he had sent the
                                queen's commission directed to the archbishop and others, to draw up statutes for <name
                                    type="place">Christ-Church Oxford</name>, dated <name type="place">Greenwich</name>
                                <date>6 June, 1566</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence LXXXII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>580</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="215" locusStart="581" locusEnd="582">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Nicholas Wotton</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. N. Wootton</name>, recommending <name
                                    type="person">Mr. Anthony Rush</name> to be schoolmaster at <name type="place"
                                    >Canterbury</name>, dated <name type="place">Canterbury</name>
                                <date>ultima June 1561</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CIII and note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>582</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="216" locusStart="583" locusEnd="586">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="person">Nicholas
                                    Wotton</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The archbishop's answer</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CIII and note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>584</locus> - <locus>586</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="217" locusStart="587" locusEnd="588">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir William Petre</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir William Petres</name>, that he had sent the
                                archbishop a letter and articles received from <name type="place">Germany</name>, which
                                her majesty desires him to consider, dated <name type="place">Greenwich</name>
                                <date>14 July, 1560</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence LXXXII</ref>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>588</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="218" locusStart="589" locusEnd="592">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Cecil</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Mr. secretary Cecill</name>, thanking the archbishop
                                for his advice concerning the appeasing the controversy about Christ's descent into
                                hell, and expressing his concern at a commission the queen was minded to put forth to
                                enquire into the waste of the clergy thro' the whole realm, dated <name type="place"
                                    >Westminster</name>
                                <date>12 September 1567</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCXXXIV</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>590</locus> - <locus>592</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="219" locusStart="593" locusEnd="594">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">G. Rogers</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>From <name type="author">G. Rogers</name>, desiring the archbishop to grant a
                                dispensation to <name type="person">John Deker</name> to hold a prebende: dated from the
                                court <date>19 December 1559</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>594</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="220" locusStart="595" locusEnd="596">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Parry</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>From <name type="author">Thomas Parry</name>, desiring that <name type="person"
                                    >William Forde</name> may have the parsonage of <name type="place">Cleve</name> in
                                the county of <name type="place">Gloucester</name>, dated from the court <date>26 August
                                    1559</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>596</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="221" locusStart="597" locusEnd="598">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir John Mason</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir John Mason</name>, desiring that the students of
                                    <name type="place">New-College</name> may be treated with lenity in hopes of their
                                future conformity, dated <date>May 12, 1562</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>598</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="222" locusStart="599" locusEnd="600">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter to <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name> concerning <name type="person"
                                    >Dr. Baskerville</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from óó, desiring that <name type="person">Dr. Baxtervyle</name> may be
                                released from his imprisonment on his promise of conformity, dated <date>November 20,
                                    1562</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence p. 171 note</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="223" locusStart="601" locusEnd="608">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="person">Nicholas
                                    Bacon</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the archbishop to the lord-keeper in favor of <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Baxtervyle</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CXXIV</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>602</locus> - <locus>608</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="224" locusStart="609" locusEnd="610">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Francis Knollys</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir F. Knollys</name>, desiring the archbishop to
                                persuade <name type="person">Edward Chamber</name> to subscribe, and wishing the
                                archbishop success in his good enterprize against the enormities still retained in the
                                queen's closet [probably the use of the crucifix] dated from the court <date>13 October
                                    1559</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence LXVII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>610</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="225" locusStart="611" locusEnd="616">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Abraham Cave</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Abraham Cave</name>, desiring the archbishop to call
                                before the high commission court <name type="person">John Marshall</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Mary wife of John Kempe</name> for living together in adultery: dated
                                from the <name type="place">Savoye</name>
                                <date>18 February 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>612</locus> - <locus>616</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="226" locusStart="617" locusEnd="618">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">James Boleyn</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">James Boleyn</name>, desiring the archbishop to grant
                                    <name type="person">sir Robert Payne</name> parson of <name type="place"
                                    >Salington</name> in <name type="place">Norfolk</name> a dispensation for
                                non-residence and for holding two benefices, dated <date>April 27</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>618</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="227" locusStart="619" locusEnd="620">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Edward Warner</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Edward Warner</name>, desiring that <name
                                    type="person">Christopher Southes</name> might be admitted by proxy to the prebend
                                of <name type="place">Ofgoodby</name> in the church of <name type="place"
                                >Lincoln</name>; dated from the <name type="place">tower of London</name>
                                <date>22 July, 1560</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>620</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="228" locusStart="621" locusEnd="622">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Robert Tyrwhitt</name> and <name type="author"
                                    >Sir Nicholas Throckmorton</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Robert Tyrwhyt</name> and <name type="author">N.
                                    Throkmorton</name> in favor of <name type="person">Thomas Darbie</name>; dated <name
                                    type="place">London</name>
                                <date>28 September 1569</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>622</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="229" locusStart="623" locusEnd="624">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Henry Radcliffe</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Henry Radclyff</name>, desiring the archbishop to
                                grant <name type="person">Edward Crofte</name> a scholar of <name type="place"
                                    >Cambridge</name> a dispensation to hold a benefice for seven years; dated from the
                                court <date>8 July, 1568</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>624</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="230" locusStart="625" locusEnd="625">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir George Howard</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir George Howard</name>, recommending <name
                                    type="person">Mr. Beard</name> vicar of <name type="place">Greenwich</name> to the
                                archbishop: dated from the court <date>11 October 1563</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLI and note</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="231" locusStart="625" locusEnd="626">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="author">Sir
                                    George Howard</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The archbishop's answer</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLI and note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>626</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="232" locusStart="627" locusEnd="636">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir Thomas Gresham</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir Thomas Gresham</name>, desiring the archbishop to
                                institute the bearer to the living of <name type="place">Great Massingham</name> in
                                    <name type="place">Norfolk</name>; dated <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>25 May, 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>628</locus> - <locus>636</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="233" locusStart="637" locusEnd="638">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir William Butts</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir William Butts</name> to <name type="person">Dr.
                                    Parker</name> (when master of C.C.C.C.) recommending two young persons and their
                                tutor to him: dated from the court <date>19 May, 37 Henrici VIII</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>638</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="234" locusStart="639" locusEnd="640">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Sir William Butts the younger</name> to <name
                                    type="person">Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">sir William Butts</name>, son to the former, desiring
                                the archbishop to maintain <name type="person">Marmaduke Wood</name> in the possession
                                of the living of <name type="place">Wissingset</name> in <name type="place"
                                    >Norfolk</name>, against one <name type="person">Watesone</name>, who was already
                                possessed of the livings of <name type="place">North Walsham</name> and <name
                                    type="place">Erpingham</name>, and who wanted to obtain it from the archbishop;
                                dated <name type="place">Thornage</name>
                                <date>ultima Januarii 1567</date></title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>640</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="235" locusStart="641" locusEnd="644">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr J. Smith</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Dr. J. Smith</name>, desiring that <name
                                    type="person">Tristam Swadell</name> might have leave to return to <name
                                    type="place">Cambridge</name>: dated <name type="place">Monthall</name>
                                <date>February 5</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>642</locus> - <locus>644</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="236" locusStart="645" locusEnd="645">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Edmund Wyndham</name> and others to <name
                                    type="person">Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Edmund Whyndham</name> and others, desiring the
                                archbishop to grant unto <name type="person">John Toundshend</name> a dispensation to
                                hold the living of <name type="place">Eastwell</name> in <name type="place"
                                    >Suffolk</name> for a longer time, without taking priests orders: dated <date>6
                                    August 1567</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="237" locusStart="646" locusEnd="654">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">R. Hopton</name> and others to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">R. Hopton</name> and others, desiring that one <name
                                    type="person">Master Lawrens</name> may have his licence restored to him, as he was
                                the only preacher between <name type="place">Blyburgh</name> and <name type="place"
                                    >Ipswich</name>, dated <date>27 October 1567</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCXXXVI</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>Signatures of the letter are pasted on p. <locus>646</locus>. Letter starts on p.
                                    <locus>647</locus></supplied>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>648</locus> - <locus>654</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="238" locusStart="655" locusEnd="656">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">J. Bourne</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">J. Bourne</name>, desiring the archbishop to give
                                credit to the bearer <name type="person">Mr. Allen</name>, in what he should relate of
                                some things that required reformation; dated from the castle of the <name type="place"
                                    >Holte</name>
                                <date>10 February 1562</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>656</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="239" locusStart="657" locusEnd="660">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Wroth</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Wrothe</name>, recommending <name
                                    type="person">Mr. Bewlie</name> parson of <name type="place">Racheford</name> a
                                suitor for the living of <name type="place">South-church</name>, dated <name
                                    type="place">Ratcheford</name>
                                <date>16 July, 1562</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>658</locus> - <locus>660</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="240" locusStart="661" locusEnd="661">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Warham St Leger</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Warham Sentleger</name>, that he had remitted the
                                archbishop thirty pounds: dated <name type="place">Leeds</name>
                                <date>13 April 1560</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence LXXVIII and
                                note</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="241" locusStart="662" locusEnd="662">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="author">Warham
                                    St Leger</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The archbishop's answer</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence LXXVIII and
                                note</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="242" locusStart="663" locusEnd="664">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Walter Haddon</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Gualteri Haddon</name>, data <date>pridie nonas
                                    Julii</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CLXVI</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>664</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="243" locusStart="665" locusEnd="668">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Henry</name> óó to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Henry</name> óó, desiring to have a licence to eat
                                flesh, dated <name type="place">Sherland</name> the <date>17 February
                                1563</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>666</locus> - <locus>668</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="244" locusStart="669" locusEnd="670">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Josselyn</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">T. Josselyn</name>, he thanks the archbishop for his
                                kindness towards his son <name type="person">John Josselyn</name>, and desires his
                                acceptance of a doe and two cygnets: dated <name type="place">Newhall-Josselyn</name>
                                <date>21 November 1560</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>670</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="245" locusStart="671" locusEnd="674">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">G. Somerset</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">G. Somerset</name>, recommending a servant to the
                                archbishop, dated <name type="place">Badmondisffelde</name> in <name type="place"
                                    >Suffolk</name>
                                <date>February 8, 1559</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>672</locus> - <locus>674</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="246" locusStart="675" locusEnd="676">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Henry Doyle</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Henry Doyley</name>, thanking the archbishop for
                                granting his son leave to visit him: dated <name type="place">Pondhall</name>
                                <date>12 March 1560</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>676</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="247" locusStart="677" locusEnd="678">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Kempe</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Kempe</name>, desiring the archbishop to grant
                                his licence for the marriage of his daughter with <name type="person">Thomas
                                    Shurleye</name>, dated <name type="place">Olente</name> in <name type="place"
                                    >Kent</name>
                                <date>February 8, 1560</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>678</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="248" locusStart="679" locusEnd="684">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Henry Crisp</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Henry Cryspe</name>, desiring to have a lease of
                                    <name type="place">Cheslett-park</name>, dated <name type="place">Thanet</name>
                                <date>January 30</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>680</locus> - <locus>684</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="249" locusStart="685" locusEnd="686">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Walter Haddon</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Gualteri Haddon</name>, data <name type="place"
                                    >Brugis</name>
                                <date>3 kalendas Augusti 1565</date>, de victoria in Turcas</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Ascham 1703">Aschami Epistolae 1703, p. 444</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="250" locusStart="689" locusEnd="690">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Seckford</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Sekford</name> that it was the queen's
                                pleasure that the widow of <name type="person">Allen</name> her late chaplain and
                                minister of <name type="place">Clyffe</name> should have xx marks yearly out of that
                                benefice: dated from the court</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>690</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="251" locusStart="691" locusEnd="692">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Seckford</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, desiring that <name type="person">Mr. Wendye</name> archdeacon
                                of Suffolk might have a prebend of <name type="place">Norwich</name>, dated from the
                                court <date>June 21, 1561</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence C</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>692</locus> address</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="252" locusStart="695" locusEnd="700">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Mann</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Io. Mann</name>, data <name type="place">Madrid</name>
                                <date>4 Novembris 1566</date>, quod impetraverat immunitatem religionis et securitatem
                                ab omnibus molestiis sed sibi soli; famulis suis negabatur</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>696</locus> - <locus>700</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="253" locusStart="701" locusEnd="702">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Masters</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Masters</name>, desiring that his brother who
                                did not conform in apparel might be suffered for a short time: dated <name type="place"
                                    >Greenwich</name>
                                <date>8 June, 1566</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>702</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="254" locusStart="703" locusEnd="706">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from óó to <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name> on a matrimonial
                                cause</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from óó on a matrimonial cause, dated from the court <date>May
                                8</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>704</locus> - <locus>706</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="255" locusStart="707" locusEnd="710">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Masters</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Masters</name>, recommending a person from
                                the <name type="person">earl of Leicester</name>; dated <name type="place"
                                    >Hampton-court</name>
                                <date>November 1</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>708</locus> - <locus>710</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="256" locusStart="711" locusEnd="712">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Gilbert Gerrard</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">G. Gerrerd</name>, desiring the archbishop to protect
                                    <name type="person">Latham</name> fellow of <name type="place">Merton-College
                                    Oxford</name>, who was in danger of losing his fellowship; dated <date>29 December
                                    1567</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCXXXVIII note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>712</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="257" locusStart="713" locusEnd="714">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Gilbert Gerrard</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, desiring the archbishop to dispense with the decree that he had
                                made, that three of the seniors of <name type="place">Merton-College</name> should be
                                priests; dated <name type="place">London</name>
                                <date>21 June, 1568</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCL and note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>714</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="258" locusStart="715" locusEnd="716">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="author">Gilbert
                                    Gerrard</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The archbishop's answer to the last letter, in which he expresses his surprize that
                                out of twenty fellows of <name type="place">Merton-College</name> there should not three
                                be found disposed to enter into orders, and declares that he cannot in conscience recall
                                his decree: dated <name type="place">Croydon</name>
                                <date>June 21</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCL and note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>716</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="259" locusStart="717" locusEnd="720">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to <name type="author">Gilbert
                                    Gerrard</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The archbishop's answer to <name type="person">Gerrerd</name>'s former letter, that
                                the fellows of <name type="place">Merton</name> accused <name type="person"
                                    >Latham</name> of many heinous crimes: <date>ultima Decembris</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCXXXVIII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>718</locus> - <locus>720</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="260" locusStart="721" locusEnd="722">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">F. Allen</name> to <name type="author">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">F. Allen</name> enclosing letters from the council,
                                dated <name type="place">Havering</name>
                                <date>15 July, 1568</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>722</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="261" locusStart="723" locusEnd="723">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Tamworth</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Tamworth</name>, recommending <name
                                    type="person">William King</name> M.A. of Cambridge to the archbishop's service:
                                dated from the court <date>24 May</date>; with a note written by the archbishop that he
                                had received him as his chaplain <date>21 June, 1565</date></title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="262" locusStart="723" locusEnd="724">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Tamworth</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, desiring that his kinsman [<name type="person">Ralph
                                    Lever</name>] may have the archdeaconry of <name type="place"
                                >Northumberland</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>724</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="263" locusStart="725" locusEnd="726">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Heneage</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">T. Heneage</name>, desiring the archbishop's interest
                                to procure a lease from <name type="place">All-Soul's College Oxford</name> for the
                                    <name type="person">widow Forster</name>; dated from the court <date>11 May,
                                    1568</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCXLIV and
                                note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>726</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="264" locusStart="727" locusEnd="728">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Heneage</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, that <name type="person">Mrs. Foster</name> had not yet been
                                able to procure the lease, chiefly thro' the opposition of the warden; dated from the
                                court <date>30 May, 1568</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCXLIV and
                                note</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>728</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="265" locusStart="729" locusEnd="732">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letters from <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> to the warden of <name
                                    type="place">All Souls College, Oxford</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Two letters from the archbishop, one to the society, dated <name type="place"
                                    >Croydon</name>
                                <date>June 11, 1568</date>, the other to the warden, dated <name type="place"
                                    >Lambeth</name>
                                <date>May 12</date>, in recommendation of <name type="person">Mrs. Forster</name>'s
                                suit</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCXLIV and
                                CCXLVIII</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="266" locusStart="733" locusEnd="734">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Goodrich</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Goodrick</name>, petitioning that a
                                dispensation may be granted to the son of the <name type="person">widow Sparkes</name>
                                to hold an ecclesiastical benefice; dated <name type="place">Stolmmere</name>
                                <date>July 29, 1560</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Parker, Correspondence CCXLIV and
                                CCXLVIII</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>734</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>



                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="267" locusStart="735" locusEnd="740">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Richard Goodrich</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the same, recommending a person for orders: dated <name type="place"
                                    >White-friers London</name>
                                <date>March 30, 1559</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>736</locus> - <locus>740</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="268" locusStart="741" locusEnd="742">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Wotton</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">Thomas Wotton</name>, congratulating the archbishop
                                upon his promotion, and desiring to be appointed his high steward: dated <name
                                    type="place">Bocton-Malherbe</name>
                                <date>30 July 1559</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>The letter contains a wax seal on p. <locus>741</locus></supplied>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>742</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="269" locusStart="743" locusEnd="744">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Crowmere</name> to <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">William Crowmere</name>, recommending <name
                                    type="person">Mr. Simon Clerke</name> to be one of the preachers of <name
                                    type="place">Christ-Church Canterbury</name>, dated <name type="place"
                                    >Tunstalle</name>
                                <date>27 July, 1560</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>p. <locus>744</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="270" locusStart="745" locusEnd="750">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Tufton</name> and <name type="author">Thomas
                                    Wotton</name> to <name type="person">Matthew Parker</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">John Tufton</name> and <name type="author">Thomas
                                    Wotton</name>, recommending <name type="person">Edward Peckham</name> school-master
                                at <name type="place">Egerton</name> for holy orders, dated <date>5 May,
                                1565</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>746</locus> - <locus>750</locus> blank except for addresses on some
                                pages</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>