<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC121">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>121</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. 3</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Synodalia</head>
                <head type="James">Synodalia</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">305</height>
                        <width unit="mm">214</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">12.5 x 8.5</measureGrp>.</p>



                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iv + pp. 1-4 + ff. 5 + 5a-i + 5k-t + pp.5x-6 + 7-116 (117-126 missing) + 127-136 +
                        137a + 137aa + 137b + 137bb + 137c-138 + 139-162 + 162a-t + 163-276 (277-278 missing) + 279-364
                        + 375 + 369 + 377 + 367 + 379 + 365 + 371 + 373 + 380a-b + 381-396 (397-428 missing) + 429-514
                        (515-518 missing) + 519-522 + 522a-f + 523-526 (527-528 missing) + 529-530 + ff.
                        v-vii</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1" locusEnd="2">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Form of holding convocation following ancient customs</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Forma seu descriptio convocationis celebrandae, prout ab antiquo observari
                                consuevit</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="3" locusEnd="4">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Form of choosing and presenting prolocutors</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Forma eligendi et presentandi proloquutoris</title>
                        </head>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="5r" locusEnd="5v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Writ of <name type="author">Matthew Parker archbishop of Canterbury</name> summoning
                                the bishop and clergy of <name type="place">London</name> to convocation, <date>3 April
                                    1570</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Breve <name type="author">Matthiae archiepiscopi Cantuariensis</name> directum
                                episcopo Londoniensi ut citet clerum ad convocationem <date>tertio die Aprilis,
                                    1570</date>, in <name type="place">ecclesia cathedrali S. Pauli London.</name>
                                celebrandam</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On this Convocation see <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Concilia</hi> IV 261</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="5ar" locusEnd="5bv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Election of <name type="person">John Taylor dean of Lincoln Cathedral</name> as
                                prolocutor of the lower house of convocation of <date>5 November 1547</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Electio <name type="person">Iohannis Taylor</name> S. T. P. decani ecclesiae
                                cathedralis Lincolniensis in proloquutorem inferioris domus convocationis <date>5
                                    Novembris 1547</date>, cum nominibus personaliter presentium in hujusmodi
                                electione</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Gasquet and Bishop 1890">Gasquet and Bishop, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Edward VI and the Book of Common Prayer</hi>, Appendix VII, p. 449</ref>, regard
                                <supplied>items 4-8</supplied> as a fragment of the Journals of this Convocation. They
                            refer to this MS. wrongly as 113. An extract is in <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694"
                                >Strype's Cranmer p. 220</ref>. Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi
                                    rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 15</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="5cr" locusEnd="5fr">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Names of the monitors <q>ad comparendum</q> of the lower house of the convocation of
                                    <name type="place">Canterbury</name>, <date>Michaelmas 1547</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Nomina monitorum ad comparendum in inferiori domo convocationis <name type="place"
                                    >provinciae Cantuariensis</name> termino S. Michaelis A. D.
                                <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Gasquet and Bishop 1890">Gasquet and Bishop, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Edward VI and the Book of Common Prayer</hi>, Appendix VII, p. 449</ref>, regard
                                <supplied>items 4-8</supplied> as a fragment of the Journals of this Convocation. They
                            refer to this MS. wrongly as 113. An extract is in <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694"
                                >Strype's Cranmer p. 220</ref>. Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi
                                    rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 15</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="5fv" locusEnd="5hv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Names of the monitors <q>ad comparendum</q> of the lower house of convocation who
                                attended the discussions concerning the marriage of priests</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Nomina eorum qui singulis sessionibus hujus convocationis adfuerunt cum notis
                                breviusculis rerum ibidem tractarum, a secunda sessione usque ad octavam quando
                                proposita est quaestio de matrimonio sacerdotum</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Gasquet and Bishop 1890">Gasquet and Bishop, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Edward VI and the Book of Common Prayer</hi>, Appendix VII, p. 449</ref>, regard
                                <supplied>items 4-8</supplied> as a fragment of the Journals of this Convocation. They
                            refer to this MS. wrongly as 113. An extract is in <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694"
                                >Strype's Cranmer p. 220</ref>. Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi
                                    rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 15</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="5ir" locusEnd="5iv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>On rectors that are not resident in their benefices</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Causae quae adferre solent hoc tempore quod rectores ecclesiarum non resideant in
                                beneficiis suis quatenus de jure canonico</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Gasquet and Bishop 1890">Gasquet and Bishop, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Edward VI and the Book of Common Prayer</hi>, Appendix VII, p. 449</ref>, regard
                                <supplied>items 4-8</supplied> as a fragment of the Journals of this Convocation. They
                            refer to this MS. wrongly as 113. An extract is in <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694"
                                >Strype's Cranmer p. 220</ref>. Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi
                                    rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 15</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="5kr" locusEnd="5kv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>On those who oppose the judgement on perpetual residences</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Causae quae obstant quo minus decretum perpetuae residentiae suum effectum
                                consequatur et remedia huic malo adhibenda</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Gasquet and Bishop 1890">Gasquet and Bishop, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Edward VI and the Book of Common Prayer</hi>, Appendix VII, p. 449</ref>, regard
                                <supplied>items 4-8</supplied> as a fragment of the Journals of this Convocation. They
                            refer to this MS. wrongly as 113. An extract is in <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694"
                                >Strype's Cranmer p. 220</ref>. Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi
                                    rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 15</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="5lr" locusEnd="5tv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Petition of the lower house of convocation to the bishops in the reign of <name
                                    type="person">Phillip</name> and <name type="person">Mary</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Petition of the lower house of convocation to the bishops in the reign of <name
                                    type="person">Philip</name> and <name type="person">Mary</name> with 28 articles
                                annexed submitted to their lordships consideration</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 95</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="5x" locusEnd="6">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articles concerning tithes and married priests</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Alii articuli Latini de decimis solvendis, de eis quae nuper sacerdotum uxores
                                habitae sunt ut libera nubenda potestas eis permittatur, de nundinis ut in celebrioribus
                                festis et dominicis diebus fieri non permittantur, &amp;c.</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 97</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="7" locusEnd="32">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="person">Cardinal Reginald Pole</name>, <title>Legantine constitutions,
                                    <date>1555</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Constitutiones legantinae editae <name type="place">Londini</name> sub anno
                                    <date>1555</date>, praesidente reverendissimo domino <name type="person">Reginaldo
                                    cardinali Polo</name>, legato de latere, regnantibus christianissimis principibus
                                    <name type="person">Philippo</name> et <name type="person">Maria</name> regibus,
                                &amp;c.</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 121</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="33" locusEnd="34">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Acta of the convocation of <name type="place">Canterbury</name>, <date>January
                                    1557/8</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Acta convocationis seu sacrae synodi advocatae autoritate brevis regis <name
                                    type="person">Philippi</name> et <name type="person">Mariae</name>, celebratae per
                                dominum <name type="person">Reginaldum Pole</name> cardinalem archiepiscopum
                                Cantuariensem A. D. <date>1557, primo Januarias</date>, et anno <name type="person"
                                    >Pauli papae IV</name>. 3<abbr rend="superscript">tio</abbr></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Acta hujus synodi hic fusius memorantur quam apud Wilkins</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 155</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="35" locusEnd="60">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articles promulgated at the convocation of <name type="place">Canterbury</name>,
                                    <date>January 1557/8</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articuli in quinque capita divisi, viz. (1) de doctrina: (2) de hiis quae ad
                                orationem pertinent: (3) de templis decore ornandis et resarciendis: (4) de disciplina
                                ecclesiastica renovanda et moribus cleri per eandem reformandis et de vestitu: (5) de
                                academiis et scholis</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 156</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="61" locusEnd="62">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Decretal of the convocation of <name type="place">Canterbury</name> of <date>January
                                    1557/8</date> concerning the property appropriated for the benefit of <name
                                    type="person">Cardinal Pole</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Decretum [ut videtur synodi] ut episcopus Glocestrensis mittat ad dominum legatum vel
                                eo absente ad episcopum Eliensem, divisionem et distinctionem temporalium bonorum
                                singulorum beneficiorum olim appropriatorum per serenissimos reges ad dispositionem
                                reverendissimi domini legati dimissorum, &amp;c.</title>
                        </head>



                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="63" locusEnd="97">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Canons of the convocation of <name type="place">Canterbury</name>, <date>January
                                    1557/8</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Decreta sive canones ecclesiastici in 25 capitibus</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Probabile videtur haec decreta una cum articulis precedentibus in hac synodo, si non
                                stabilita saltem proposita fuisse</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 159</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="16" locusStart="97" locusEnd="98">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Writs published after the ordinance of earls and barons, <date>1315</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Writtes published after the ordinance of erles and barons, A. D.
                                <date>1315</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>The first is against excess of diet, and prescribes how many dishes should be served
                                at the tables of all ranks of men, and forbids the minstrels resorting to houses if not
                                invited; the second to establish the prices of provision</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 16 and 17 are added to 15</ab>
                        <ab>See also <ref type="ms" target="CCC101">MS 101. 47, 48</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="17" locusStart="99" locusEnd="116">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Names of the earls and barons that ought to be present at the convocations of the
                                province of <name type="place">Canterbury</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Nomina eorum quae debent comparere in convocationibus prelatorum et cleri <name
                                    type="place">Cantuariensis provinciae</name> per singulas dioeceses Cantuariensis
                                Provinciae [ut ab antiquo fieri consuevit ante dissolutionem monasteriorum,]</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 16 and 17 are added to 15</ab>

                        <ab>pp. <locus>106</locus>-<locus locusNew="116">114</locus> blank: 115-126 removed <q>quia
                                superfluae</q>
                            <supplied>(<locus>115</locus>-<locus>116</locus> replaced)</supplied></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="18" locusStart="127" locusEnd="137aa">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">John de Feckenham</name>, <title>Speech on the Uniformity Bill</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A discourse of certain Romanists exhibited to the queen's counsel immediately upon
                                    <name type="person">Q. Elizabeth</name>'s coming in: amongst which was thought <name
                                    type="person">Dr. Hethe</name> to be the penner of the said discourse</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab><name type="person">Feckenham</name>'s Speech, <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1709">Strype,
                                Annals I, Appendix IX</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="19" locusStart="137b" locusEnd="138">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Nicholas Heath, Archbishop of York</name>, <title>A speech against the
                                bill for the royal supremacy</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>[A speech] spoken openly in the first session of <name type="person">Q.
                                    Elizabeth</name> by tharchbishoppe of York, <name type="author">Dr. Hethe</name>
                                [against the bill for the supremacy,]</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1709">Strype, Annals I, Appendix VI</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="20" locusStart="139" locusEnd="162">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>A declaration of doctrine offered and exhibited by the protestants, signed by <name
                                    type="person">George Hovy</name>, <name type="person">John Ploughe</name>, <name
                                    type="person">John Opynshaw</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A declaration of doctrine offred and exhibited by the protestantes to the queene at
                                the first coming over of them, signed by <name type="person">George Hovy</name>, <name
                                    type="person">John Ploughe</name>, <name type="person">John Opynshaw</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Dixon 1902">Dixon's <hi rend="italic">Church History</hi>, V
                                107 note</ref>: <ref type="bibl" target="Hardwick 1876">Hardwick, Articles, p. 117
                                note</ref>. <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1709">Strype, Annals I 115</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="21" locusStart="162a" locusEnd="162t">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Proceedings of a conference at <name type="place">Westminster</name>, <date>March
                                    1559</date>, concerning articles of religion</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The declaration of the procedynge of a conference begon at <name type="place"
                                    >Westminster</name>
                                <date>the laste of Marche, 1559</date>, concerning certaine articles of religion and the
                                breaking up of the sayde conference by defaulte of certayne byshops parties of the said
                                conference</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Imprynted at <name type="place">London</name> by <name type="person">Richard
                                    Jugge</name> and <name type="person">John Cawood</name> prynters to the queens
                                majestie</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>The managers for the papists were, <name type="person">White Bishop of
                                    Winchester</name>, <name type="person">Baine Bishop of Litchfield</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Scott Bishop of Chester</name>, <name type="person">Oglethorpe Bishop
                                    of Carlisle</name>, <name type="person">Watson Bishop of Lincoln</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Dr. Cole</name>, <name type="person">Dr. Harpesfelde</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Dr. Langdall</name>, <name type="person">Dr. Chedsey</name>; for the
                                protestants <name type="person">Dr. Scory Bishop of Chychester</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Dr. Coxe</name>, <name type="person">Mr. Whithed</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Mr. Grindall</name>, <name type="person">Mr. Horne</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Mr. D. Sandes</name>, <name type="person">Mr. Gest</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Mr. Aylmer</name>, <name type="person">Mr. Juell</name></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>10 ff. (5.4 x 3.5 in.) printed. See <ref type="bibl" target="Pocock 1865e">Pocock's Burnet V
                                514</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="22" locusStart="163" locusEnd="182">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Paper delivered by the Protestants at the <name type="place">Westminster</name>
                                conference of <date>March 1559</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Paper read and delivered by the protestants on the first question</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Pocock 1865e">Burnet, <hi rend="italic">History of the
                                    Reformation</hi>, ed. Pocock V 507</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="23" locusStart="183" locusEnd="191">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title><name type="author">Dr Coles</name>' answer to the paper delivered by the Protestants
                                at the <name type="place">Westminster</name> conference of <date>March
                                1559</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="author">Dr. Coles</name> answer to the same</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Pocock 1865e">Burnet, <hi rend="italic">History of the
                                    Reformation</hi>, ed. Pocock V 507</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="24" locusStart="192" locusEnd="196">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Acts of the convocation of <date>January 1558/9</date> held by royal writ while the
                                archbishopric was vacant</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Acta convocationis habitae per breve reginae decano et capitulo Cantuariae directum
                                sede archiepiscopali vacante <date>24 Januarii 1558</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 179</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="25" locusStart="197" locusEnd="232">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The protestants discourse on the second question</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1709">Strype, Annals I, Appendix xvi</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="26" locusStart="233" locusEnd="266">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Thirty-Nine Articles</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articuli de quibus in synodo <name type="place">Londinensi</name>, A. D.
                                    <date>1562</date>, ad tollendam opinionum dissensionem et consensum in vera
                                religione firmandum inter episcopos convenit</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Printed in full by <ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1829">Lamb, <hi rend="italic">History of
                                    the XXXIX Articles</hi> 1829</ref>, with facsimiles of the bishops' signatures</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="27" locusStart="267" locusEnd="364">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Ecclesiastical Statutes</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articles drawn out bi som certen and wer exhibited to be admyted bi authoritie, but
                                not so allowed [a body of ecclesiastical statutes]</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1709">Strype, Annals I pt 2, Appendix II A, p. 562</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="28" locusStart="365" locusEnd="379">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>A bill to authorise every archbishop and bishop to erect one office of registership
                                of all the church books in due order to be kept in every diocese</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A bill to authorize every archbishop and bishop to erect one office of registership
                                of all the church books in due order to be kept in every dioces</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Folding leaves bound across the text</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="29" locusStart="371" locusEnd="380b">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Petition of <name type="author">Thomas Bowsey</name> to the <name type="person"
                                    >Archbishop of Canterbury</name> that he might have the registership of the diocese
                                of <name type="place">Canterbury</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Petition of <name type="author">Thomas Bowsey</name>, who drew up the bill, presented
                                with it to the archbishop, in which after thanking his grace for the many marks of
                                favour he had already received from him at <name type="place">Stoke</name> and at <name
                                    type="place">Bene't College Cambridge</name>, he humbly begs, that if this bill
                                should thro' his graces furtherance pass into a law, he might have the registership of
                                the <name type="place">diocese of Canterbury</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Folding leaves bound across the text</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="30" locusStart="381" locusEnd="388">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of Archbishop elect <name type="author">Matthew Parker</name> and four other
                                bishops to <name type="person">Elizabeth I</name>, undated (<date>October
                                1559?</date>)</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A letter from the archbishop elect, and the bishops elect of London, Ely, Chichester
                                and Hereford, to <name type="person">queen Elizabeth</name>, humbly petitioning her to
                                accept a thousand marks per annum (which they promise to pay as long as they hold their
                                bishopricks) if her majestie would stay and remit the present alteration and exchange;
                                or if this their supplication should not be thought meet to take place they humbly offer
                                certain articles which they desire may be observed in the proposed exchange of
                                appropriations for manors</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, Parker Appendix X</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Correspondence LXVIII</ref>: <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Bentham 1771">Bentham's Ely Appendix XXXII</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="31" locusStart="389" locusEnd="392">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Elizabeth I</name> to Archbishop <name type="person"
                                    >Matthew Parker</name>, the <name type="person">bishop of London</name> and <name
                                    type="person">William Byll</name> dated at <name type="place">Westminster</name>,
                                    <date>21 January 1561</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from <name type="author">queen Elizabeth</name> to <name type="person">Matthew
                                    archbishop of Canterbury</name>, <name type="person">Edmund bishop of London</name>,
                                    <name type="person">Will. Byll</name> almoner to the queen, <name type="person"
                                    >Walter Haddon</name> master of the requests and the other commissioners in causes
                                ecclesiastical, directing them to revise the calendar and order of lessons in the common
                                prayer book, to see that churches and chancels are decently and properly repaired, and
                                to supervise the translation of the common prayer into Latin made for the use of the
                                universities: dated <name type="place">Westminster</name>
                                <date>Jan. 21, anno regni 3<abbr rend="superscript">tio</abbr></date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, Parker Appendix XV</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="32" locusStart="393" locusEnd="396">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articles of the <name type="place">Lambeth</name> conference <date>12 April
                                    1561</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articles agreed upon at the seconde session in <name type="place">Lambeth</name>
                                <date>the 12 day of April A. D. 1561</date>, by the most reverende fathers in God <name
                                    type="person">Matthue lorde archebisshop of Canterburye</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >Thomas lord archebisshop of York</name>, with the assent of there bretherne
                                bysshops to the same</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>[Original signed by the archbishop and the bishops of London and Ely]</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Cardwell 1839">Cardwell, Documentary Annals LVI</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="33" locusStart="429" locusEnd="452">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Thirty-nine Articles</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articles whereupon it was agreed by the archbusshoppes and bushoppes of both the
                                provinces and the whole clergie in the convocation holden at <name type="place"
                                    >London</name> in the yere of our lorde God <date>1562</date>, according to the
                                computation of the churche of <name type="place">Englande</name>, for the avoiding of
                                diversities of opinions and for the stablishing of consente touching true
                                religion</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Original signed by the archbishop and ten of his suffragans</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>In the 20 Article, these words now in our printed copies are wanting, <q>The church
                                    hath power to decree rites or ceremonies and authority in controversies of faith and
                                    yet.</q></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1829">Lamb, Articles</ref>: with facsimiles of signatures</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="34" locusStart="453" locusEnd="481">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articles of the synod held at <name type="place">London</name>, <date>3 April
                                    1571</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articuli de sacro ministerio et procuratione ecclesiarum, in quos plene consensum est
                                in synodo a domino <name type="person">Matthaeo archiepiscopo Cantuariensi</name> et
                                totius Angliae primate et metropolitano et reliquis omnibus ejus provinciae episcopis
                                partim personaliter presentibus partim procuratoria manu subscribentibus in synodo
                                inchoata <name type="place">Londini in aede D. Pauli</name>
                                <date>3 Aprilis 1571</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Originale cum subscriptionibus autographis episcoporum</quote>
                        </ab>


                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins, <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV.
                                263</ref>. <ref type="bibl" target="Cardwell 1842">Cardwell, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Synodalia</hi> I 111-131</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="35" locusStart="482" locusEnd="482">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Form of excommunication</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Forma excommunicationis in ecclesia legendae</title>
                        </head>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="36" locusStart="523" locusEnd="526">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter from the commissioners in ecclesiastical causes to all churchwardens,
                                sidesmen, etc. dated <name type="place">Lambeth</name>
                                <date>June 11, 1571</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Letter from the commissioners in ecclesiastical causes to all churchwardens,
                                sidesmen, &amp;c. dated <name type="place">Lambeth</name>
                                <date>June 11, 13 Eliz.</date> commanding them not to suffer any minister to officiate
                                in any church or chapple unless by the common prayer, and unless they be licenced by the
                                queen or the bishop since the <date>1st of May last past</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>printed</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 36, 37 now follow no. 41</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Correspondence CCLXXXIX</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="37" locusStart="527" locusEnd="530">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Copy of a letter from the commissioners in ecclesiastical causes to all
                                churchwardens, sidesmen, etc. dated <name type="place">Lambeth</name>
                                <date>June 11, 1571</date> subscribed by the commissioners</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Original copy of the same subscribed by the commissioners</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab><supplied>Items</supplied> 36, 37 now follow no. 41</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Bruce and Perowne 1853">Correspondence CCLXXXIX</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="38" locusStart="483" locusEnd="486">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Injunctions given by the authority of the king's highness to the clergy of this his
                                realm [by <name type="person">Thomas Cromwell</name> vice-regent]
                                <date>1536</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Injunctions given by thauctorite of the kynges highness to the clergie of this his
                                realm [by <name type="person">Thomas lord Crumwell</name> vice-gerent] A. D.
                                    <date>1536</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>printed by <name type="person">Thomas Berthelet</name> kings printer</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737c">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi>, III
                                813</ref>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="483">The first is that the Deane, persons, vicars</incipit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="39" locusStart="487" locusEnd="488">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Visitors in <name type="person">King Edward's</name> time, <date>1547</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Visiters in <date when-iso="1547"><name type="person">king Edwards</name> tyme, anno
                                    primo</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Three, four, or sometimes five with a register went to visit four or five
                                dioceses</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>Pasted on the flyleaf of <supplied>item</supplied> 40. <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694"
                                >Strype, Cranmer I 209</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="40" locusStart="489" locusEnd="520">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Injunctions given by the king's majesty as well to the clergy as to the laity of this
                                realm</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Injunctions given by the kyngs majestye as well to the clergie as to the laytie of
                                this realm</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Original signed by <name type="person">Edward VI</name>. the protector and
                                council</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 3</ref>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="490">The firste is that all Deanes, Archdeacons, parsonnes</incipit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="41" locusStart="521" locusEnd="522f">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Letter of <name type="author">Elizabeth I</name> to the <name type="person">bishop of
                                    London</name>, <date>March 1553</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A copie of a letter with articles sent from the queenes majestie unto the bysshoppe
                                of London, and by him and his officers at her graces commaundement to be putte in spedie
                                execution wyth effecte in the whole diocese, as well in places exempt as not exempte
                                whatsoever according to the tenour and forme of the same. Sent by the queene majesties
                                commaundement in the moneth of <date>Marche A. D. 1553</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>printed</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Wilkins 1737d">Wilkins <hi rend="italic">Concilia</hi> IV 88</ref>.
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Cardwell 1839">Cardwell, Documentary Annals XXX</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>








                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 1/12/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks: 527 is in the fold at 529</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
