<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC128">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>128</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. 7</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Documents Relating to Archbishop Cranmer</head>
                <head type="James">Documents Relating to Abp Cranmer</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">314</height>
                        <width unit="mm">210</width>
                    </measureGrp>, various sizes, <extent>pp. 442 numbered</extent>. Cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate>.</p>



                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-ii + pp. 1-2 (3-4 missing) + 5-166 + 166a-d + 167-264 + 264a-265a + 265-324 +
                        324a-325a + 325-436 + 436a + 437a +437-442 + ff. iii-iv</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="eng">English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1" locusEnd="364">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articles against several of the clergy prepared for <name type="person">Archbishop
                                    Cranmer</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articles against several of the clergy, interrogatories for, and depositions of <name
                                    type="person">Dr. John Willoughby</name>, <name type="person">Robert Serles</name>,
                                    <name type="person">William Gardiner</name>, <name type="person">Edmund
                                    Shethur</name>, <name type="person">Richard Parkhurst</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >Arthur St. Leger</name>, <name type="person">John Mills</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >William Hunt</name>, <name type="person">William Cocks</name>, <name type="person"
                                    >John Thatcher</name>, &amp;c.</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>The occasion and import of these examinations are explained by <name type="person"
                                    >archbishop Parker</name> in the following note at p. <locus>20</locus>.
                                    <q>Memorandum that <name type="person">king Henry</name> beinge divers times by
                                        <name type="person">bushop Gardiner</name> enformed against <name type="person"
                                        >bushoppe Cranmer</name>, and the saide <name type="person">Gardiner</name>
                                    havinge his instruccions of <name type="person">D. London</name> a stoute and
                                    filthie prebendary of <name type="place">Windesor</name>, who theare convicted did
                                    weare a paper openly, and rodde throughe the towne with his face towards the horse
                                    taile, and also had informacion of <name type="person">Mr. Moyles</name>, <name
                                        type="person">Mr. Baker</name> and sum others promooted by the said <name
                                        type="person">Cranmer</name>, whose tales he uttred to the king, who perceiving
                                    the malice trusted the said <name type="person">Cranmer</name> with thexamination of
                                    thes matters, which he did of divers persons as by this doth appeare.</q></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab locusNew="2">No. 1 has a partial index in <name type="person">Cranmer</name>'s hand</ab>
                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694">Strype, Cranmer chap. xxv, xxvi, and Appendix
                                xxxiii</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="365" locusEnd="404">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Accounts for the imprisonment and execution of <name type="person">Cranmer</name>,
                                    <name type="person">Latimer</name> and <name type="person">Ridley</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The booke of the expences of D. <name type="person">Cranmer</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Latymer</name> and <name type="person">Ridley</name> for the time of
                                their imprisonment in <name type="place">Oxford</name> and of their execution, delivered
                                into the hands of the most reverend father <name type="person">Matthew archbushop of
                                    Canterbury</name> by <name type="person">Thomas Wincle</name> and <name
                                    type="person">John Wells</name> of <name type="place">Oxford</name>, sometime
                                bayliffs there</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <quote>Before the accompts are</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="367">
                            <quote>(1) A letter from <name type="author">Lawrence Humphrey</name> to the archbishop in
                                favour of the bailiffs to whom 40£. was still due on this account</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="369">
                            <quote>(2) A petition of <name type="author">Wincle</name> and <name type="author"
                                    >Wells</name> praying the payment of the same</quote>
                        </ab>


                        <ab>No. 2 partly in <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1694">Strype chap. xxi (end)</ref> with the
                            letters of <name type="author">Humfrey</name> and <name type="author">Wincle</name></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="405" locusEnd="442">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Biography of <name type="person">Thomas Cranmer, Archbishop of
                                Canterbury</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>A declaracion concerning the progeny with the manner and the trade of the life and
                                bryngyng up of that most reverent father in God <name type="person">Thomas
                                    Cranmer</name> late archbishop of Canterbury, and by what order and meanes he came
                                to his preferment and dignity</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>This life was written at the desire of <name type="person">archbishop Parker</name>
                                by one who had been a domestic of <name type="person">Cranmer</name>'s, and though
                                concise contains many curious anecdotes, most of which have been inserted by <ref
                                    type="bibl" target="Strype 1694">Strype in his life of Cranmer</ref></quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>No. 3 printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Nichols 1859"><hi rend="italic">Narratives of the
                                    Reformation</hi>, Nichols, Camden Society p. 238</ref>. See also <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Strype 1694">Strype, <hi rend="italic">Cranmer</hi>, chap. xxx etc.</ref></ab>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck:</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
