<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>

                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC139">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>139</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>F. 5</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>64</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Simeon of Durham OSB, Historia regum. Richard of Hexham OSA, De gestis regis Stephani
                    et de bello standardii. John of Hexham OSA, Nennius</head>

                <head type="James">Simeon Dunelmensis. Ricardus et Johannes de Hexham. Nennius</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">302</height>
                        <width unit="mm">217</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">12 x 8.4</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 182 + 2</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 36 and 35 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xii</origDate>, in several
                    hands. Mommsen assigns the Nennius-portion to cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate>, but to me it seems
                    that all is of cent. <origDate>xii late</origDate>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num> I<num>10</num> (10 canc.) II<num>8</num> (2 canc.) III<num>8</num>
                            IV<num>8</num> V<num>10</num> (4, 5, cut out and replaced by a sheet of two leaves: (8
                        canc.) VI<num>10</num> VII<num>8</num> (+ 1 leaf of cent. xvi inserted before 8)
                            VIII<num>8</num>-XVI<num>8</num> (+1) XVII<num>8</num> XVIII<num>8</num> XIX<num>14</num>
                        (1, 2 canc.) XX<num>8</num> (wants 5-8) | XXI<num>10</num> (10 canc.) XXII<num>8</num> (wants 6,
                        7)</collation>.</p>


                <p function="Additions">f. <locus>ir</locus> covered with <material>paper</material>: <decoNote>on f.
                            <locus>iv</locus>a <date>xv</date>th cent. sketch of the Virgin crowned and the
                        Child</decoNote>.<lb/> f. <locus>iir</locus>
                    <date>xv</date>th cent. list of contents: In hoc libro continentur hec (15 items).<lb/> f.
                        <locus>iir</locus> 3 verses (<date>xv</date>) scribbled.<lb/> Three extracts in a black hand of
                    cent. <date>xii</date>:<lb/> (a) <name type="person">Gennadius</name> massiliensis in libro de
                    illustribus uiris<lb/>
                    <name type="person">Jeronimus</name> natus patre <name type="person">eusebio</name>... <name
                        type="person">Eusebius</name> quoque <name type="place">cesaree</name> palestine ep... Dexter
                    uero pagatiani filius...<lb/> (to the effect that all three wrote historia omnimoda)<lb/> Hec in
                    libris illustr. uirorum de omnimoda hysteria scripta sunt.<lb/> (b) Titulus <name type="person"
                        >origenis</name> super tumulum eius ab ipso compositus<lb/> Ille ego origenes doctor uerissimus
                    olim<lb/> ...<lb/> His mihi coniectum undique tela premunt.<lb/> (From the verses composed by <name
                        type="author">Isidore of Seville</name> for his library.)<lb/> (c) <name type="person"
                        >Pompeius</name> trogus ciuis romanus fuit. cuius pater sub <name type="person">gaio
                        cesare</name> militauit ... cuius libris omnium seculorum regum nationum populorumque res geste
                    continentur.<lb/> Col. 2 has been written and carefully erased.</p>


                <p function="Provenance" rend="afterContents">Most editors assign the book to <name type="place"
                        >Hexham</name>, <name type="person">Mommsen</name> to <name type="place">Salley</name> on
                    account of its relation to <ref type="ms" target="CUL127">University Library Ff. 1. 27</ref>, part
                    of which is from <name type="place">Salley</name> (see <ref type="ms" target="CCC066">MS 66</ref>).
                    I consider <name type="place">Hexham</name> the more likely.<lb/> It is clear from many (eleven)
                    references in Bale's <ref type="bibl" target="Bale 1902">Index Scriptorum (s.v. <name type="person"
                            >Nennius</name>, <name type="person">Ailred</name>, <name type="person">Ric.
                            Hagustaldensis</name>, Chronicon p. 488, etc.)</ref> that in his time a book very similar to
                    this in contents was at <name type="place">Westminster Abbey</name>. This fact is recognized by the
                    editors of the <ref type="bibl" target="Bale 1902">Index</ref>. When <name type="person"
                        >Joscelin</name> wrote his Catalogue of British historians, it seems to have been in the hands
                    of a prebendary of <name type="place">Westminster</name> named <name type="person">Pekyns</name>.
                    But from the same catalogue we learn that Dr <name type="person">Nicholas Wotton</name>, Dean of
                    Canterbury, gave <name type="person">Parker</name> a volume containing much of the same matter as
                    this. The items specified by <name type="person">Joscelin</name> are <name type="person">Simeon of
                        Durham</name>, <name type="person">John</name> and <name type="person">Richard of Hexham</name>,
                    and articles 11, 12, 14 in this MS. It seems most likely therefore that the <name type="place"
                        >Westminster</name> volume was a sister book to this, and has perished, and that <ref type="ms"
                        target="CCC139">MS 139</ref> is the book given by Dean <name type="person">Wotton</name> to
                        <name type="person">Parker</name>.<lb/>
                    <name type="person">Wotton</name> was Dean of <name type="place">York</name> as well as of <name
                        type="place">Canterbury</name> and so may have procured the volume from his northern home.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-d + i-ii + 1-180 + iii-vi</foliation>.</p>




                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="16v">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Historia omnimoda ab orbe condito ad regnum <name type="person">Davidis</name>, cui
                                subnectuntur nomina pontificum Romanorum a <name type="person">Sancto Petro</name> ad
                                    <name type="person">Calixtum II</name></title>
                        </head>




                        <rubric locus="1r">Incipit historia omnimoda</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Mundum sine inicio dicimus in tempore</incipit>
                        <ab>Sections follow, de deo et anima, de dissensione annorum, Diuerse opiniones philosophorum et
                            nostrorum</ab>
                        <ab>Quotations from <name type="author">Ambrose</name>, <name type="author">Augustine</name>,
                                <name type="author">Origen</name>, <name type="author">Epiphanius</name></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="2r">de salute <name type="person">adam</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="2r">qui interrogat ueniam clare desiderat</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="3r" locusNew="2r">Cronica omnimode hystorie</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="2r">Prima etas mundi fuit ab <name type="person">adam</name> usque ad <name
                                type="person">noe</name></incipit>
                        <ab><name type="author">Arnobius</name> rethor in psalmos is quoted: also <name type="author"
                                >Rabanus</name> in Genesim, <name type="person">Gregorius Turonensis</name></ab>
                        <ab>Goes down to <name type="person">David</name>. The last paragraphs are</ab>
                        <ab>De bello codri etc.</ab>
                        <ab><name type="person">Bersellai</name> galaadites fidelis <name type="person">dauid</name>
                            <name type="person">achitefel</name> proditorius</ab>
                        <ab>Nota quod lucas euuang. generationem domini a <name type="person">salathiel</name> usque ad
                                <name type="person">dauid</name> per xxx uiros ascendendo conuenerat. Similiter ab
                            ultimo <name type="person">Joseph</name> us(que) ad <name type="person"
                            >salathiel</name></ab>
                        <rubric locus="15v">Exortatio scriptoris</rubric>
                        <ab>(<handNote>in another hand</handNote>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="15v">Per descriptum uolubile tempus sic uoluitur uolubilis mundus</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="15v">per lumen scientie ad gloriam et honorem perducaet</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="15v">Hec sententia debet scribi post nomina pontificum</rubric>
                        <ab locus="16r">List of Popes to <name type="person">Calixtus II</name>
                                (<date>1119</date>-<date>1124</date>)</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="16v">Explicit omnimoda historia</rubric>
                        <ab>Another copy (with different ending) in MS. <ref type="ms" target="OMC008">Magdalen College
                                Oxford 8</ref></ab>





                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="17r" locusEnd="35v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Regino of Pr&#252;m</name>, <title>Chronicon</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Cronica <name type="author">abbatis Prumiensis monasterii</name> a Christo nato ad
                                annum <date>1002</date></title>
                        </head>





                        <rubric locus="17r">Incipit cronica <name type="author">abbatis prumiensis monasterii</name> ubi
                                <name type="person">lotharius</name> imperator ad conuersionem uenit</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="17r">Anno imperii <name type="person">Octouiani</name> cesaris xl. ii. iesus
                            Christus filius dei natus est</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>Here begins a hand which has written the bulk of the volume</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="29r">Liber II</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="35v">ex quo uulnere eadem nocte extinguitur</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="35v">Explicit cronica <name type="author">abatis prumiensis
                            ecclesiae</name></rubric>
                        <ab><name type="author">Regino of Prum</name>. <ref type="bibl" target="Pertz 1829">MGH.
                                Scriptores I 537</ref>. This MS. was not seen by the editors. It ends in
                                <date>1002</date> (<ref type="bibl" target="Pertz 1829">p. 609 MGH</ref>)</ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="36r" locusEnd="46r">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Richard of Hexham OSA</name>, <title>De gestis regis <name type="person"
                                    >Stephani</name> et de bello standardii</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Historia piae memoriae <name type="person">Ricardi prioris Hagustaldensis
                                    ecclesiae</name> de gestis regis <name type="person">Stephani</name> et de bello
                                Standardii</title>
                        </head>





                        <ab>Originally began on the same page (f. <locus>35v</locus>) but a little more than half a
                            column has been erased. The two next leaves were cut out and replaced by a sheet (still
                            cent. <date>xii</date>) <handNote>in at least three hands</handNote></ab>
                        <rubric locus="36r">Incipit historia pie memorie prioris <name type="author">Ricardi
                                Haugustaldensis</name> ecclesiae De gestis regis <name type="person">Stephani</name> et
                            de bello standardii</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="36r">Anno uerbi incarnati <date>m.c.xxxv</date></incipit>
                        <ab>Last printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Howlett 1886">Chronicles of Stephen, Henry II,
                                Richard I (Rolls) by R. Howlett: III p. lvi: 137</ref>. This is the only copy</ab>
                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="46r">defuncti sunt</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="46r">Explicit bellum standardii</rubric>






                    </msItem>





                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="46r" locusEnd="48v">



                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Cronica ab <name type="person">Adamo</name> ad <name type="person">Henricum V.</name>
                                imperatorem</title>
                        </head>



                        <rubric locus="46r">Incipit cronica ab <name type="person">Adam</name> usque ad <name
                                type="person">henricum</name></rubric>
                        <incipit><name type="person">Adam</name> c.xxx. annorum genuit <name type="person">seth</name>
                            cui superuixit dccc<abbr rend="superscript">tis</abbr></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="48v">posteritas uidebit</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="48v">Expliciunt cronica a principio mundi usque ad <name type="person"
                                >Henricum</name> imperatorem filium <name type="person">Henrici</name> qui anno v<abbr
                                rend="superscript">to</abbr> regni sui accepit <name type="person">Mathildem</name>
                            filiam <name type="person">Henricus</name> regis anglie in coniugium. Anno ab incarnatione
                            domini <date>m. c. et x</date></rubric>
                        <ab>Contains short notes of English affairs, especially of the northern sees</ab>


                    </msItem>




                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="48v" locusEnd="90r">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Simeon of Durham OSB</name>, <title>Epistola ad <name type="person"
                                    >Hugonem decanum Eboracensem</name> de archiepiscopis Eboracensium</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Simeonis</name> monachi ecclesiae S. Cuthberti Dunelmi
                                ad <name type="person">Hugonem</name> decanum Eboracensem de archiepiscopis
                                Eboraci</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab locus="48v">Ed. <ref type="bibl" target="Raine 1886">Raine, <hi rend="italic">Historians of
                                    the Church of York</hi> (Rolls) II xvii 252</ref>, principally from another MS. <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Twysden 1652">Twysden Scriptores, col. 75</ref>, gives our text</ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="50r" locusEnd="51v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Simeon of Durham OSB (attrib.)</name>, <title>De obsessione <name
                                    type="place">Dunelmi</name> et de probitate <name type="person">Ucthredi</name>
                                comitis et de comitibus qui ei succeserunt</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De obsessione <name type="place">Dunelmi</name> et de probitate <name type="person"
                                    >Uithredi</name> comitis</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab locus="50r">Arnold: <ref type="bibl" target="Arnold 1882">Symeon of Durham (Rolls) I
                                315</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="Twysden 1652">Twysden, col. 79</ref></ab>
                        <ab>Ends f. <locus>51v</locus></ab>


                    </msItem>




                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="52r" locusEnd="129v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Simeon of Durham OSB</name>, <title>Historia regum</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Historia sanctae et suavis memoriae <name type="person">Symeonis</name> monachi et
                                precentoris <name type="place">ecclesiae sancti Cuthberti Dunelmi</name> de regibus
                                Anglorum et Dacorum et creberrimis bellis et rapinis et incendiis eorum post obitum
                                venerabilis <name type="person">Bedae</name> presbiteri fere usque ad obitum <name
                                    type="person">Henrici</name> filii <name type="person">Willelmi</name> nothi</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The title (Incipit historia sancte et suauis etc.) is written on f. <locus>51v</locus> at
                            the bottom of col. 2. But f. <locus>52r</locus> sqq. are <handNote>in a different
                                hand</handNote>, with rubric in large letters at top</ab>
                        <rubric locus="52r">Incipit passio sanctorum <name type="person">Ethelberti</name> atque <name
                                type="person">Ethelredi</name> regie stirpis puerorum</rubric>
                        <ab>After four leaves <handNote>the hand settles down into one like that of no. 1</handNote>
                            which continues to f. <locus>76r</locus></ab>
                        <ab>f. <locus>59v</locus>, recto blank, is an insertion of cent. <date>xvi</date> with the
                            Prologus <name type="person">Rogeri de Houedon</name> in historiam suam (which imitates the
                            lost prologue of <name type="person">Symeon</name>)</ab>
                        <ab>At the top of f. <locus>60r</locus> is a <date>xvi</date>th cent. note</ab>
                        <ab> Historia <name type="person">Simeonis Dunelm</name>. monachi. sed desunt folia nonnulla.
                            debuerat posuisse immediate post titulum operis ante passionem <name type="person"
                                >Ethelberti</name> et <name type="person">Ethelredi</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>This is the only copy of the Historia Regum of <name type="person">Symeon</name>: last
                            printed by Arnold, <ref type="bibl" target="Arnold 1885">Symeon of Durham II (Rolls: for his
                                account of the MS. see p. x, etc.)</ref>. Parts of the text occur in a
                            <date>xii</date>th cent. MS. formerly Ashburnham, Appendix, no. 112 now <ref type="ms"
                                target="BNF692">Bibl. Nat. Nouv. acq. Lat. 692</ref>. A transcript of the C. C. C. MS.
                            is in <ref type="ms" target="CCC100">MS 100</ref>. 1</ab>
                        <ab>There are marginalia <handNote>in various hands</handNote>, notably one very tall one</ab>
                        <ab>There seems to be <handNote>a change of hand</handNote> at f. <locus>76r</locus> (<ref
                                type="bibl" target="Arnold 1885">Arnold</ref>, p. 95), Sequitur recapitulatio</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>The hand which follows, on f. <locus>77r</locus>, begins with a <decoNote>large
                                    red and green initial</decoNote>. It goes on for a long time</handNote>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="129v" locusEnd="132v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">John of Hexham OSA</name>, <title>Continuation of <name type="person"
                                    >Simeon of Durham OSB</name>'s Historia regum</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Historia <name type="author">Ioannis prioris Hagustaldensis</name> ecclesiae XXV
                                annorum</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab locus="131v" locusNew="129v">Printed by <ref type="bibl" target="Arnold 1885">Arnold, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Symeon of Durham</hi> II 284</ref></ab>
                        <ab>On <locus locusNew="132r">134r</locus> is <decoNote>a rude late (?) sketch of a
                                comet</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>On <locus locusNew="132v">134v</locus> intervene, in the text of <name type="author">John of
                                Hexham</name>, between pp. 296 and 297 of <ref type="bibl" target="Arnold 1885"
                                >Arnold</ref>'s ed., nos. 9 <supplied>(Carmen Serlonis)</supplied>, 9<abbr
                                rend="superscript">a</abbr>
                            <supplied>(Carmen de morte Sumerledi)</supplied>, 10 <supplied>(Ailred, Relatio de
                                standardo)</supplied></ab>
                        <ab>Another copy of 8 is in <ref type="ms" target="BNF692">BibliothËque Nationale Nouv. acq.
                                Lat. 692</ref> (see above on 7)</ab>





                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="9.1" locusStart="132v" locusEnd="133r">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Serlo of Fountains OCist</name>, <title>Descriptio de bello inter regem
                                    <name type="place">Scotiae</name> et barones <name type="place"
                                >Angliae</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Descriptio Serlonis monachi fratris <name type="person">Radulphi</name> abbatis de
                                Parcho de bello inter regem <name type="place">Scotiae</name> et barones <name
                                    type="place">Angliae</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="134v" locusNew="132v">Carmen Serlonis. <ref type="bibl" target="Twysden 1652"
                                >Twysden</ref>, col. 331. <ref type="bibl" target="Raine 1880">Raine, Lawrence of
                                Durham</ref>, p. 74</ab>

                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="9.2" locusStart="133r" locusEnd="133v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">William of Glasgow</name>, <title>Carmen de morte Sumerledi</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab locus="135r" locusNew="133r">Carmen de morte Sumerledi. <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Arnold 1885">Arnold</ref>, l. c. II 385. <ref type="bibl" target="Skene 1871"
                                >Skene, Fordun I</ref>, Appendix V <ref type="bibl" target="Raine 1880">Raine</ref>, l.
                            c. p. 78</ab>




                    </msItem>




                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="134r" locusEnd="138r">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Aelred of Rievaulx OCist</name>, <title>Relatio de standardo</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Descriptio venerabilis viri <name type="author">Aetheldredi abbatis Rievallis</name>
                                de bello inter regem <name type="place">Scotiae</name> et barones <name type="place"
                                    >Angliae</name> apud <name type="place">Standardum juxta Alvertoniam</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><name type="author">Aethelred</name> de bello Standardi, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Howlett 1885">Chronicles of Stephen etc. II, see p. lviii</ref>. <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Skene 1871">Skene, Fordun I, Appendix IV 136</ref></ab>
                        <ab>Begins with a <decoNote>large red and green initial</decoNote>. On ff. <locus
                                locusNew="134v">136v</locus>, <locus locusNew="135r">137r</locus> are <decoNote>two
                                marginal drawings of the Standard</decoNote>: the first is late (cent.
                                <origDate>xvi?</origDate>), the other original. These or similar ones have been often
                            reproduced</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus locusNew="138r">140r</locus> the text of <supplied>item</supplied> 8 is
                            resumed. <ref type="bibl" target="Arnold 1885">Arnold p. 297</ref></ab>

                        <rubric locusNew="138r">Explicit descriptio <name type="author">Aethelredi
                            abbatis</name></rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="138r">Incipit descriptio predicti <name type="person">prioris
                                haugustaldensis</name> ecclesie</rubric>
                        <ab>Ends f. <locus locusNew="147r">149r</locus></ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="147r" locusEnd="149v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Aelred of Rievaulx OCist</name>, <title>Miraculum de quadam sanctimonali
                                de <name type="place">Watton</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Quoddam miraculum mirabile descriptum a viro venerabili <name type="person"
                                    >Aethelredo</name> abbate Rievall. de quadam sanctimoniali femina de <name
                                    type="place">Wattun</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Twysden 1652">Twysden, col. 415</ref>. <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Migne 195">Migne P. L. CXCV 789</ref></ab>
                        <ab locus="149r" locusNew="149v">At end a <origDate>xvi</origDate>th cent. note referring to the
                            Life of St Elizabeth in <ref type="ms" target="CCC138">MS 138</ref>
                            <supplied>item</supplied> 10</ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="150r" locusEnd="152v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Stephen of Whitby OSB</name>, <title>Historia fundationis abbatiae <name
                                    type="place">Sanctae Mariae Eboracensis</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Quo modo et a quibus cenobium <name type="place">Sanctae Mariae Eboraci</name>
                                fundatum sit, et quantas invidorum perturbationes impulsum sustinuerat, sed Dei
                                protegente gratia magis ac magis auctum et multiplicatum fuerat; autore <name
                                    type="author">Stephano</name> ejusdem cenobii abbate</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Dugdale et al 1846c">Monasticon III 544</ref></ab>
                        <ab locus="152r" locusNew="150r">Begins with <decoNote>a green initial</decoNote>. These three
                            leaves are in <handNote>a fresh hand, upright and regular</handNote></ab>


                    </msItem>




                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="152v" locusEnd="152v">


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Quo modo Funtanense cenobium sumpsit exordium</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="154v" locusNew="152v">is but a short paragraph prefatory to <supplied>item</supplied>
                            14</ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="153r" locusEnd="158r">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Thurstan archbishop of York</name>, <title>Epistola de egressu
                                monachorum Fontanensium</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistola <name type="author">Thurstini archiepiscopi Eboraci</name> ad <name
                                    type="person">Wilhelmum archiepiscopum Cantuariae</name> de cenobio <name
                                    type="place">Sanctae Mariae Eboraci</name> et observantia regulae Sancti Benedicti
                                in eo</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="155r" locusNew="153r">See <ref type="bibl" target="Walbran 1863">Memorials of the
                                Abbey of St Mary of Fountains, ed. Walbran</ref>, Surtees Society 1863</ab>
                        <ab><handNote>The script is probably the same as that of <supplied>item</supplied> 11</handNote>
                            etc.</ab>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="158r" locusEnd="160r">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">William of Malmesbury OSB</name>, <title>Gesta regum Anglorum
                                (excerpt)</title></head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De vita et conversatione <name type="person">Gereberti</name> papae</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="160r" locusNew="158r">From <ref type="bibl" target="Stubbs 1887">William of
                                Malmesbury Gesta Regum I 193-201 fallere</ref></ab>


                    </msItem>




                    <msItem n="16" locusStart="160r" locusEnd="161v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">William of Malmesbury OSB</name>, <title>Gesta regum Anglorum
                                (excerpt)</title></head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Visio <name type="author">Karoli</name> imperatoris</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="162r" locusNew="160r">
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Stubbs 1887">ibid. I 112</ref>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="17" locusStart="161r" locusEnd="161r">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">William of Malmesbury OSB</name>, <title>Gesta regum Anglorum
                                (excerpt)</title></head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Visio <name type="author">S. Maurilii</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="161r">
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Stubbs 1889">ibid. II 327</ref>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>




                    <msItem n="18" locusStart="161r" locusEnd="161v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">William of Malmesbury OSB</name>, <title>Gesta regum Anglorum
                                (excerpt)</title></head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De annulo statuae commendato</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="163r" locusNew="161r">
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Stubbs 1887">ibid. I 256</ref>
                        </ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="19" locusStart="162r" locusEnd="165r">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Geffrei Gaimar</name>, <title>Estoire des Engleis
                            (excerpt)</title></head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Narratio de uxore <name type="person">Ernulfi</name> ab <name type="person"
                                    >Aella</name> rege Deirorum violata</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Hardy and Martin 1888">Gaimar (Rolls) I 328</ref>; also
                            in the <ref type="bibl" target="Petrie 1848">Notes to Gaimar, Monumenta I 795</ref> and in
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Wright 1850b">Wright's Caxton Society edition</ref></ab>
                        <ab>On a fresh quire and <handNote>in a large regular hand</handNote></ab>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="20" locusStart="165r" locusEnd="165v">



                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De eo quod <name type="place">Eboracensis</name> ecclesia nullum dominium super
                                Scotos habere debet</title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locus="167r" locusNew="165r">De <name type="place">Eboracensi</name> ecclesie primatu
                            super scottos nulla est auctoritas</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="165v">possessiones ipsa in suum solum optinet</explicit>


                    </msItem>



                    <msItem n="21" locusStart="165v" locusEnd="165v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Visio cuiusdam clerici de gloria <name type="person">regis Malcolmi</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Visio cujusdam clerici de gloria regis <name type="person">Malcolmi</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="167v" locusNew="165v">Visio <name type="person">Malcolmi</name> cui ad singula
                            interrogata super statu suo in hunc sensum respondit</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="165v">Cur sic care taces. pro me loquitur me(a) uita</incipit>
                        <ab>14 lines ending</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="165v">quidque tuis mandans perpetuo ualeant</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="165v">Rex uero <name type="person">Malcolmus</name> summe ingenuitatis
                            titulus ueluti surculus ex dulcissima abscisus arbore</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="165v">lucidissima in celestes thesauros intulerunt mella</explicit>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Skene 1871">Skene, Fordun I, Appendix VI</ref>, from a copy
                            furnished by Mr <name type="person">Henry Bradshaw</name>: <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Raine 1880">Raine, l. c. p. 81</ref></ab>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="22" locusStart="166r" locusEnd="176v">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Nennius (attrib.)</name>, <title>Historia
                            Brittonum</title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Eulogium brevissimum <name type="place">Britanniae</name> insulae quod <name
                                    type="person">Ninnius</name>
                                <name type="person">Elvodugi</name> discipulus congregavit</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>A new volume, <layout>double columns of 35 lines</layout>, <handNote>hand very slightly
                                sloping</handNote>, <decoNote>plain red initials</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>The first leaf was originally blank</ab>
                        <ab>On the recto is a paragraph in <handNote>a small hand of cent. <date>xiii
                                early</date></handNote>, not beginning at the top of the page</ab>
                        <ab locus="168r" locusNew="166r">Gualenses nichilominus insistebant ius suum sibi concedi
                            postulantes</ab>
                        <ab>Quid enim inquiunt o rex formidas et tunicas illas ferreas quas eminus cernis nimium
                            expauescis. Nobis certe sunt latera ferrea pectus ereum mens timoris uacua quorum nec pedes
                            fugam nec unquam uulnus terga sensere. quid gallis apud <name type="place">cliderhou</name>
                            profuere lorice. Numquid non inermes isti ut dicunt illos et loricas proicere et negligere
                            et scuta relinquere coegerunt. Uideat igitur o rex prudentia uestra quale sit in his habere
                            fiduciam que in necessitate magis sunt oneri quam consolationi. Nos apud <name type="place"
                                >cliderhou</name> de loricatis uictoriam reportauimus. Nos hodie et istos anime uirtute
                            pro scuto utentes lanceis prosternemus. Hoc bellum factum est inter anglos et pictos et
                            scottos apud <name type="place">cliderhou</name>
                            <date>feria vi die vii [xii?] ante natiuitate sancti Johannis Baptistae anno predicto id est
                                m. c. xxx vii<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr></date></ab>
                        <ab>Bellum apud <name type="place">Cliderhou</name> ubi multi nobiles et ignobiles
                            perierunt</ab>
                        <ab>This is a quotation from <name type="author">Aelred</name> de Bello Standardi (<ref
                                type="bibl" target="Howlett 1885">Chronicles of Stephen etc. II, p. 190</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus locusNew="166v">168v</locus> are various items enumerated by <name
                                type="person">Mommsen</name> in his prolegomena to <name type="person">Nennius</name>,
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Mommsen 1898">Mon. Germ. Hist. XIII 1 (Chronica Minora III 1),
                                p. 125</ref></ab>
                        <ab>On the margin</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="166v">Incipit apologia. <name type="author">Nemnii</name> britonum
                            historiografi</ab>
                        <ab>and</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="166v">Incipit hystori[c]a ortografia mundi</ab>
                        <ab>(not as <ref type="bibl" target="Mommsen 1898">Mommsen</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>Col. 1.</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="166v">Incipit eulogium breuissimum <name type="place">brittannie
                            insule</name>. quod <name type="person">Ninnius</name>
                            <name type="person">eluodugi</name> discipulus congregauit</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="166v">Ego <name type="person">Ninnius</name>
                            <name type="person">eluodugi</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="166v">Cedo illi qui plus nouerit in ista pericia satis quam ego</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="166v">Explicit eulogium</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="166v">Item eiusdem quod scribi debet in fine libri</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="166v">De malis et peruersis naturis gen-ti-um</rubric>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Mommsen 1898">Chronica Minora II 389</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>Inuidia iudeorum</ab>
                        <ab>This is written in <layout>two columns</layout>, <handNote>with additions by the large hand
                                which annotates the MS. throughout and also by a neater and smaller hand</handNote></ab>
                        <ab><handNote>The original hand</handNote> goes down to</ab>
                        <ab>Ira brittonum</ab>
                        <ab>then</ab>
                        <ab>De bonis naturis gentium</ab>
                        <ab>Prudencia hebreorum to Argutia hispanorum</ab>

                        <ab><handNote>The large hand</handNote> adds to col. 1</ab>
                        <ab>Libido sueuorum</ab>
                        <ab>Duricia (uel superbia above) pictauorum <hi rend="footnote">The original hand already had
                                Duricia pictorum</hi></ab>

                        <ab>It adds to col. 2</ab>
                        <ab>A line erased</ab>
                        <ab>Communio normannorum</ab>
                        <ab>Grecus irascitur ante causam</ab>
                        <ab>Francus in causa</ab>
                        <ab>Romanus propter causam</ab>
                        <ab>Francus fortis</ab>
                        <ab>Romanus grauis</ab>
                        <ab>Affer semper uersipellis</ab>
                        <ab>The second (smaller) hand adds to the Vices</ab>
                        <ab>Spurcicia sclauorum</ab>
                        <ab>Rapacitas normannorum</ab>
                        <ab>Normanni nimis sunt animosi</ab>
                        <ab>The large hand adds to the Virtues</ab>
                        <ab>Sollercia egiptiorum</ab>
                        <ab>Col. 2. At top, three lines erased, perhaps written by the large hand</ab>
                        <ab>Despicientes deum viii<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> ab (hole in vellum) bates
                            fuerunt</ab>
                        <ab><name type="person">Riccardus</name> prior primus abbas de fontibus [<date>1132</date>]</ab>
                        <ab><name type="person">Riccardus</name> sacrista se(cundus) abbas de fontibus
                                [<date>1139</date>]</ab>
                        <ab>Lower down are the additions to the list of Virtues and Vices</ab>
                        <ab>Then in the original hand the two poems Adiutor benignus, and Fornifer</ab>
                        <rubric locus="169r" locusNew="167r">Sancti spiritus assit nobis gratia. Incipit Res gesta a
                                <name type="author">Nennio</name> sapiente composita</rubric>
                        <ab>With marginal and interlinear additions in several hands including the large hand and the
                            hand of f. <locus locusNew="166v">168v</locus></ab>
                        <ab>Ends</ab>

                        <explicit locus="178v" locusNew="176v">finibus cosmi</explicit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Mommsen 1898">Mommsen</ref>, p. 218): the section ending thus is
                            placed by several other MSS. as well as this after that ending Luchechach (<ref type="bibl"
                                target="Mommsen 1898">Mommsen</ref>, p. 219) which forms the end of M.'s text</ab>


                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="23" locusStart="176v" locusEnd="179r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Caradog of Llancarfan</name>, <title>Vita Sancti Gildae</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Res gestae a <name type="person">Nennio</name> sapiente compositae, Vita sanctissimi
                                atque doctissimi viri <name type="person">Gildas</name> autore <name type="author"
                                    >Caradoco Nancarbanensi</name></title>
                        </head>




                        <ab locus="178v" locusNew="176v"> Vita <name type="person">Gildae</name>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><ref type="bibl" target="Mommsen 1898">Mommsen</ref>, p. 107</ab>
                        <ab>Capitula and rubric in the hand of f. <locus locusNew="166v">168v</locus></ab>
                        <ab>Ends <locus locusNew="179r">181r</locus></ab>
                        <ab>In another rough hand follow</ab>
                        <ab>(a) Col. 1. The poem Fornifer</ab>
                        <ab>(b) Col. 2. On the translation of <name type="person">St Benedict</name> to <name
                                type="place">Fleury</name></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="179v">Circa hec tempora cum in castro cassino</incipit>
                        <ab>(c) (De naturis gentium)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="179v">Inuidia iudeorum</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="179v">Duritia uel superbia pictauorum</explicit>
                        <ab>This is copied in a confused order</ab>
                        <ab>In the lower margin the name <name type="person">Aelsi</name></ab>
                        <ab>On the verso and last leaf are many <date>xv</date>th cent. scribbles and a few earlier</ab>
                        <ab>On the Kings of <name type="place">England</name></ab>


                        <ab>On the same, in verse: Dux Normannorum <name type="person">Willelmus</name> vi validorum (to
                                <name type="person">Edward III</name>)</ab>
                        <ab><name type="person">Willelmus</name> rufus. versus</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <lg>
                                <l>Visibus humanis aulas ornatas inanis</l>
                                <l>fecit fundare propter sua festa parare</l>
                                <l>aulam maiorem construxit <name type="place">Londoniarum</name></l>
                                <l>orbis terrarum non optinet utiliorem</l>
                                <l>Iudicibus legis ac ad conuiuia regis</l>
                                <l>regnum regnorum flos est domus illa domorum</l>
                            </lg>
                        </ab>


                        <ab>(Referring to <name type="place">Westminster Hall</name>)</ab>
                        <ab>Further notes on English Kings</ab>
                        <ab>Drawings of two bearded men: one labelled Tome T.. ywalle</ab>
                        <ab>A badly written name <name type="person">Arthur Harvy(?)</name></ab>

                    </msItem>





                </msContents>










                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, CF 2nd</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC June 2007</p>
                            <p>remarks: </p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>


            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
