<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC197A">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>197A</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>M. 14</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>152</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">The Trial of Joan of Arc. The Westminster Chronicle</head>
                <head type="James">Processus Johannae la Pucelle. Chronicon Westmonasteriense</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper and vellum</material>, various sizes: vellum, <measureGrp
                        type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">292</height>
                        <width unit="mm">240</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">11.3 x 8.5</measureGrp>, paper sometimes smaller. Cent.
                        <origDate>xvi and xv</origDate>.</p>
                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iv + pp. a-d + 1-64 + 67-68 + 65-66 + 69-72 + 72a-73a + 73-110 + 110a-111a +
                        111-243 + ff. v-vi</foliation>.</p>



                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="enm frm eng">Latin, Anglo-Norman, Middle English and
                        English.</textLang>



                    <label>Contents</label>
                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="a" locusEnd="d">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Epistle of <name type="author">King Alfred</name> to <name type="person">Bishop
                                    Werfrith</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>The epistle of <name type="author">king Ælfred</name> to <name type="person">Bishop
                                    Werfrith</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locusNew="a">The Epistle of <name type="author">King Alfred</name> to <name
                                type="person">Werfrithus</name> (erased), bishop of (Worcester)</rubric>
                        <ab>In English: on <extent>2 ff.</extent> of <material>paper</material></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="1" locusEnd="84">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The trial of <name type="person">Joan of Arc</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Processus contra <name type="person">Iohannam dictam le Puzel</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <extent>42 ff.</extent>
                            <origDate>xvi</origDate>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="1">Processus contra <name type="person">Johannam dictam le Puzel</name></rubric>
                        <ab>Documents in Latin and French with some English renderings</ab>
                        <ab locus="35">Extract from Hall's Chronicle</ab>
                        <ab locus="37">Description and <decoNote>figure of a Jewish coin</decoNote> figured in <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Beza 1565">Beza's N. T.</ref><hi rend="footnote">Apparently the coin
                                was given to <name type="person">Parker</name> by <name type="person">Ambr.
                                    Blaurer</name></hi></ab>
                        <rubric locus="39">Processus pro <name type="person">Joanna galla dicta le
                            Puzell</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="39">De puella quadam <name type="person">Joanna</name> nuncupata que
                            temporibus nostris preter solitum feminis</incipit>
                        <ab>Ends p. <locus>78</locus>: signed <q>
                                <name type="person">Robertus Cybole</name>
                            </q></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="78">
                            <q>Exscriptum ex originali ipsius authoris qui singulas paginas totius libri manu sua et
                                nomine sic subscripserat <name type="person">R. C.</name> R. C.</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>This is <name type="person">Robert Ciboule</name> who took part in the process of
                            rehabilitation of <name type="person">Joan of Arc</name> in <date>1437</date>. See <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Quicherat 1841-9">Quicherat, Procés, 1841-9</ref>, who has published
                            extracts</ab>
                        <ab locus="79">Extract</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="79">ex historia quadam veteri ubi tractatur de regibus <name type="person"
                                >Richardi 2'</name> et <name type="person">Hen. 4'</name>. et est in supplemento
                            Chronice <name type="person">Ranulphi</name> mutuat. a <name type="person">M<abbr
                                    rend="superscript">ro</abbr> Lambert</name>, et est liber <name type="person">L.
                                Nowel</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="79">In primordio huius regis (<name type="person">Henrici quarti</name>)
                            excrescebat nimis insolentia indumentorum</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="79">nos percutere non desinet</explicit>
                        <ab>pp. <locus>80</locus>-<locus>84</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="85" locusEnd="93">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Articuli venerabilis domini <name type="author">Ricardi Scrope</name> archiepiscopi
                                Eboracensis contra <name type="person">Henricum quartum</name> intrusorem regni <name
                                    type="place">Angliae</name> A. D. <date>1399</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Articuli venerabilis domini <name type="author">Ricardi Scrope</name> archiepiscopi
                                Eboracensis contra <name type="person">Henricum quartum</name> intrusorem regni <name
                                    type="place">Angliae</name> A. D. <date>1399</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="85">Articuli venerabilis domini <name type="author">Ricardi. Scrope</name>
                            etc.</rubric>
                        <ab>Ed. by <ref type="bibl" target="Wharton 1691b">Wharton, <hi rend="italic">Anglia Sacra</hi>
                                II 362</ref> from this MS</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="93" locusEnd="94">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Causa quare decollatus est archiepiscopus <name type="person">Ricardus
                                Scrope</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Causa quare decollatus est archiepiscopus <name type="person">Ricardus
                                Scrope</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="85" locusNew="93">Hec fuerunt cause quare decollatus est Archiepiscopus <name
                                type="person">Ricardus Scrope</name></rubric>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wharton 1691b">Wharton, <hi rend="italic">Anglia Sacra</hi> II p.
                                369</ref>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="94" locusEnd="98">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Martyrdom of <name type="person">Richard Scrope</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Martirium praedicti <name type="person">Ricardi archiepiscopi</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="94">Hic incipit martirium predicti <name type="person">Ricardi
                                Archiepiscopi</name></rubric>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wharton 1691b">Wharton, <hi rend="italic">Anglia Sacra</hi> II p.
                                369</ref>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="96">Apparition of the Archbishop to <name type="person">John Sibson</name>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wharton 1691b">(p. 371)</ref></ab>
                        <ab locus="97">Penance of the King <ref type="bibl" target="Wharton 1691b">(p. 371)</ref></ab>
                        <ab locus="98">Story how <name type="person">Henry IV</name>'s body was thrown into the sea <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Wharton 1691b">(p. 372</ref></ab>
                        <ab>Ending</ab>
                        <explicit locus="98">Deus omnipotens est testis et iudex quod ego <name type="author">Clemens
                                Maydestone</name> vidi virum illum et audiui ipsum iurantem patri meo <name
                                type="person">Thome Maydestone</name> omnia predicta fore vera</explicit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="99" locusEnd="108">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Depositio <name type="person">regis Ricardi</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Depositio <name type="person">regis Ricardi</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locusNew="101">(With sermon of <name type="person">Archbishop Arundel</name> on p.
                                <locus>101</locus>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="104">Ending with <name type="person">Henry</name>'s revocation of allegiance to
                                <name type="person">Richard</name>, in English</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <supplied>pp. <locus>107</locus>-<locus>108</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="109" locusEnd="213">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Westminster Chronicle</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Continuatio chronici <name type="person">Ranulphi</name> per <name type="author"
                                    >Iohannem Malverne</name>, ab anno Domini <date>1236</date>. ad annum
                                    <date>1394</date></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Ad annum <date>1346</date>, <q>Hic revera <name type="person">Ranulphus monachus
                                        Cestr.</name> suas cronicas terminavit: Post hunc scripsit quidam monachus
                                    Wigorn. <name type="author">Iohannes Malvern</name></q>. Saepe concordat haec
                                continuatio cum <name type="person">Thoma de Walsingham</name> et autore anonymo
                                historiae <name type="person">Ricardi II</name>. a <name type="person">Cl. Hearne</name>
                                editae, multa tamen habet quae in aliis frustra quaeres, digna certe quae historicis
                                nostris impressis addatur</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab><material>Paper</material>, <layout>54 lines to a page</layout>: cent. <origDate>xiv late or
                                xv early</origDate>, <handNote>in a pretty hand</handNote>. The quires have been of 16
                            leaves</ab>
                        <ab locus="109">Names of the children of <name type="person">Edward III</name>. Distich on Kings
                            of <name type="place">England</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="109"><name type="person">Edward I</name> to the Abbot and Convent of <name
                                type="place">Westminster</name>, reciting the Scotch agreement (<name type="place"
                                >Norham</name>
                            <date>1291</date>, <ref type="bibl" target="Rymer 1705">Rymer, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Foedera</hi> II 529</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="110">Accounts, in French</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="111">
                            <date>1326</date>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="111"><name type="person">Edwardus tercius</name> filius <name type="person">E.
                                ij</name> post conquestum adolescens quindecim circiter annorum uiuente adhuc patre
                            suo</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Lumby 1882">Polychronicon, Rolls ed. VIII, p. 324</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab>Ends in <date>1394</date> with the death of the <name type="person">Countess of
                            Derby</name></ab>
                        <explicit locus="210">Istis quoque duabus sororibus hereditas duorum comitatuum <name
                                type="place">herefordie</name> videlicet et <name type="place">Northampton</name> inter
                            se spectabat equaliter diuidenda</explicit>
                        <ab>For this see Appendix I to the Polychronicon (<ref type="bibl" target="Lumby 1882">VIII, 324
                                sqq., 355-406</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="Lumby 1886">IX, Introduction and pp.
                                1-283</ref>). In these the whole text is printed. For the greater part of it this MS. is
                            the unique authority. The attribution to a monk of <name type="place">Worcester</name> is
                            incorrect. The Dean of Westminster has shown that the writer was a <name type="place"
                                >Westminster</name> monk (<ref type="bibl" target="Armitage Robinson 1907">Proceedings
                                of the British Academy 1907</ref>) </ab>
                        <ab>pp. <locus>211</locus>-<locus>213</locus> blank</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="214" locusEnd="244">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Acts of parliament <date>1 Henry VI</date> and state of affairs during his
                                minority</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Acts of parliament I <name type="person">Henrici VI</name>. and state of affairs
                                during his minority</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab><handNote>Current hand</handNote>, <layout>44 lines to a full page</layout></ab>
                        <rubric locus="214">Acta habita in parliamento tento die lune proxima ante festum S. Martini
                                <date>anno regno regis henrici vi<abbr rend="superscript">ti</abbr>
                            primo</date></rubric>
                        <ab>In Latin, French and English</ab>
                        <ab>The last item is</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="239">Acta apud <name type="place">Cantuariam</name>
                            <date>eodem anno viii<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr></date></rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="243">ending p. <locus>243</locus></ab>
                        <ab>p. <locus>244</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 20.11.07</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
