<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC219">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>219</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Lib. ab Al. 32</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>


                <head type="CCC">Gesta Alexandri</head>

                <head type="James">Gesta Alexandri</head>


                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">243</height>
                        <width unit="mm">170</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">9.5 x 6.2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 70</extent>, <layout>29
                        lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xii</origDate>, <quote>seculo <origDate>xvi</origDate>
                        scriptus</quote>, <handNote>in a very good hand</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation> 1<num>8</num> (wants 1, 2) 2<num>8</num>-9<num>8</num></collation>.</p>

                <p><label>2 fo.:</label>
                    <secFol>Futuri</secFol>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">The covers are lined with bits of a very large printed Psalter, and the
                    flyleaves <supplied>(ff. <locus>ir</locus>-<locus>iv</locus>,
                        <locus>xr</locus>-<locus>xv</locus>)</supplied> are fragments of a MS. service-book
                        (<origDate>xv</origDate>) with music on four-line stave.
                    <!--This service book is very similar to one that is used in other Corpus manuscripts--></p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-v + 1-70 + vi-x</foliation>.</p>



                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="64r">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Gesta <name type="person">Alexandri</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Gesta <name type="person">Alexandri</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Historia regis Macedonum <name type="person">Philippi</name>, filiique ejus <name
                                    type="person">Alexandri magni</name>, excerpta de libris <name type="person"
                                    >Pompeii</name>
                                <name type="person">Trogi</name>
                                <name type="person">Orosii</name>
                                <name type="person">Iosephi</name>
                                <name type="person">Ieronimi</name>
                                <name type="person">Solini</name>
                                <name type="person">Augustini</name>
                                <name type="person">Bedae</name> et <name type="person">Ysodori</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <rubric locus="1r"><name type="place">Macedonia</name> ante a nomine emathionis uel emathii
                            Regis cuius prima</rubric>

                        <incipit locus="1r">Uirtutis experimenta</incipit>

                        <ab>
                            <handNote>Names of authorities are in red in the margin</handNote>
                        </ab>


                        <ab locus="12v" locusNew="11v">Liber II</ab>



                        <ab locus="22v"><supplied>Liber</supplied> III</ab>



                        <ab locus="27v" locusNew="37v"><supplied>Liber</supplied> IV</ab>


                        <ab>Ends</ab>

                        <explicit locus="64r">Denique hec solutio belli macedonici et hic finis fuit perindeque qui
                            belli finis idem et libri sit</explicit>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="64r" locusEnd="70r">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Collatio <name type="person">Alexandri</name> cum <name type="person">Dindimo</name>
                                per Litteras Facta (Collatio I)</title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Epistolae <name type="person">Alexandri</name> ad <name type="person">Dindimum</name>
                                regem Bragmanorum, et <name type="person">Dindimi</name> ad <name type="person"
                                    >Alexandrum</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="64r">Incipit epistole <name type="person">Alexandri</name> ad <name type="person"
                                >dindium</name> regem bragmannorum et <name type="person">dindimi</name> ad <name
                                type="person">Alexandrum</name>. <name type="person">Alexander</name></rubric>

                        <incipit locusNew="64r">Sepius ad aures meas</incipit>

                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="70r">aut in <name type="place">indie</name> quod a meliore
                            prestantur</explicit>

                        <ab>See <ref type="bibl" target="Ward 1883">Ward, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Romances</hi> I
                                108</ref></ab>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>70v</locus> a note</ab>

                        <ab locusNew="70v"><q>xx<abbr rend="superscript">ti</abbr> acr. <abbr>dnic</abbr> terre in <name
                                    type="place">urstwik</name> perten. terr. nuper duce Suff. att intt. milonis brigge
                                per annum S. xiii<abbr rend="superscript">s</abbr> iiij<abbr rend="superscript"
                                >d</abbr></q>. <name type="place">Urswick</name> is in <name type="place"
                                >Lancashire</name></ab>
                    </msItem>


                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 25.01.2007</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
