<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC242">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>242</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Lib. ab Al. 37</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>vac.</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">William Buckmaster, Collection of Documents Relating to the University of Cambridge.
                    Catalogue of English Saints and Kings</head>
                <head type="James">Will. Buckmaster's Collections</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">200</height>
                        <width unit="mm">147</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">7.8 x 5.8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 88</extent>, <layout>22
                        etc. lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate>, <handNote>in various fairly good
                        hands</handNote>.</p>


                <p function="Provenance">Given by <name type="person">Dr J. Jegon</name>, Master. On f.
                        <locus>ir</locus>: Liber <name type="person">Ricardi Ramsey</name> ex dono <name type="person"
                        >W. bidforde</name>. Also: Statutum <date>xxi<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> anno R. Henr.
                        octavi</date> viz.: Charges for probacion of willes. Mortmaines. On f. <locus>iir</locus>: This
                    booke was given me att <name type="place">sowthwell</name> by one <name type="person">Mr Lee</name>
                    officiall to the Archdeacon of Nottingham <date>Martii i<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr>
                        1592</date> Eliz. 35°. <name type="person">J. Jegon</name>.</p>


                <p function="Additions">Flyleaves <supplied>(ff. <locus>ar</locus>-<locus>av</locus>,
                            <locus>br</locus>-<locus>bv</locus>)</supplied> of vellum from a MS. (scholastic theology)
                    of cent. <origDate>xiv</origDate>.</p>
                <p function="Additions">On f. <locus>ivv</locus> and f. <locus>1r</locus> notes.</p>
                <p function="Additions" rend="afterContents">The pads of the covers are made of a late paper
                    manuscript.</p>
                <p function="Research" rend="afterContents">In some early lists (see Introduction) this book is ascribed
                    to <name type="person">Cuthbert Tunstall</name>, Bishop of Durham.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-c + i-iv + 1-88 + d-f</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin, English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1v" locusEnd="71v">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">William Buckmaster</name>, <title>Collection of documents
                                relating to Cambridge University</title></head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Plurimae orationes coram senatu habitae; — literae <name type="author">Henrici
                                    VIII</name>. ad academiam, et determinatio academiae de matrimonio ejus cum <name
                                    type="person">regina Katerina</name>; — excerpta ex chartis regiis; — modus
                                procedendi in curiis civilibus; — historiola de fundatione academiae,
                                &amp;c.</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locusNew="1v">Receipt of <name type="person">Bishop Tunstall</name> for <name type="person"
                                >Chrysostom</name> on I Cor. from the University, <date>3 June 1530</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="2r">Speech of <name type="author">Buckmaster</name> giving notice that letters were
                            to be sent to the Chancellor and others at the opening of Parliament</ab>
                        <ab locus="2v">Notes of such letters being sent in <date>1529</date> and <date>1533</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="2v">Note of nomination of proctors, <date>1530</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="3r">Latin speeches (and a few in English) by <name type="author">Buckmaster</name> in
                            Congregation</ab>
                        <ab locus="11v">The king to the University, <date>16 May 1529</date>, in the matter of the
                            divorce (<ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, Documents</ref>, p. 19)</ab>
                        <ab locus="12r">Proceedings and answer of the University</ab>
                        <ab locus="15r">Case of <name type="person">Dakers</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="16v">List of Bishops, <date>1527-1530</date>, <date>1534</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="17r">Speech about the Cista de Bowcer</ab>
                        <ab locus="17v">Order to appoint a commission to examine heretical books, <date>4 May
                                1530</date>. Names of commissioners (<ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, p.
                                26</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="19r">Speeches and proceedings in Congregation (<date>1537</date> etc.)</ab>
                        <ab locus="25r">Address to the Senate (printed in <ref type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb,
                                Documents, p. 15</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="28r"><name type="author">Dr Fox</name> to <name type="person">Buckmaster</name> (<ref
                                type="bibl" target="Lamb 1838">Lamb, p. 14</ref>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="28v">Speech on <date>S. Luke's Day 1530</date> on resigning office</ab>
                        <ab locus="30r">Bulls and Charters relating to the University</ab>
                        <ab locus="35r">Note of proceedings between University and Town, <date>24 July 1534</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="35v">Forms of Citations etc. and legal notes</ab>
                        <ab locus="53r">Note of privileges of the Universities</ab>
                        <ab locus="54r">Historiola of <name type="author">Cantilupe</name>, neatly written</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="54r">Anno a mundi creacione 4321</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="63r">satis clare habentur</explicit>
                        <ab locus="63r">Notes of British history</ab>
                        <ab locus="63v">The riot in <date>4 Richard II</date> (see <ref type="ms" target="CGC249">Gonv.
                                and Caius 249</ref>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="63v">Memorandum quod die sabbati</incipit>
                        <ab locus="65v">Notes of British history</ab>
                        <rubric locus="67r">The Vepers in Dyvynytie</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="67v">The commencemente in Dyvynytie</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="69r">The Vepers in arte</rubric>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied>ff. <locus>70r</locus>-<locus>71v</locus> blank</supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="72r" locusEnd="88v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Catalogue of English saints and kings</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Catalogus sanctorum qui in <name type="place">Anglia</name> requiescunt; — catalogus
                                amnium et fluminum in <name type="place">Anglia</name>; — catalogus regum Britonum et
                                Saxonum, &amp;c.</title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locus="72r">He sunt notaciones de sanctis qui in Anglica patria requiescunt. <name
                                type="person">Sanctus Albanus</name> martyr iuxta locum que vocatur <name type="place"
                                >wetlingacester</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="73v">sanctaque <name type="person">morwenna</name> Abbatissa in loco qui
                            dicitur <name type="place">Rumesige</name> prope <name type="place">amnem
                            Taerstan</name></explicit>
                        <ab>Cf. <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1889">Liebermann, <hi rend="italic">Heiligen
                                    Englands</hi>, p. 10</ref></ab>
                        <rubric locus="74r">Amnes ac flumina in <name type="place">Anglia</name></rubric>
                        <rubric locus="75v">Catalogus Regum</rubric>
                        <ab>(<name type="person">Cerdic</name> — <name type="person">Henry 8</name>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="76v">Lists of Saxon kings</ab>
                        <ab>Ending f. <locus>79r</locus></ab>
                        <ab>ff. <locus>79v</locus>-<locus>86r</locus> blank</ab>
                        <ab locus="86v">List of Proctors and Vice-Chancellors, <date>1511</date>-<date>1545</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="88r">Sums of money in the various chests, <date>1532</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="88v">Notes of admissions to degrees (?) in the years
                                <date>1528</date>-<date>1544</date>. Many names of monks occur</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="br">On the last flyleaf: <name type="person">M. Besyll</name>, <name type="person"
                                >M. Gosnell</name>, <name type="person">M. Pulley</name>, <name type="person">M.
                                Swayne</name>, <name type="person">M. Weste</name>, <name type="person">M.
                            Stokes</name></ab>

                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 15/4/08</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
