<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>

                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC026">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>26</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>C. 9</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>30</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Matthew Paris OSB, Chronica maiora I</head>

                <head type="James">Matthaei Paris Chronica Maiora I</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">260</height>
                        <width unit="mm">195</width>
                    </measureGrp>
                    <measureGrp type="James">14.2 x 9.6</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 2 + 6 + 140 + 2 + 1</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 56 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num> | A<num>6(?)</num> | I<num>10</num> (+ 3 half-leaves after 7)
                            II<num>10</num> (+ 3 half-leaves after 8) III<num>12</num> IV<num>10</num>-VI<num>10</num>
                            VII<num>12</num> (2 canc.) VIII<num>8</num> IX<num>10</num> X<num>8</num> XI<num>10</num> (5
                        canc.) XII<num>13</num> XIII<num>14</num> (+ 2 leaves after 2, and 1 at the end) | B<num>2</num>
                        | 1 flyleaf</collation>.</p>


                <p function="Provenance">Written at <name type="place">St Albans</name>, and presented to the convent by
                        <name type="author">Matthew Paris</name>.</p>

                <p>MS 26 contains the first part of the Chronica Maiora S. Albani of <name type="author">Matthew
                        Paris</name>, from the Creation to the end of the year <date>1188</date>.</p>

                <p function="Research">The full text of the Chronica Maiora contained in volumes 26, <ref type="ms"
                        target="CCC016I">16I</ref> and <ref type="ms" target="CCC016II">16II</ref> was edited in the
                        <ref type="bibl" target="Luard 1872">Rolls Series by Dr H. R. Luard</ref>. They are described by
                        <ref type="bibl" target="Madden 1866">Sir F. Madden in the preface to <hi rend="italic">Matthew
                            Paris Historia Anglorum</hi> (Rolls pp. liv-lxi)</ref>, and by Sir <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Hardy 1871">T. Duffus Hardy <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Materials</hi> III
                        117-119</ref>. <ref type="person">Madden</ref> was of opinion that the two volumes were largely
                    in the autograph of <name type="author">Matthew Paris</name>: <name type="person">Hardy</name> in
                    the introduction to vol. III of his Catalogue contests this opinion with success, and shows that
                    only small portions of the nature of corrections and supplements can be safely assigned to the hand
                    of <name type="author">Paris</name> himself. His discussion is accompanied by facsimiles of the
                    various manuscripts which have been supposed to be in <name type="author">Paris</name>'s
                    handwriting. The following are taken from our MSS.<lb/> pl. X, XI from MS 26. pl. XII-XVI from <ref
                        type="ms" target="CCC16II">MS 16</ref>.</p>



                <p function="Research">In what follows I summarize the descriptions of <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Madden 1866">Madden</ref> and <ref type="bibl" target="Hardy 1871">Hardy</ref>, and add
                    a survey of the illustrations, chiefly marginal, which occur in the two volumes. Many of these have
                    been reproduced, notably in the illustrated editions of <ref type="bibl" target="Green 1892">Green's
                            <hi rend="italic">Short History</hi></ref> and of <hi rend="italic">Social England</hi> ;
                    but I do not know that any convenient list of them exists, though they are mentioned as they occur
                    in the footnotes to <ref type="bibl" target="Luard 1872">Luard's edition</ref>. <hi rend="footnote"
                        >The drawings of shields are described by <ref type="bibl" target="Luard 1872">Luard <hi
                                rend="italic">Chronica Maiora </hi>vi, App. I</ref>. He also gives facsimiles of the
                        writing in vols. I and II.</hi>
                </p>

                <p function="Research">The Cotton <ref type="ms" target="LBLND5">MS. Nero D. v</ref> contains a copy of
                    the text of both volumes made at <name type="place">St Albans</name> later in the
                    <date>xiii</date>th century.</p>


                <p function="Provenance">It belonged to <name type="person">Edward Aglionby</name> of <name type="place"
                        >Balsall Temple</name>, who lent it to <name type="person">Parker</name>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">There are two flyleaves at the beginning from a Canon Law MS.
                        (<origDate>xiv</origDate>: <layout>double columns</layout>, <handNote>closely
                    written</handNote>).</p>

                <p>It begins with an unidentified computation reaching to the year <date>231</date> A.D. and continues
                    with the text of <name type="author">Roger of Wendover</name> corrected and supplemented by <name
                        type="author">M. Paris</name>. The supplements are either on the margins or on inserted leaves:
                    these inserted leaves are now <locus locusNew="8r">15</locus>-<locus locusNew="10v">20</locus>,
                        <locus locusNew="16r">31</locus>-<locus locusNew="16v">32</locus>, <locus locusNew="19r"
                        >37</locus>-<locus locusNew="19v">38</locus>, <locus locusNew="127r">253</locus>-<locus
                        locusNew="128v ">256</locus>.</p>

                <p function="Writing">The remainder of the volume is in <handNote>two hands</handNote>. The first writes
                        <locus locusNew="1r">1</locus>-<locus locusNew="7r">14</locus>, <locus locusNew="11r"
                        >21</locus>-<locus locusNew="15v">30</locus>, <locus locusNew="17r">33</locus>-<locus
                        locusNew="18v">36</locus>, <locus locusNew="20r">39</locus>-<locus locusNew="59r">117</locus>,
                        <locus locusNew="97r">193</locus>-<locus locusNew="126v">252</locus>, <locus locusNew="129r"
                        >257</locus>-<locus locusNew="141v">282</locus>. The second, <handNote>a somewhat rounder
                        hand</handNote>, appears to extend from <locus locusNew="59r">117</locus> to <locus
                        locusNew="76v">192</locus>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">Marginal additions are few at first, but become more numerous after the year
                        <date>1100</date>. At the end of the year <date>1188</date>, in the lower margin, is this note
                    by <handNote>a hand of cent. <origDate>xiv</origDate></handNote> (which also appears in <ref
                        type="ms" target="CCC016II">MS 16II, on f. 37v</ref>): <q>Anno dominice incarnationis
                            <date>MCLXXXIX</date> est uera continuacio historie <name type="author">Mathei
                            Parisiensis</name> in alio uolumine eiusdem manus</q>. This refers to no. 16.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. A-B + a-b + i-vi + 1-141+ vii-ix + C-D</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="frm">Latin and Anglo-Norman.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="ir" locusEnd="viv">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Matthew Paris OSB</name>, <title>Chronica maiora I (preliminary
                                matter)</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The preliminary matter consists of</ab>
                        <ab>a. Itinerary from <name type="place">London</name> to <name type="place">Jerusalem</name>
                            with a description in French, similar to one in the <ref type="ms" target="LBLR07">Royal MS.
                                14, C. vii</ref> but containing some interesting variations. It occupies seven pages.
                            The portion from <name type="place">London</name> to <name type="place">Dover</name> is
                            engraved by <ref type="bibl" target="Gough 1780">Gough <hi rend="italic">Brit. Topogr.</hi>
                                pl. VII, fig. 2</ref>. The text is printed by the <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Michelant and Raynaud 1882">Société de l'Orient Latin, Itinéraires Français, p.
                                125</ref></ab>

                        <ab locus="ivv">b. A brief genealogical chronicle <q>Cronica sub conpendio abreuiata a fratre
                                    <name type="author">M. Parisiensi</name></q></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="ivv">Considerans prolixitatem Cronicorum <name type="place"
                            >Anglie</name></incipit>
                        <ab>It runs from <name type="person">Alfred</name> to <name type="person">Edward the
                                Elder</name>: then a leaf has been cut out. This took place at an early period, for a
                            copy of it of cent. <date>xiii late</date> in <ref type="ms" target="LBLTE6">Tiberius E. vi
                                (f. 5)</ref> terminates in the same manner. At the end of the volume on p.
                                <locus>285</locus> it is resumed and continued to <name type="person">Henry
                            II</name></ab>

                        <ab locus="vr">c. Circular Paschal table</ab>



                        <ab locus="vv">d. Table of Concurrentes etc. from <date>1116</date> to <date>1620</date>: a
                            similar one is in <ref type="ms" target="LBLR07">Royal 14, C. vii</ref></ab>
                        <ab>Diagram of the winds with verses. Sunt subsolano socii</ab>
                        <ab>Attributed to <name type="author">M. Paris</name> in <ref type="ms" target="LBLND1">Nero D.
                                I, f. 184v</ref></ab>




                        <ab locus="vir">e. Kalendar. See below</ab>




                        <ab>The following are my own notes on illustrations, etc.</ab>
                        <ab locus="ir">The itinerary from <name type="place">London</name> to the <name type="place"
                                >Holy Land</name>, ff. <locus>ir</locus>-<locus>ivr</locus>, is illustrated with
                                <decoNote>conventional cities, and with ships and figures of men every now and
                                then</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>ivv</locus> Genealogy: <decoNote>circular diagram with bust of <name
                                    type="person">Alfred</name> in C.</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>vr</locus>
                            <decoNote>the circular Paschal table is made to revolve</decoNote>: <decoNote>head of metal
                                pin in C.</decoNote>
                            <decoNote>Spandrels of beautiful ornament</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Another table or diagram formerly stuck to the lower part of the page is
                                gone</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>vv</locus> Table of Concurrentes. <decoNote>Diagram of winds</decoNote> etc.
                            (French and English names).</ab>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>vir</locus> Kalendar, six months on page</ab>


                        <ab><hi rend="bold">January</hi><lb/> 3. <name type="person">Genouefe</name> red<lb/> 4. Oct.
                            dedicac.<lb/> 5. Dep. <name type="person">S. Aedwardi</name> red. De <name type="person">S.
                                Aedwardo</name> comm.<lb/> 7. Dep. <name type="person">S. Aedwardi</name> reg. et c. hic
                            fiet festum red<lb/> 19. Dep. <name type="person">S. Wlstani</name> red<lb/> 27. Festum
                            Reliquiarum in eccl. <name type="person">S. Albani</name> blue</ab>


                        <ab><hi rend="bold">February</hi><lb/> 28. <name type="person">Osuualdi</name> archiep.</ab>
                        <ab><hi rend="bold">March</hi><lb/> 2. <name type="person">Ceadde</name> ep. C.<lb/> 10.
                            Inuencio <name type="person">S. Oswini</name> Reg. M. red<lb/> 25. <name type="person"
                                >Ermelandi</name></ab>



                        <ab><hi rend="bold">April</hi><lb/> 11. <name type="person">Guthlaci</name> C. Added, Ob. <name
                                type="person">Michael</name> de mentemor. Abb. (<date>1349</date>, date in lower
                            margin)<lb/> 19. <name type="person">Aelphegi</name> archiep. M. red<lb/> 24. Inuencio <name
                                type="person">S. Yuonis</name> Ep.<lb/> 30. <name type="person">Erkenuualdi</name> Ep.
                            red</ab>


                        <ab><hi rend="bold">May</hi><lb/> 7. <name type="person">Johannis</name> Archiep.</ab>




                        <ab><hi rend="bold">June</hi><lb/> 7. Transl. <name type="person">S. Wlstani</name> Ep. red<lb/>
                            14. <name type="person">Basilii</name> Archiep. red<lb/> 17. <name type="person"
                                >Botulfi</name> Abb. red<lb/> 21. <name type="person">Leofredi</name> Abb. (black). De
                                <name type="person">S. Albano</name> iii lect. red<lb/> 22. Passio <name type="person"
                                >S. Albani</name> Anglorum prothomartiris blue<lb/> 23. <name type="person"
                                >Aetheldrede</name> V.<lb/> 25. Inuencio <name type="person">S. Amphibali</name>
                            sociorumque eius blue, with octave</ab>


                        <ab><hi rend="bold">July</hi><lb/> 2. <name type="person">Swithin</name> red</ab>

                        <ab><hi rend="bold">August</hi><lb/> 2. Inuencio <name type="person">S. Albani</name> blue and
                            red, with octave<lb/> 5. <name type="person">Oswaldi</name> red<lb/> 20. <name type="person"
                                >Oswini</name> reg. m. red, with octave</ab>


                        <ab><hi rend="bold">September</hi><lb/> 4. Transl. <name type="person">S. Cuthberti</name>
                            red<lb/> 17. <name type="person">Lamberti</name> red</ab>


                        <ab><hi rend="bold">October</hi><lb/> 13. Transl. <name type="person">S. Ae(d)wardi</name> Reg.
                            C. green<lb/> 17. Transl. <name type="person">S. Etheldride</name> V.</ab>




                        <ab><hi rend="bold">November</hi><lb/> 17. <name type="person">Hugonis</name> Ep. C. red<lb/>
                            20. <name type="person">Aedmundi</name> Reg. M. blue.</ab>


                        <ab><hi rend="bold">December</hi><lb/> 3. <name type="person">Birini</name></ab>





                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="ixv">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Matthew Paris OSB</name>, <title>Chronica maiora I</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>Illustrations</ab>



                        <ab locus="7" locusNew="4r">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Brutus</name> worshipping <name type="person">Diana</name>,
                                who has deer's horns and winged feet</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="11" locusNew="6r">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Lear</name> and his three daughters: <name type="person"
                                    >Cordeilla</name> has scroll, tant as tant vauz tant te pris pere</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="24" locusNew="12v">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Alexander</name> sits holding globe: feet on lion and
                                dragon</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="28" locusNew="14v">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Cassibelanus?</name> seated king</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="30" locusNew="15v">
                            <decoNote>The Virgin reclining: child in manger: ox and ass: curtain on rod</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="32" locusNew="16v">
                            <decoNote>The three kings on camels gallop to R.</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="35" locusNew="18r">
                            <decoNote>Crucifixion with Virgin and <name type="person">St John</name>: four
                                nails</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="36" locusNew="18v">
                            <decoNote>A man stones <name type="person">Stephen</name> kneeling</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="39" locusNew="20r">
                            <decoNote>A small figure of the Virgin</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="66" locusNew="33v">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Merlin</name> half-length only partly inked in: below two
                                dragons and boar, in pencil</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="87" locusNew="44r">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Machometus</name>: below his feet a red pig sus: he holds two
                                scrolls. Poligamus esto. Scriptum est enim Crescite et multiplicamini. Presentes
                                delicias pro futuris non spernite</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="105" locusNew="53r">
                            <decoNote>Bust: <name type="person">Offa</name> in cowl, crown falls off showing tonsure:
                                another of a woman in cowl and crown</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="116" locusNew="58v">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Alban</name> beheaded. Executioner catches his (own) falling
                                eyes in L. hand</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="117" locusNew="59r">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Offa</name> directs two men, who dig up <name type="person"
                                    >Alban</name>'s coffin</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="129" locusNew="65r"><decoNote><name type="person">Alfred</name> half-length in
                                medallion with scroll</decoNote>, Primus in anglia regnam solus</ab>
                        <ab locus="160" locusNew="80v"><decoNote>Single combat on horseback between <name type="person"
                                    >Aedmundus ferreum latus</name> and <name type="person">Cnuto rex
                                Dacie</name></decoNote>. <decoNote><name type="person">Angli</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Daci</name> in two towers R. and L.</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="165" locusNew="83r">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Mimekan nanus</name> cuts off legs of <name type="person"
                                    >Rodogan gigas</name> (lightly inked in)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="172" locusNew="86v">
                            <decoNote>Shield and crown of <name type="person">Harold</name> (az. lion rampant
                                or)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="174" locusNew="87v">
                            <decoNote>The same reversed. Shield of <name type="person">William</name> (gu. 3 leopards
                                or)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="180" locusNew="90v">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">William</name>'s shield and crown reversed. <name
                                    type="person">William II</name>'s shield and crown (the same)</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab locus="197" locusNew="99r">
                            <decoNote>Crosier (of Abbot <name type="person">Richard of St Albans</name>)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="211" locusNew="106r">
                            <decoNote>Hand holding taper (opposite description of the Holy places: and account of <name
                                    type="person">William</name>'s court in <name type="place">Westminster
                                Hall</name>)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="212" locusNew="106v">
                            <decoNote>Shield and crown of <name type="person">William II</name> reversed: bow and arrow
                                below. Shield of <name type="person">Henry I</name></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="218" locusNew="109v">
                            <decoNote>Crosier and cross reversed (death of <name type="person">Anselm</name>)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="220" locusNew="110v">
                            <decoNote>Two Templars on one horse</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="110v">
                            <decoNote>Hospital founded by <name type="person">Matilda</name> in <name type="place"
                                    >London</name></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="222" locusNew="111v">
                            <decoNote>Men fall out of ship (wreck of the White Ship)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="223" locusNew="112r">
                            <decoNote>Bust of <name type="person">Alexander of Scotland?</name></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="225" locusNew="113r"><decoNote>Shield and crown of <name type="person">Henry I</name>
                                reversed</decoNote>. <decoNote>Shield of <name type="person"
                            >Stephen</name></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="234" locusNew="117v">
                            <decoNote>Bust of <name type="person">David of Scotland</name></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="238" locusNew="119v"><decoNote>Shield of <name type="person">Stephen</name>
                                reversed</decoNote>. <decoNote>Shield of <name type="person">Henry
                            II</name></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="254" locusNew="127v">
                            <decoNote>Baptism of the <name type="person">Soldan of Yconium</name> by the patriarch of
                                Antioch: in a tub. A cleric holds box of chrism</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="261" locusNew="131r">
                            <decoNote>Shield of the young king <name type="person">Henry</name>, party per pale gu. and
                                sable to denote death. The crown above, not upright</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="263" locusNew="132r">Murder of <name type="person">Becket</name>: <decoNote>the four
                                knights; <name type="person">Grim</name> with cross interposing. <name type="person"
                                    >Becket</name> falls away from altar on R.</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="265" locusNew="133r">
                            <decoNote>Falling walls (<name type="place">Leicester</name>)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="267" locusNew="134r">
                            <decoNote>Bust of <name type="person">William of Scotland</name>, crown falling off. Bust of
                                a Scotchman with axe, weeping</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="270" locusNew="135v">
                            <decoNote><name type="person">Robert Mercer</name> of <name type="place">St Albans</name>,
                                and two men digging up <name type="person">S. Amphibalus</name></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="274" locusNew="137v"><decoNote>Crown and shield of <name type="person">Philip of
                                    France</name> (az. six fleurs-de-lys or 3, 2, 1)</decoNote>. <decoNote>Reversed
                                crown of <name type="person">Louis</name></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="275" locusNew="138r">
                            <decoNote>Crowned mitre of <name type="person">Prester John</name></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="276" locusNew="138v">
                            <decoNote>Crown and shield (half black) of the young <name type="person">Henry</name>,
                                reversed</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="279" locusNew="140r">
                            <decoNote>Battle. <name type="person">Salaadinus</name> and <name type="person">Guido
                                    rex</name> struggling for Crux Sancta</decoNote>
                        </ab>


                        <ab locusNew="viir">
                            <decoNote>After the text, a full page with three splendid coloured drawings. Busts of
                                crowned Virgin, and Child with cross-nimbus: border of clouds below</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="viir"><decoNote>Below this on L. Head of the dying Christ</decoNote>. <decoNote>On
                                R. Head of Christ full-face with jewelled collar of tunic</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="viiv"><decoNote>Mappa mundi</decoNote> on verso, <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Gough 1780">Gough Brit. Topogr. I 66, 86</ref>. The map in <ref type="ms"
                                target="LBLND5">Nero D. v</ref> was copied from this. Genealogy of kings, one leaf</ab>


                        <ab locusNew="ixr">On the last flyleaf are notes, viz.</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="ixr">Title. <q>Cronica ab origine mundi usque ad a. d. millesimum ... simum
                                videlicet usque ad mortem <name type="person">henrici (II)</name> Regis anglie</q></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="ixr">
                            <q>iiii marce auri dedit ... de ... pro pace</q>
                            <lb/>
                            <q>vii marce dabantur comiti legr S. pro carta quam habuit a rege de custodia Wascon</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="ixr"><name type="person">S. Patrick</name> prophesies greatness of the unborn
                                <name type="person">S. David</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="ixr"><q>Circa <name type="place">carleolum</name> patria est dicta <name
                                    type="place">aluedele</name></q>.<lb/>
                            <q>Hic. uersus austrum cocormue villa. patria. complem</q>.<lb/>
                            <q>Aqua dorecte et currit (?) per cocormue</q></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="ixr">
                            <q><name type="person">Edwarde Aglionby</name> of <name type="place">Balsall
                                Temple</name></q> (<origDate>xvi</origDate>) </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="ixr">
                            <q>
                                <name type="person">Ihesus</name>
                                <name type="person">maria</name>
                                <name type="person">Johnes</name>
                            </q> (<origDate>xv</origDate>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="ixr">Note on dispersion of Apostles and division of the world</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="ixr">List of Saxon kings, <name type="person">Egbert</name> to <name type="person"
                                >Ethelred</name></ab>
                        <ab>Verso, covered with paper, apparently blank</ab>


                    </msItem>


                </msContents>




                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, CF 2nd</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC + CF 16.5.2007</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>


            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
