<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC286">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>286</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>L. 15</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>136</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Gospels of St Augustine</head>
                <head type="James">Evangelia Cantuariensia</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">245</height>
                        <width unit="mm">190</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">9.5 x 7.5</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 2 + 265 + 6</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 25 lines to a page</layout>. Assigned to the <origDate>vi</origDate>th
                    cent. by <name type="person">Tischendorf</name> (note by him on last flyleaf <supplied>(f.
                            <locus>vr</locus>)</supplied>) on account of its marked likeness to <ref type="ms"
                        target="BMLAM1">Codex Amiatinus</ref>; to the <origDate>vi</origDate>th cent. also by <name
                        type="person">Traube</name> (note in catalogue); to the <origDate>vii</origDate>th cent. by more
                    recent writers. <handNote>In fine uncials on lines ruled with the dry point</handNote>; words not
                    divided. Beginnings of clauses are thrown out; the rest of the clause indented. <decoNote>First
                        words of chapters in red</decoNote>. Sections (Eusebian-Ammonian) and headlines (occasional)
                        <handNote>in smaller hand</handNote>. <handNote>Each gospel is said to be in a distinct
                        hand</handNote>. </p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num>, gap, iii<num>2</num> iv<num>8</num>-xii<num>8</num> xiii<num>10</num>
                        (wants 1 or 4) xiv<num>8</num>-xviii<num>8</num> (+ 8*) xix<num>8</num> (wants 1, 8)
                            xx<num>8</num>-xxviii<num>8</num> xxix<num>4</num> (wants 4)
                            xxx<num>8</num>-xxxvi<num>8</num> xxxvii<num>4</num>, b<num>2</num> c<num>2</num>
                            d<num>2</num></collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">Most critics agree in thinking that it was written in <name type="place"
                        >Italy</name>. From <name type="place">St Augustine's, Canterbury</name> (see charters at end).
                        <hi rend="footnote"><ref type="bibl" target="James 1903"><hi rend="italic">Ancient
                                Libraries</hi>, pp. lxvii, lxviii</ref>. It is probably, but not certainly, mentioned by
                            <name type="person">Thomas of Elmham</name>.</hi>
                </p>

                <p>Quires iv-xii have on their last page near the inner corner Q. IIII etc. <handNote>in a hand at least
                        near the time of the original</handNote>. Most of the others have had a number written in cent.
                        <origDate>xiv</origDate> on their first page. This has been erased in a majority of cases. </p>

                <p>The vellum is of very unequal quality. The ink has disappeared in a good many places from the thinner
                    sheets.</p>

                <p>f. <locus>ir</locus> blank except for a slight green stain caused perhaps by metal. f.
                        <locus>iir</locus> has a small rust mark at top. <decoNote>On f. <locus>iiv</locus> is a bearded
                        head cleverly sketched <handNote>by an English hand</handNote> of cent. <origDate>x,
                            xi?</origDate></decoNote>
                </p>

                <p function="Research" rend="afterContents">This manuscript was <ref type="bibl" target="Bentley ???"
                        >Bentley's B</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="Smith 1860-63">Westcott's 23 (Dict. Bibl. article
                        Vulgate)</ref>. In the Novum Testamentum Latine of <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Wordsworth and White 1899">Wordsworth and White it is X</ref>. It was collated for this
                    edition by <name type="person">Dr A. W. Streane</name>. It is no. 20 in <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Gregory 1894">Gregory's Prolegomena, p. 995</ref>.</p>



                <p function="Research" rend="afterContents">The principal reproductions are in: <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Westwood 1868">Westwood, Anglo-Saxon and Irish MSS., pp. 49, 50</ref>. <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Westwood 1843-5a">Westwood, Palaeographia Sacra Pictoria, pl. ii</ref>. <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Goodwin 1847">Goodwin, Cambridge Antiquarian Society</ref>. Alphabets, etc., 3 pages of
                    text, painting I, and small scenes from painting II. In colours. <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Bond and Thompson 1873-78">Palaeographical Society I, pl. 33, 34, 44</ref>. <ref
                        type="bibl" target="CAS ???">Cambridge Antiquarian Society Proceedings Vol. II, pl. ix, painting
                        II</ref>. In colours. <ref type="bibl" target="Garrucci 1873-81">Garrucci, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Storia del' arte Cristiana</hi> III</ref>.</p>
                <p function="Research" rend="afterContents"><name type="person">Mr H. J. White</name> (Article Vulgate
                    in <ref type="bibl" target="Hastings and Selbie 1898-1904">Hastings' Dict. Bib. IV 887</ref>) says
                    of this MS. (according to tradition sent by <name type="person">Pope Gregory</name> to <name
                        type="person">Augustine</name>) <q>the text does not bear out this supposition, it closely
                        resembles that of the preceding MS. (<ref type="ms" target="OBL698">Bodl. Auct. D. 2. 14</ref>)
                        and is really Anglo-Saxon, though it has been corrected throughout in accordance with a MS. of
                        the Amiatinus type.</q> In spite of this complexion of the text it must be remembered that a
                    large consensus of critics assign to the writing and paintings an Italian origin. It is of course
                    possible that like the <ref type="ms" target="BMLAM1">Codex Amiatinus</ref> this book may have been
                    written by an Italian resident in England.</p>
                <p function="Research" rend="afterContents">The latest discussion of the MS. which I have seen is that
                    by <ref type="bibl" target="Chapman 1908">Dom J. Chapman, <hi rend="italic">Early History of the
                            Vulgate Gospels</hi> (1908) 183 sqq.</ref>, who disagrees with Mr White's conclusions. His
                    final statement (p. 189) is: <q>The two noble volumes of Gospels [i.e. this MS. and the Bodleian
                        Gospels, <ref type="ms" target="OBL698">Auct. D. 2. 14</ref>] are old enough to be what they
                        were believed to be; and I do not think the internal evidence of their readings can be shown to
                        make this impossible.</q></p>
                <p function="Research" rend="afterContents">Traube (<ref type="bibl" target="Traube 1907">Nomina Sacra,
                        p. 189, note 3</ref>) says: <q>Es hatten dns die alten Handschriften, die aus <name type="place"
                            >Rom</name> und Süditalien nach <name type="place">England</name> durch <name type="person"
                            >Augustin</name> und seine Nachfolger kamen, Handschriften, von denen wir selbst noch
                        besitzen z. B. den <name type="person">Bonifatianus I</name> in <name type="place">Fulda</name>,
                        die Evangelia <name type="person">S. Augustini</name> Cambridge C. C. C. 286 und <ref type="ms"
                            target="WURQ02">Würzburg Theol. Q. 2</ref> (der Laudianus dagegen schreibt die Nomina sacra
                        aus.)</q></p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-c + i*-iii* + 1* + 1-265 + i-v + d-g</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="ang">Latin and Old English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="0.1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="74r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Gospel of <name type="author">Matthew</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Evangelia quatuor Latine secundum versionem <name type="person">D. Hieronimi</name>,
                                haud tamen absque majoris momenti lectionibus ab editione vulgata discrepantibus. De hoc
                                autem codice notandum est eum ab aliis antiquissimis codicibus, quos in <name
                                    type="place">Anglia</name> scriptos esse constat, cum quoad membranorum faciem tum
                                quoad atramenti colorem tum denique quoad literarum ductum maxime differre. Quae quidem
                                cum aliis infra dicendis rationibus faciunt ut credam hunc codicem unum esse eorum quos
                                ad <name type="person">Augustinum</name> Anglorum apostolum et primum Dorobernensem
                                archiepiscopum mille et centum abhinc annis misit <name type="person">Gregorius magnus
                                    papa Romanus</name>. De libris ab eo in <name type="place">Angliam</name> missis
                                consulat eruditus lector <name type="person">Iohannem Diaconum</name> in vita <name
                                    type="person">Gregorii magni</name> cap. 37. et <name type="person">Beda</name>
                                historiam ecclesiasticam lib. i. cap. 29</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>f. <locus>1r</locus> begins imperfectly in capitula of <name type="author">Matthew</name>
                            (xii)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r">(Nine)uitarum signum<lb/>pharisaeis tradit<lb/>matrem et fratres
                            spernit</incipit>
                        <ab>xxviii ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="2r">et doctrina eius de baptismo</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="2r">Explicuerunt</rubric>
                        <ab>(red)</ab>
                        <ab>Below this is written (<origDate>xi?</origDate>) <q>Siferð<lb/>7<!--&#8266;-->
                            tate</q></ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="2r">Incipit ipse liber</rubric>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>2v</locus> is only <name type="author">Mattheus</name> hominem in large
                            capitals</ab>
                        <ab>Text begins at top of f. <locus>3r</locus></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="3r">Liber generationis</incipit>
                        <ab>(in red)</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>This page bears some stains from a lost frontispiece</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>A conspicuous corrector, <handNote>who writes in black uncials</handNote>, appears on f.
                                <locus locusNew="14v">14r</locus>, <locus>15r</locus> etc.: he may be of cent.
                                <origDate>viii</origDate>. A later corrector, <handNote>English
                                    (<origDate>ix?</origDate>)</handNote>, writes haec on f. <locus>14v</locus>,
                            imperauit on <locus>18r</locus>, muliere on f. <locus>45v</locus> etc.</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>29r</locus>, col. 2, is seen <handNote>a line written in the same script as the
                                section-numbers</handNote>. See also f. <locus>39r</locus>, col. 1, and notably f.
                                <locus>58v</locus>, col. 2, bottom</ab>
                        <ab>Ends <locus>74r</locus>, <decoNote>colophon in rustic capitals, lines alternately red and
                                black</decoNote></ab>
                        <rubric locus="74r">Explicit Euangelium<lb/>secundum <name type="author"
                            >Mattheum</name><lb/>Incipit Euangelium<lb/>secundum <name type="author"
                            >marcum</name><lb/>Deo gratias </rubric>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="0.2" locusStart="75r" locusEnd="77r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Prologue and Capitula to <name type="author">Mark</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locusNew="75r">
                            <decoNote>Two little heads of dogs (?)sketched at top of f. <locus>75r</locus></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Prologue to <name type="author">Mark</name></ab>
                        <incipit locus="75r"><name type="author">Marcus</name> euangelista dei</incipit>


                        <explicit locusNew="75v">incrementum dat deus est</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="75v">Explicit prologus</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="75v">(<decoNote>rustic capitals, red</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="75v">Incipiunt capitula</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="76r">i de <name type="person">iohanne baptista</name> et uictu etc.</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="77r">xiii -et resurrectio eius</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="77r">Explicuerunt<lb/>capitula.</rubric>
                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="0.3" locusStart="77r" locusEnd="265v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Gospels of <name type="author">Mark</name>, <name type="author">Luke</name> and <name
                                    type="author">John</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locusNew="77r">Incipit<lb/>ipse liber</rubric>

                        <ab locus="78r">Text, beginning in red</ab>

                        <ab locusNew="78r"><decoNote>Between the columns is drawn a half-length figure of a being with
                                lion's claws and ears, and human face, winged, holding a book (facsimile in <ref
                                    type="bibl" target="Goodwin 1847">Goodwin, l.c.</ref>). It is before this leaf that
                                the leaf with the frontispiece seems to have stood: there are some colour-stains on
                                    <locus>78r</locus></decoNote>.</ab>

                        <ab><locus>91r</locus>, col. 2, has been largely re-inked</ab>
                        <ab>Ends <locus>124r</locus>. Colophon as before <decoNote>in red and black rustic
                                capitals</decoNote></ab>

                        <rubric locusNew="124r">Explicit Euangelium secund(um)<lb/><name type="author">Marcum</name>.
                            Incipit<lb/>secundum <name type="author">Luca</name></rubric>
                        <ab><locus>124v</locus> blank</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>On f. <locus>125r</locus> the famous painting in twelve compartments. For
                                reproductions see above. Another painting most probably preceded it</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><locus>125v</locus> is blank</ab>
                        <ab>Prologue</ab>
                        <incipit locus="126r"><name type="person">Lucas</name> syrus antiocensis arte medicus</incipit>

                        <explicit locusNew="126v">prodisse</explicit>

                        <rubric locusNew="126v">Explicit prologus<lb/>Incipiunt capitula</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="127r">i <name type="person">Zacharias</name> angelo non credens</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="129r">xx -resurrectio eius et reliqua</explicit>

                        <rubric locusNew="129r">Explicuerunt<lb/>Brebes. Incipit<lb/>ipse liber</rubric>

                        <ab locus="129v">
                            <decoNote><locus>129v</locus> has the second painting, of <name type="author">St
                                Luke</name>, surrounded by scenes from the Ministry. For reproductions see
                                above</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab locus="130r">Headline in rustic</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="130r">Incipit Euangelium secundum <name type="author">Luca</name></rubric>
                        <ab>Text</ab>
                        <incipit locus="130r">Quoniam quidem</incipit>
                        <ab>After <locus>130v</locus> a leaf is gone. <locus>130v</locus> ends Et incredibiles (1 17).
                                <locus>131r</locus> begins Et regni eius (1 33)</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>194v</locus>, col. 2 <q>passio dni nri</q> is written in the hand of the later
                            corrector (<handNote>English minuscule of cent. <origDate>viii?</origDate></handNote>)</ab>

                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <rubric locus="205v">Explicit Euangelium secundum <name type="author">Luca</name>.<lb/>Incipit
                            secundum <name type="author">Iohanne</name><lb/>Inc. prologus<lb/>eiusdem.
                            Deo<lb/>gratias</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="205v">
                            <decoNote>Here a leaf with the frontispiece to John is missing. There are slight stains on
                                f. <locus>206r</locus></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Headline</ab>
                        <rubric locus="206r">Praefatio</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="206r">Iohannes euangelista</incipit>

                        <explicit locusNew="206v">doctrina seruetur. Amen</explicit>

                        <rubric locusNew="206v">Explicit prologus<lb/>Incipiunt capitula</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="207r">i Pharisaeorum leuitae</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="207v">xiv -Et resurrectio eius</explicit>

                        <rubric locusNew="207v">Expliciunt capitula. incipit ipse liber</rubric>

                        <ab>At top of <locus>207v</locus>
                            <handNote>in rustic capitals</handNote> + More volans aquilae petit astra <name
                                type="author">Iohannes</name></ab>

                        <ab>Text</ab>
                        <incipit locus="208r">In principio erat<lb/>uerbum</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>On f. <locus>256r</locus> is a spirited sketch of a man in a pointed cap
                                gesticulating: probably meant for a Jew</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <rubric locus="265v">Explicit Euangelium<lb/>secundum <name type="author"
                            >Iohannem</name><lb/>Deo gratias<lb/>semper. Amen</rubric>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="74v" locusEnd="74v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Grant of renders from land at <name type="place">Brabourne, Kent</name> by <name
                                    type="author">Ealhburg</name> to <name type="place">St Augustine's Abbey</name>, c.
                                A.D. <date>850</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Testamentum <name type="author">Ealhburgae</name> in quo recitantur quae legavit
                                    <name type="place">monasterio S. Augustini</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Quod quidem testamentum publicavit <name type="person">D. Georgius Hickesius</name>
                                in dissertatione sua epistolari</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>74v</locus>, <handNote>in fine round black hand</handNote>, the Will of <name
                                type="author">Ealhburh</name></ab>

                        <incipit locus="74v">In nomine domini <name type="author">ealhburh</name> hafaþ geset myd hyre
                            freonda</incipit>
                        <ab>(facsimile in <ref type="bibl" target="Goodwin 1847">Goodwin, Cambridge Antiquarian Society
                                1847, pl. 1</ref>)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="74v">agife land 7 bec þam hi&#447;um to <name type="place"
                                >sanct&#230; agustine</name></explicit>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wanley 1705">Wanley, p. 151</ref>

                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="RJR">
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Sawyer 1968">S 1198</ref>
                            </supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="77v" locusEnd="77v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement between <name type="person">Wulfric, abbot of St Augustine's,
                                    Canterbury</name>, and <name type="person">Ealdred, son of Lyfing</name>, about land
                                at <name type="place">Clife, Kent</name>, c. A.D. <date>990 x 1005</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Conventio Saxonice scripta [Paulo ante initium evangelii secundum D. Marcum] quae
                                facta fuit inter <name type="person">Wulfricum abbatem</name> [qui floruit A.D.
                                    <date>949</date>] et <name type="person">Ealredum Lifingi filium</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>77v</locus>, originally blank, <handNote>in good black hand</handNote></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="77v">In nomine domini nostri Iesu Christi her s&#447;utelað on þisum
                            ge&#447;rite hu &#447;ulfric abb.</incipit>


                        <ab>(facsimile in <ref type="bibl" target="Goodwin 1847">Goodwin, l.c.</ref>)</ab>

                        <explicit locusNew="77v">to hyra sa&#447;le ðearfe á butan ende; amen</explicit>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Wanley 1705">Wanley, p. 157</ref>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <supplied agent="RJR">
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Sawyer 1968">S 1455</ref>
                            </supplied>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="ir" locusEnd="ir">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement about land at <name type="place">Wicham</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Redditio terrae de <name type="place">Wicham</name> Deo et <name type="place">S.
                                    Augustino</name> et <name type="person">domino Hugoni abbati</name> per <name
                                    type="person">Robertum Fresla</name>, in illa quadragesima in qua <name
                                    type="person">rex Henricus</name> dedit filiam suam imperatori</title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locusNew="ir">Item de terra <name type="place">WICHAM</name> nominata, etc.</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>This is in a hand very closely resembling that of the Missal <ref type="ms"
                                    target="CCC270">MS 270</ref></handNote>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="ir" locusEnd="ir">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement between <name type="person">Osbern de Ripla</name> and <name type="place"
                                    >St Augustine's Abbey</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Conventio inter <name type="person">Osbernum de Ripla</name> filiosque ejus et
                                abbatem <name type="place">S. Augustini</name> de annua pensione XVIs. VIIId. solvenda
                                ex terra de <name type="place">Ripla</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <incipit locusNew="ir">Hec est actio que facta est in presentia <name type="person">hugonis
                                abbatis secundi</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="ir"><date>Anno ab incarnatione domini Mill<abbr rend="superscript">mo</abbr>
                                    c<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> xlvi<abbr rend="superscript">to</abbr> xv<abbr
                                    rend="superscript">mo</abbr> kal. apr.</date> apud <name type="person"
                                >Norburnam</name> in Hallimoto</explicit>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>In a good black pointed hand</handNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="iv" locusEnd="iir">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>List of relics</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Reliquiae quae sunt in uno parvo nigro scrinio uno flore notato</title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locusNew="iv">Héé sunt reliquie in uno paruo nigro scrinio flore uno signato. De ligno
                            domini plures particule. De sepulchro domini. De Scapula <name type="person">Sancti
                                Nicomedis martiris</name>. De Capillis <name type="person">Sancte Cecilie uirginis et
                                martiris</name>, De <name type="person">Sancta Margareta</name>. De <name type="person"
                                >Sancto Ianuario</name>. De uestis <name type="person">Sancte Marie</name>. De ossibus
                            et uestis <name type="person">Sancti Clementis martiris</name>. De uestis <name
                                type="person">Sancte Cecilie</name>. De <name type="person">Sancto Antonio
                                episcopo</name>. De <name type="person">Sancto Laurentio martire</name>. De <name
                                type="person">Sancto Johanne Baptista</name> os unum. De <name type="person">Sancto
                                Pancratio martire</name>. Costa de <name type="person">Sancto Mathia Apostolo</name>. De
                                <name type="person">Sanctis Wandregesilo</name>-<name type="person">Martino</name>-
                                <name type="person">Medardo</name> atque <name type="person">Gildardo</name>, <name
                                type="person">Odulfo episcopo</name>, <name type="person">Audoeno</name>, Dens <name
                                type="person">Sancti Vedasti</name>, De <name type="person">Sanctis Wlgaro</name>, <name
                                type="person">Paulino</name>, <name type="person">Affre</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Geruasio</name>, <name type="person">Ambrosio</name>. De cruce <name type="person"
                                >Sancti Andree apostoli</name>, De <name type="person">Sanctis Mildretha</name>, <name
                                type="person">Wilfrido</name>, <name type="person">Eadgitha</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Folquino</name>, <name type="person">Walburga</name>, <name type="person">Amato
                                Episcopo</name>, <name type="person">Petrocio</name>, <name type="person">Bartholomeo
                                Apostolo</name>, <name type="person">Tecla</name>. Digitus <name type="person">Sancti
                                Gregorii</name>. De <name type="person">Sancto Jacobo Apostolo fratre Sancti
                                Johannis</name>. De <name type="person">Sanctis Nicholao</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Leonardo</name>, <name type="person">Benedicto</name> et alie plures reliquie sine
                            scriptis. Et de <name type="person">Sancta Fide Virgine</name>
                        </incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="iv">In a separate line: <q><name type="person">Hollord</name>. <name type="person"
                                    >Ketil</name>. <name type="person">Ozor</name>. <name type="person">Yun</name>.
                                    <name type="person">Andreus</name>. <name type="person">Asclathe</name></q></ab>
                        <ab><locus>iir</locus> blank</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="iiv" locusEnd="iiv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement about a hill near <name type="place">Sakenhethe</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Concessio collis, qui est proximus <name type="place">Sakenhethe</name>, <name
                                    type="person">Jacobo filio Gilrici</name> per <name type="person">Robertum
                                    abbatem</name> et conventum, ea conditione ut dictus <name type="person"
                                    >Jacobus</name> ibi faciet unam salinam et reddet annuatim ad <name type="place"
                                    >curiam de Cistelet</name> II ferdendellos salis et V solidos</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>iiv</locus>
                            <handNote>in charter hand of cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate></handNote>, of the time of
                                <name type="person">Abbot Robert (de Bello)</name>
                            <date>1224</date>-<date>1252</date></ab>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="iiv" locusEnd="iiv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement about seven acres in <name type="place">Betleshangre</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Concessio 7 acrarum in <name type="place">Betleshangre</name>
                                <name type="person">Willelmo filio Hugonis de Betleshangre</name> per <name
                                    type="person">Robertum abbatem</name> et conventum, reservata pensione XLII
                                denariorum <name type="place">curiae de Norb.</name> annuatim solvenda</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>iiv</locus>
                            <handNote>in charter hand of cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate></handNote>, of the time of
                                <name type="person">Abbot Robert (de Bello)</name>
                            <date>1224</date>-<date>1252</date></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="iiv" locusEnd="iiv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement about the messuage of <name type="person">Colombine the
                                cleric</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Concessio messuagii <name type="person">Columbino clerico</name> per eundem abbatem
                                et conventum, reservata pensione Xs</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>iiv</locus>
                            <handNote>in charter hand of cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate></handNote>, of the time of
                                <name type="person">Abbot Robert (de Bello)</name>
                            <date>1224</date>-<date>1252</date></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="iiv" locusEnd="iiv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement about the messuage of <name type="person">Benedict son of
                                Radulph</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Concessio messuagii <name type="person">Benedicto filio Radulphi</name> per abbatem
                                et conventum reservata pensione XIIIIs. annuatim</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>iiv</locus>
                            <handNote>in charter hand of cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate></handNote>, of the time of
                                <name type="person">Abbot Robert (de Bello)</name>
                            <date>1224</date>-<date>1252</date></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="iiir" locusEnd="iiir">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement about ten and a half acres at <name type="place"
                                >Estbotleshangre</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Concessio 10 acrarum terrae et dim. in villa de <name type="place"
                                    >Estbotleshengre</name>
                                <name type="person">Hamoni filio Willelmi de Botleshanger</name> per <name type="person"
                                    >Robertum elemosinarium</name> cum consensu abbatis et conventus</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>iiir</locus>
                            <handNote>in charter hand of cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate></handNote>, of the time of
                                <name type="person">Abbot Robert (de Bello)</name>
                            <date>1224</date>-<date>1252</date></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="iiir" locusEnd="iiir">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Confirmation of the previous agreement about ten and a half acres at <name
                                    type="place">Estbotleshangre</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Confirmatio ejusdem donationis per abbatem et conventum</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>iiir</locus>
                            <handNote>in charter hand of cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate></handNote>, of the time of
                                <name type="person">Abbot Robert (de Bello)</name>
                            <date>1224</date>-<date>1252</date></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="iiir" locusEnd="viv">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Agreement about the garden of <name type="person">William son of John of
                                    Fenglesham</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Concessio cujusdam horti <name type="person">Willelmo filio Iohannis de
                                    Fenglesham</name> per dictum elemosinarium</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>On f. <locus>iiir</locus>
                            <handNote>in charter hand of cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate></handNote>, of the time of
                                <name type="person">Abbot Robert (de Bello)</name>
                            <date>1224</date>-<date>1252</date></ab>

                        <ab><locus>iiiv</locus>-<locus>viv</locus> blank: unimportant scribbles on f.
                            <locus>ivv</locus></ab>

                        <ab locusNew="vr">On the paper flyleaf at end is this note: <q>Codex tanta similitudine <ref
                                    type="ms" target="BMLAM1">codicis Amiatini</ref> excellit ut omnino saeculi vi esse
                                dicendus sit. M. <date>mart. 9. a. 1865</date>. <name type="person">Const.
                                    Tischendorf</name></q></ab>
                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: RJR 16/12/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
