<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>


                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC290">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>290</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>A. 9</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>9</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Ado of Vienne, Chronica</head>

                <head type="James">Chronica Odonis (Adonis)</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">257</height>
                        <width unit="mm">175</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">10 x 7</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 2 + 118 + 2</extent>,
                        <layout>25 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xi-xii</origDate>, <handNote>very well
                        written</handNote>.</p>



                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num> I<num>8</num>-XV<num>8</num> (wants 7, 8), 2 flyleaves</collation>.</p>


                <p><label>2 fo.:</label>
                    <secFol>dccc. vii. Porro</secFol>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">On f. <locus>iir</locus> an erasure not recoverable. On f. <locus>iiv</locus>
                    erased: <q>Cronica Odonis Abbatis</q>. At top of f. <locus>1r</locus> an obliterated line in red
                    which I am almost sure was: <q>Liber S. Albani ... titulum deleuerit anathema sit amen</q>.<lb/>
                    <handNote>The main hand is very like that of <name type="place">Christ Church,
                        Canterbury</name></handNote>.</p>


                <p function="Additions" rend="afterContents">The flyleaves at end are part of a deed of cent.
                        <date>xvi</date>, with notarial mark.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-ii + pp. 1-164 + 164a-b + 165-234 + ff. iii-iv + c-d</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1" locusEnd="234">

                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Ado of Vienne</name>, <title>Chronica</title></head>


                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Chronica <name type="author">Odonis</name> (<name type="author"
                                >Adonis</name>)</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>On f. <locus>iv</locus> note on the author <q>Ex Joh. parisiensi a. d.
                            <date>900</date></q></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Fine initial on f. <locus>1r</locus> in pale colours and pen and ink
                                ornament</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="1">Incipit cronica <name type="author">odonis abbatis</name> (l. Adonis)</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="1">Breues temporum annotationes per generationes et regna. Primus ex nostris
                                <name type="person">Iulius Affricanus</name></incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Migne 123"><supplied>P. L.</supplied> CXXIII</ref> 23)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="221">dehonestatus iniuria moritur</explicit>
                        <incipit locus="221">Ab orbe condito usque ad urbem conditam Anni iiii<abbr rend="superscript"
                                >or</abbr> milia cccc octuaginta iiii<abbr rend="superscript">or</abbr></incipit>

                        <explicit locusNew="224">Anno <date>dccxxiii</date>
                            <name type="person">Leoni</name> successit <name type="person"
                            >Constantinus</name></explicit>
                        <incipit locus="225">Anno dominicae incarnationis <date>dccc lxx vi</date>
                            <name type="person">Rollo</name> cum normannis gallis appulit</incipit>
                        <ab>Ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="225">Anno <abbr>i</abbr> (blank) Obiit <name type="person">Willelmus rex
                                Anglorum</name></explicit>
                        <ab>(this in another hand)</ab>


                        <rubric locus="225">Incipit genealogia Regum Francorum</rubric>

                        <incipit locusNew="225">Ex genealogia <name type="person">Priami</name> fuit <name type="person"
                                >Meroueus</name> pater <name type="person">Childerici</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="232"><name type="person">karlomannum</name> pariter sue benedictionis oleo
                            perunxit</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="232">Item genealogia Regum</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="232">Ex genealogia <name type="person">Priami</name> fuit <name type="person"
                                >meroueus</name> qui genuit <name type="person">Childericum</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="233"><name type="person">ludouicus</name> qui fuit huius prosapie regalis
                            rex ultimus</explicit>

                        <ab>
                            <handNote>Another hand</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="233"><name type="person">Karolus</name> princeps <name type="person"
                                >Pipini</name> regis filius</incipit>
                        <ab>(<decoNote>Condemnation of <name type="person">Charles</name>: dragon comes out of his
                                tomb</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <explicit locus="234">nobis uiua uoce sunt testati que uiderunt et audierunt</explicit>




                    </msItem>





                </msContents>



                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text:copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, but not by a second person</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 31.05.2007</p>
                            <p>remarks: </p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>



            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
