<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC002III">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>2III</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Under C. 2</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>356</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">The Bury Bible</head>
                <head type="James">Bibliorum Pars I</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">522</height>
                        <width unit="mm">360</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">20.6 x 14</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 357</extent>
                    <supplied>(now bound in three parts)</supplied>, <layout>double columns of 42 lines</layout>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xii</origDate>, <handNote>in a magnificent round hand</handNote>, <decoNote>and with
                        splendid ornaments</decoNote>.</p>
                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num> (1 canc.) I<num>10</num> (wants 4 and 7: 8 is a double leaf),
                            II<num>8</num>-XLIV<num>8</num> XLV<num>6</num> (wants 5, 6)</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">The book comes from <name type="place">Bury St Edmunds Abbey</name>. On the
                    upper corner of f. <locus>2r</locus> (first leaf of text) is a mark rather smaller than in most Bury
                    books, but of the same kind: B. 1.<lb/> The press-mark shows that this was the first book in class
                    B. The B here stands for <hi rend="italic">Biblia</hi>.<lb/> Further, at f. <locus>322r</locus> the
                    edge of the leaf has been mended with a patch of vellum in <origDate>cent. xv</origDate> on which is
                    sketched a crowned head (cut off at the neck) and a scroll inscribed <hi rend="italic">hic, hic,
                        hic</hi>. This represents <name type="person">St Edmund</name>'s head, which called out <q>Here,
                        here,</q> to those who were searching for it after the martyrdom. It fixes the provenance in a
                    very satisfactory way.<lb/> In the old catalogue (<date>cent. xii, xiii</date>) of the Abbey books
                    preserved in a <ref type="ms" target="CPC047">MS. at Pembroke College</ref> and printed in my <ref
                        type="bibl" target="James 1895"><hi rend="italic">Essays on the Abbey of Bury</hi>, 1895, p.
                        23</ref>, the second item is <q>Bibliotheca in duo uolumina (!)</q>: and in the <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Arnold 1892"><hi rend="italic">Gesta Sacristarum</hi>, Arnold, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Memorials of Bury St Edmunds Abbey</hi> (Rolls Series II, p. 290)</ref> in the account of
                        <name type="person">Hervey</name> (sacrist under <name type="person">Anselm</name> in
                        <date>1121-1148</date>) this passage occurs:<lb/>
                    <q>Iste <name type="person">Herveus</name> frater <name type="person">Taleboti prioris</name> omnes
                        expensas inuenit fratri suo priori in scribenda magna bibliotheca et manu <name type="person"
                            >magistri Hugonis</name> incomparabiliter fecit depingi. Qui cum non inueniret in partibus
                        nostris pelles uitulinas sibi accommodas, in <name type="place">Scotiae</name> partibus
                        parchamenas comparauit.</q><lb/> This passage seems to refer specially to the illuminating of
                    the Bible in question. I interpret it thus: that <name type="place">Hervey</name> found the money
                    for his brother the prior to have a great Bible written, and had it painted after a matchless sort
                    by the hand of <name type="person">Master Hugo</name>. The latter not finding vellum to suit him in
                    our district procured parchment from <name type="place">Ireland</name>.<lb/> Clearly there cannot
                    have been any difficulty in getting good vellum to write upon in <name type="place">England</name>.
                    But the special vellum required by the painter was a superior and rarer article. Now it will be
                    found that in this Bible all or almost all of the paintings are done upon separate pieces of vellum
                    which have been pasted down on the leaves of the book.<lb/> I have no hesitation therefore in
                    identifying the volume before us with a portion of the Bible of <name type="person">Magister
                        Hugo</name>. It is most interesting to have a work of this artist preserved. Like many workers
                    of his time, he exercised more than one craft. He is recorded to have made the bronze doors of <name
                        type="place">St Edmund's Church</name>, to have carved a fine rood for it, and to have cast a
                    great bell.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-iii + 242-347 + iv-vi</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="242r" locusEnd="357v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The Bury Bible</title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="245r">Explicit <name type="person">Ysaias</name> propheta habet versus III D
                            LXXX</rubric>
                        <ab locus="245r">Prol. to <name type="person">Jeremiah</name></ab>
                        <incipit locus="245r"><name type="person">Ieremias</name> propheta cui hic prologus</incipit>
                        <ab locus="245v">
                            <decoNote>The lower half has a picture, stuck on. Fine frame with pattern drawn in
                                perspective on black ground.<lb/> Ground of picture blue with green panels. Above, <name
                                    type="person">Jeremiah</name> seated on rocks holds out white scroll to R. Below, on
                                L., three soldiers attack a walled city (<name type="place">Jerusalem</name>) which is
                                defended by three within who throw red stones. These warriors have helmets, chain mail,
                                and pointed shields</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="246r">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial, stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="274v">Prologue to <name type="person">Baruch</name></ab>
                        <incipit locus="274v">Liber iste qui baruch nomine</incipit>
                        <ab locus="275r">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial (a green monkey in the middle: very good) stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="277r">Epistle of <name type="person">Jeremy</name>
                            <supplied>(<name type="person">Jeremiah</name>)</supplied>. <decoNote>Decorative initial,
                                not stuck on</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="278r">Hebrew alphabet. The forms of the letters are not given, but the names are
                            given twice with different Latin equivalents</ab>
                        <ab locus="278r">1. Aleph doctrina - Tau signa</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="278v">2. Aleph deus - Tau fortitude</ab>
                        <rubric locus="278v">Incipit lamentatio<name type="person">Jeremie</name> prophete quod est in
                            titulo chynoth cum absolutione litterarum hebraicarum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="281r">Explicit Lamentatio <name type="person">Jeremie</name> prophete. Incipit
                            oratio eiusdem (= Lam. v)</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="281r">Explicit <name type="person">Jeremias</name> propheta habet uersus IIII
                            CCCC L</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="281r">Prologue to <name type="person">Ezekiel</name></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="281r"><name type="person">Ezechiel</name> propheta cum Ioachin</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="281r">
                            <decoNote>with initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="281v">
                            <decoNote>Picture (and initial) stuck on. The picture is reproduced in colours in <ref
                                    type="bibl" target="CAS 1893"><hi rend="italic">Camb. Ant. Soc. Proc.</hi> vol. VII,
                                    pl. VIII (I)</ref>.<lb/> The main grounds are blue and green. In C. a mandorla with
                                Christ seated on the rainbow, holding open book on His knee and blessing. Four masks of
                                winds blowing at top and bottom. In 4 circles R. and L. formed by conventional
                                branch-work are the Four creatures: L. top, Angel with book; below, lion with scroll. R.
                                top, Eagle with scroll; below, ox with scroll, all nimbed and winged. At bottom in C. in
                                (rather more than) half circle, <name type="person">Ezekiel</name> half-length in
                                pointed cap holding scroll in both hands and looking up</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="300r">
                            <decoNote>On the margin a deer is sketched and below it in pencil <q>halla</q>(?)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="307r">Explicit <name type="person">Ezechiel</name> propheta habet versus III CCC
                            XL</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="307r">Prologue to <name type="person">Daniel</name>
                            <decoNote>with initial</decoNote></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="307r"><name type="person">Danielem</name> prophetam iuxta
                            septuaginta</incipit>
                        <ab locus="307v">
                            <decoNote>Decorative initial to text, stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="317v">Explicit <name type="person">Daniel</name> propheta habet versus mille
                                DCCC<abbr rend="superscript">tos</abbr> L<abbr rend="superscript">ta</abbr></rubric>
                        <ab locus="317v">Prol. beati <name type="author">Hieronimi</name> presbiteri in liber XII<abbr
                                rend="superscript">cim</abbr> prophetarum qui apud hebreos dicitur Thareasra</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="317v">Non idem ordo</incipit>
                        <ab locus="318r">Prol. in <name type="person">Osee</name></ab>
                        <incipit locus="318r">Temporibus loathan</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="318r"><name type="person">Osee</name>. <decoNote>Initial stuck on</decoNote></ab>
                        <rubric locus="321v">Explicit <name type="person">Osee</name> propheta</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="321v">Argumenta to <name type="person">Joel</name></ab>
                        <ab>1.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="321v"><name type="person">Iohel</name> filius <name type="person"
                                >fatuhel</name></incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="321v"><name type="person">Iohel</name> qui interpretatur</incipit>
                        <ab>3.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="321v"><name type="person">Iohel</name> de tribu ruben</incipit>
                        <ab locus="322r">
                            <decoNote>Initial stripped off. On this leaf is the sketch of <name type="person">St
                                    Edmund</name>'s head</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="323r">Arguments to <name type="person">Amos</name></ab>
                        <ab>1. (<decoNote>With initial</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="323r"><name type="person">Amos</name> propheta</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="323v"><name type="person">Ozias</name> rex</incipit>
                        <ab>3.</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="323v"><name type="person">Amos</name> pastor</ab>
                        <ab locus="324r">
                            <decoNote>Initial not stuck on. <name type="person">Amos</name> nimbed, seated, holds
                                scroll. Green ground</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="326v">Arguments to <name type="person">Obadiah</name></ab>
                        <ab>1.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="326v"><name type="person">Jacob</name> patriarcha</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="326v"><name type="person">Abdias</name> qui interpretatur</incipit>
                        <ab locus="327r">
                            <decoNote>Initial stripped off</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="327r">Arguments to <name type="person">Jonah</name></ab>
                        <ab>1.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="327r"><name type="person">Jonam</name> sanctum hebrei</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="327v"><name type="person">Jonas</name> columba</incipit>
                        <ab locus="327v">
                            <decoNote>Initial, not stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="328v">Arguments to <name type="person">Micah</name></ab>
                        <ab>1.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="328v">Temporibus <name type="person">loathan</name></incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="328v"><name type="person">Micheas</name> de morasthi</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="328v">
                            <decoNote>Initial not stuck on. <name type="person">Micah</name> in cap and mantle and tunic
                                holds scroll. He stands in a kind of running attitude. Green and blue ground</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="330v">Arguments to <name type="person">Nahum</name></ab>
                        <ab>1.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="330v"><name type="person">Naum</name> prophetam</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="331r"><name type="person">Naum</name> consolator</incipit>
                        <ab locus="331r">
                            <decoNote>Initial not stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="332r">Arguments to <name type="person">Habakkuk</name></ab>
                        <ab>1. (<decoNote>With initial</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="332r">Quatuor propheta</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="332v"><name type="person">Abbacuc</name> amplexans</incipit>
                        <ab>3.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="333r"><name type="person">Abbacuc</name> luctator</incipit>
                        <ab locus="333r">
                            <decoNote>Initial stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="334r">Arguments to <name type="person">Zephaniah</name></ab>
                        <ab>1. (<decoNote>With initial</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="334r">Tradunt hebrei</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="334v"><name type="person">Sophonias</name> speculator</incipit>
                        <ab locus="334v">
                            <decoNote>Initial stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="335v">Arguments to <name type="person">Haggai</name></ab>
                        <ab>1. (<decoNote>Initial</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="335v">Moriente dario</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="335v"><name type="person">Aggeus</name> festiuus</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="335v">
                            <decoNote>Initial, not stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="336v">Arguments to <name type="person">Zechariah</name></ab>
                        <ab>1 (<decoNote>Initial</decoNote>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="336v">Secundo anno darii filii</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="337r">Secundo anno darii regis</incipit>
                        <ab>3.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="337r"><name type="person">Zacharias</name> memor</incipit>
                        <ab locus="337v">
                            <decoNote>Initial, not stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="341v">Arguments to <name type="person">Malachi</name></ab>
                        <ab>1.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="341v">Ultimum duodecim</incipit>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="341v"><name type="person">Malachias</name> interpretatur</incipit>
                        <ab>3.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="341v"><name type="person">Malachias</name> aperte</incipit>
                        <ab locus="342r">
                            <decoNote>Initial, not stuck on</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="343r">Explicit <name type="person">Malachias</name> propheta prophetarum xii III
                            DCCC versus sunt</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="343r">Prologue to <name type="person">Job</name></ab>
                        <ab>1.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="343r">Cogor per singulos</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>with initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>2.</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="343v">In terra quidem habitasse</incipit>
                        <ab locus="344r">Capitula</ab>
                        <ab locus="344v">
                            <decoNote>Picture, stuck on (&#8532; of page). Frame mainly red blue in triangles,
                                ground blue and green. Above on R. <name type="person">Job</name> kneels on rocks. The
                                Divine Hand on R. On L. his seven sons and three daughters face R. Below on red ground,
                                separated off by cusped line, <name type="person">Job</name> seated on rocks, in blue
                                loincloth only. His wife on L. holds a blank scroll.<lb/> The initial and first words of
                                text are introduced in the lower L. corner</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="357r">Several supplementary prologues, viz.</ab>
                        <ab locus="357r">Prol. in <name type="person">Job</name></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="357r">Si aut fiscellam</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="357r">Arg. in <name type="person">Job</name></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="357r"><name type="person">Job</name> exemplar</incipit>
                        <ab locus="357v">Arg. in <name type="person">Danihelem</name></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="357v"><name type="person">Daniel</name> interpretatur iudicium</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="357v"><name type="person">Ieronimus</name> de libro duodecim
                            prophetarum</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="357v">Duodecim prophete in unius</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="357v">Arg. in <name type="person">Sophoniam</name></ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="357v"><name type="person">Iosiam</name> regem iude</incipit>


                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 01/08/08</p>
                            <p>remarks: </p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
