<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC301">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>301</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>A. 7</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>7</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Annals of St Augustine's, Canterbury. Canterbury Documents, etc.</head>

                <head type="James">Annales S. Augustini Cantuar. Canterbury documents, etc.</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">255</height>
                        <width unit="mm">154</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">10.2 x 6</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 1 + 113</extent>,
                        <layout>mostly about 44 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xiv early</origDate>,
                        <handNote>in charter hand</handNote>.</p>
                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1 flyleaf, 1<num>8</num> 2<num>12</num>-5<num>12</num> 6<num>8</num> 7<num>4</num> |
                            8<num>4</num> (paper) | 9<num>10</num> 10<num>14</num> (5 canc.: + slip)
                        11<num>18</num></collation>.</p>
                <p><label>2 fo.:</label>
                    <secFol>autem que maior</secFol>.</p>
                <p function="Provenance">From <name type="place">St Augustine's, Canterbury</name>. At bottom of f.
                        <locus>1r</locus> is a slip pasted on: <q>Liber ffratris Stephani de Hakynton de librario Sancti
                        Augustini Cantuariensis</q>. It is not in the Catalogue.</p>



                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i + 1-68 + 68a-d (68av-68br uncut and unphotographed) + 69-90 + 90a + 91-98 +
                        98a + 99-108 + ii + c-d</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="frm">Latin and Anglo-Norman.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="68v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Annals of <name type="place">St Augustine's, Canterbury</name> (to
                                <date>1316</date>)</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Annales <name type="place">ecclesiae Augustini Cantuariensis</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>Desinunt in anno <date>1316</date></quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="1" locusNew="1r">Chronicle</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="1r">Ante incarnacionem domini m<abbr rend="superscipt">o</abbr> cc<abbr
                                rend="superscript">o</abbr> venit <name type="person">Brutus</name> in <name
                                type="place">Angliam</name> et regnauit xxiiii<abbr rend="superscript">or</abbr> annis
                            cuius tempore judicauit <name type="person">Heli</name> filios <name type="place"
                                >israel</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Fluxit ab <name type="person">Enea</name> primum Romana propago,
                            etc.</incipit>
                        <rubric locusNew="1r"><name type="person">Eneas</name> cum <name type="person">Ascaneo</name>
                            filio suo fugiens excidium</rubric>
                        <ab>Added (<date>xiv</date>): <q>Habet <name type="place">Britannia</name> in longitudinem dccc
                                milia et in latitudinem cc. Et quicunque (?) usui mortalium congruit indeficienti
                                fertilitate ministrat</q></ab>
                        <ab>Ends p. <locus locusNew="20v">44</locus> in <date>1200</date></ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="20v">Ipseque Rex ffrancorum <name type="person">Regem Johannem</name> de
                            prodicione appellauit</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="20v">Quere de gestis <name type="person">Henrici</name> filii <name
                                type="person">Johannis</name> in xi<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> xii<abbr
                                rend="superscript">o</abbr> xiii<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> et quartodecimo
                            foliis</rubric>
                        <ab>(i.e. pp. 65 sqq.)</ab>
                        <ab locus="44" locusNew="20v">List of Kingdoms, Counties and Bishoprics in <name type="place"
                                >England</name></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>Another hand begins here</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="45" locusNew="21r">Incipit cronice paucorum scilicet ab incarnatione domini
                            nostri Ihesu Christi</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="21r"><name type="person">Orosius</name> ad <name type="person">beatum
                                Augustinum</name> scribens</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="21r">ab origine mundi usque ad Christum fluxerunt anni quinque milia centum
                            nonaginta nouem</explicit>
                        <ab>The form is annalistic: at first in double columns down to <date>1038</date>: one line for a
                            year: from <date>1039</date> to <date>1186</date> a line to a year, single columns</ab>
                        <ab locus="62" locusNew="29v">Insertion on <name type="person">Archbishop Baldwin</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="63" locusNew="30r"><date>1187</date>-<date>1226</date>, a line to a year</ab>
                        <ab locus="65" locusNew="31r">Then longer entries</ab>
                        <ab locus="68" locusNew="32v"><date>1235</date>-<date>1253</date>, a line to a year. Then longer
                            entries</ab>
                        <ab>There are various changes of hand after p. <locus locusNew="55r">113</locus>
                                (<date>1304</date>): on <locus locusNew="67r">136</locus> (<date>1315</date>, Statute de
                            venditionibus) is a <date>xvi</date>th cent. reference: <q>Vide in libro qui inscribitur
                                Diuersi tractatus monasterii <name type="place">Sancti Augustini Dorobernie</name></q>.
                            This is a book mentioned in <name type="person">Parker</name>'s own list but marked therein
                            as missing by <name type="person">John Parker</name>: it is now <ref type="ms"
                                target="LAM213">Lambeth MS. 1213</ref></ab>
                        <ab>The text goes to <date>1316</date> ending with <name type="person">Edward II</name>'s letter
                            to <name type="person">Pope Clement</name> on the election of an Abbot of <name type="place"
                                >St Augustine's</name> (<name type="person">Devenysshe</name>), ending p. <locus
                                locusNew="68v">140</locus></ab>
                        <explicit locus="140" locusNew="68v"><name type="place">Calesium</name>. die
                            septembris</explicit>
                        <ab><handNote>In another hand</handNote>: the letter of the Barons on the same in French, ending
                            imperfectly. The end is supplied in a <date>xvi</date>th cent. hand on two out of four small
                            leaves of paper inserted here</ab>

                        <ab>A notice of this Chronicle is in <ref type="bibl" target="Hardy 1871">Hardy III</ref>
                            361</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="69r" locusEnd="75v">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Walter of Henley</name>, <title>Hosebandrie</title>.
                                <title>Husbandry</title></head>
                        <head type="James"><title>Hosebondrie of <name type="author">Walter of Henley</name></title>,
                            and the anonymous <title>
                                <q>Husbandry</q>
                            </title></head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Advice from a father to his son on the management and improvement of his
                                estate</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>in French</quote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <quote>This treatise contains a succinct account of the mode of husbandry and rural economy
                                of the times: it appears to have been written in the reign of <name type="person">Edward
                                    III</name></quote>
                        </ab>


                        <rubric locusNew="69r">De Gaynag' terrarum</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="69r">Le pere dist a sun fiz. beau fiz viuet sagement</incipit>

                        <explicit locusNew="75r">viii Rousches dun galon de mel</explicit>

                        <ab>This is almost certainly the copy used by <name type="person">William Lambarde</name> in his
                            note-book of <date>1571</date>, now <ref type="ms" target="LBL709">Brit. Mus. Add.
                                20709</ref>, under the title <hi rend="italic">Du gaignage des terres</hi>. See the
                            edition by Dr W. Cunningham and E. Lamond (<ref type="bibl" target="Lamond 1890">Royal
                                Historical Society 1890</ref>), pp. xxxiii, xxxviii. Corrected by Dr Cunningham in <ref
                                type="bibl" target="Cunningham 1895">Transactions Royal Historical Society IX
                            1895</ref>, p. 215</ab>

                        <ab locus="153" locusNew="75v">On weights and measures, in Latin. Prices of bread, and of
                            colours</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="75v">Digitus pars minima mensurarum</incipit>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="76r" locusEnd="76v">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De nativitate et aetate Christi</title>
                        </head>
                        <incipit locusNew="76r">A mundi creacione usque ad <name type="place">Romam</name> urbem
                            conditam</incipit>
                        <ab>(on the Pope and Cardinals)</ab>
                        <ab>Distich on lower margin: <q><name type="place">Roma</name> capit marcas bursas exhaurit et
                                archas<lb/> Ut tibi tu parcas fuge papas et patriarchas</q></ab>
                        <ab locus="156" locusNew="76v">Natus est Christus in <name type="place">Betlehem</name> nocte
                            diei dominice qui primus et summus pontifex</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="76v">anno xxxiii baptizatur et crucifigitur</explicit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="76v" locusEnd="77r">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De stationibus Romae</title>
                        </head>


                        <incipit locus="156" locusNew="76v"><name type="person">Gregorius</name> primus instituit fieri
                            staciones</incipit>
                        <ab>List follows</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="77v" locusEnd="79r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The usage and customs of the community of <name type="place">Kent</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Les usages et les coustumes les queus la comunaute de <name type="place">Kent</name>
                                clayment aver en gavelikende et en gens gavelikendyes</title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="158" locusNew="77v">De legibus <name type="place">Kancie</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="77v">Ces sunt les usages e les costumes les queus la comunaute de <name
                                type="place">kent</name> clayment auer ... dunt il est dit en Kentoys þe vader to þe
                            boghe and þe sone to þe loghe</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="78v">ke furent deuant le conqueste e en le conqueste e totes houres dekes en
                            ca</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="160" locusNew="79r">De feod' fidelitatem faciend'</rubric>

                        <ab>Forms of oaths</ab>
                        <incipit locus="161" locusNew="79r"><name type="place">Cancia</name> est prouincia in <name
                                type="place">anglia</name> iuxta oceanum</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="79r">alia habet commoda vite mortalium necessaria que recitari per singula
                            longum esset</explicit>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="79r" locusEnd="81r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Veterinary recipes for horses</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De equis medicandis</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>
                            <quote>Gallice</quote>
                        </ab>

                        <incipit locus="161" locusNew="79r">Ceo est la marechausie de chiuals. Peleyn deit cure treys
                            aunz oue sa mere</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="79v">de vin blanc a beure chaud kant il auerad ankes erre</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="81r">Contra pugturam serpentis</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="81r">Accipe aquam benedictam</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="81r">bibat illam aquam qui portauit rumores et sic recedat</explicit>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="81r" locusEnd="86v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>The monasteries of <name type="place">England</name> and their founders</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De monasteriis in <name type="place">Anglia</name> et eorum fundatoribus</title>
                        </head>
                        <incipit locusNew="81r">In <name type="place">Pago Cantuar.</name> edificauit <name
                                type="person">Edelbertus</name>
                            <name type="place">monasteria Sancti Augustini</name></incipit>
                        <ab>The last is a note on <name type="person">Etheldreda</name>: <q>Velata erat apud <name
                                    type="place">eli</name> cum sorore sua</q></ab>
                        <ab>In another hand: a table in six columns, Reges, Anni, Archiepiscopi, Anni, Abbates,
                            Anni</ab>
                        <ab>From <name type="person">Ethelbert</name> to <name type="person">Edward II</name>
                            <handNote>in the original hand</handNote>. Archbishops to <name type="person">Johannes
                                frater minor (Peckham)</name> and <name type="person">Robertus</name>. Abbots to <name
                                type="person">Radulphus (Bourn)</name>. Continued by various hands to <name
                                type="person">Edward IV</name>, King, <name type="person">Thomas Bowseyr,
                                Archbishop</name>, <name type="person">William Sellyng, Abbot</name></ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="84r">De morte imperatoris</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="84r">Stante obsessione contra <name type="person">Lucam</name> usque ad
                            terminum .xxx. dierum</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="84v">et <name type="person">Regem Cicilie fredericum</name> suum constituens
                            vicarium domino reddidit spiritum</explicit>
                        <ab>pp. <locus locusNew="85r">173</locus>-<locus locusNew="86v">176</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="87r" locusEnd="87r">

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>De situ <name type="place">Ierusalem</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locusNew="87r">Situs <name type="place">Ierusalem</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="87r"><name type="place">Ierusalem</name>, Sepulcrum domini. Ista ecclesia
                            sita est in decliuo <name type="place">montis syon</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="87r">sex miliaria a <name type="place">mari galilee</name> vel
                            Tiberiadis</explicit>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>Another hand</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="87r">Acon distat a <name type="place">nazare&#541;</name> vii miliaria
                            etc.</incipit>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="87v" locusEnd="108v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Customary and excerpt from the privileges of the monastery of <name type="place">St
                                    Augustine's, Canterbury</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Custumale et excerpta ex privilegiis <name type="place">monasterii Sancti
                                    Augustini</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locus="178" locusNew="87v">Custumare</rubric>
                        <ab>List of dues from manors: Minster etc.</ab>
                        <ab>Distribucio cere (Candlemas). Distribucio argenti in festo Sancti Augustini</ab>
                        <ab>Longitudo stragule</ab>
                        <ab locus="180" locusNew="88v">List of priuilegia</ab>
                        <ab locus="182" locusNew="89v">Knights' fees</ab>
                        <ab>Temporalia of the Archbishop, Abbot, Prior etc.</ab>
                        <ab locus="184" locusNew="90v">Custumare: of bread etc.: a slip inserted giving particulars
                            about bread</ab>
                        <ab>Dues of various officers</ab>
                        <rubric locus="196" locusNew="96v">Mensurata terra maneriorum <name type="place">Sancti
                                Augustini</name></rubric>
                        <rubric locus="198" locusNew="97v">De sompniis</rubric>
                        <ab>double columns, alphabetical: crossed out</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="97v">Arma tractare mutacionem significat</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="98v">Zonam cingere valitudinem</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="203" locusNew="99r">De confirmacione cartarum. et visu franci pleggii</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="99r"><name type="person">Edwardus</name> deo gratias ... Inspeximus
                            cartam</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="101r">apud <name type="place">douor.</name>
                            <date>xxii die maii anno regni nostri vi<abbr rend="superscript">to</abbr></date></explicit>
                        <rubric locus="208" locusNew="101v">Visus franci pleggii</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="101v">Primes wus nus dirrez </incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="101v">par le serment qe wus auet fet</explicit>
                        <ab>Notes <handNote>in various hands</handNote>, <date>xiv</date> and <date>xv</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="209" locusNew="102r">Forma treugarum inter <name type="person">Regem Anglie</name> et
                                <name type="person">Robertum de Brus</name> (<date>1323</date>)</ab>
                        <ab>Unfinished</ab>
                        <ab locus="209" locusNew="102r">Privileges claimed by the Abbot of <name type="place">St
                                Augustine's</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="209" locusNew="102r">Interpretacio verborum. Saka. Idem est quod placitum etc.</ab>
                        <ab>The Latin ends with Forstalles. Then in French: <q>Sokne cest asauer sute de vos hommes ...
                                Ferdfaire cest seruice daler en host</q></ab>
                        <ab locus="210" locusNew="102v">Notes of cent. <date>xvi</date></ab>
                        <ab>In <date>1529. Oct. 31</date>. A robbery of plate</ab>
                        <ab>In <date>1531. 3 Id. Apr.</date> (and other dates). Removal of precious metals from shrines
                            of Saints <name type="person">Augustine</name>, <name type="person">Jambert</name>, <name
                                type="person">Mildred</name> etc. and other spoliations</ab>
                        <ab>In <date>1535</date> further spoliation</ab>
                        <ab>On p. <locus locusNew="103v">212</locus>: suuerderi &#954;&#945;&#8054;
                            &#966;&#953;&#955;&#8182;&#957;</ab>
                        <ab>pp. <locus locusNew="104r">213</locus>-<locus locusNew="105r">215</locus> blank</ab>
                        <ab locus="216" locusNew="105v">Accounts <q>De Bosc. superius apud <name type="place"
                                    >Tenterdenne</name></q>
                            <date>24 <name type="person">Edwardi III</name></date> and other similar accounts</ab>

                        <ab locus="218" locusNew="106v">Paragraph <q>per viam eleccionis capituli cum expediat via mixta
                                scrutinii et compromissi</q></ab>
                        <ab>Compromisarii traxerunt se ad angulum australem capituli quorum duo, viz. fratres <name
                                type="person">Thomas Ikham</name> et <name type="person">Henricus Tilmanstone</name>
                            etc.</ab>
                        <ab locus="218" locusNew="106v">List of monks and their votes (which are for <name type="person"
                                >William Thorne</name>, <name type="person">Thomas Ikham</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Michael Pecham</name>: the last was eventually elected Abbot)</ab>
                        <ab locus="220" locusNew="107v">Extractus de quadam tabula in ecclesia conuentuali Colcestre,
                            giving dates of foundation of <name type="place">Glastonbury</name>, <name type="place"
                                >Westminster</name> (A.D. <date>169</date>), <name type="place">St Augustine's</name>,
                                <name type="place">St Alban's</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="220" locusNew="107v">Application from <name type="person">Richard Cokman</name>,
                            custos in <name type="place">St Nicholas Church at Dover</name>, to <name type="person"
                                >Francis, Cardinal of the Four Crowned</name>, for an indulgence for an altar of the
                                <name type="person">Virgin</name> and <name type="person">St John of
                            Bridlington</name></ab>
                        <ab>The Cardinal seems to be <name type="person">Francesco Uguccione</name>, Archbishop of
                            Bordeaux, d. <date>1412</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="221" locusNew="108r">Epitaph of <name type="person">Archbishop Chicheley</name>,
                                <q>Pauper eram natus etc.</q></ab>
                        <ab>Receipt for gout, in French (<date>xiv</date>)</ab>
                        <ab>Note of date of canonization of <name type="person">St Thomas of Hereford</name>
                                (<date>1320, 14 kal. Mai</date>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="221" locusNew="108r">Epitaph of <name type="person">Peter Comestor</name>
                                (<date>xvi</date>)</ab>
                        <ab>p. <locus locusNew="108v">222</locus> covered with paper</ab>
                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 13.10.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
