<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC304">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>304</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>N. 22</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>186</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Iuuencus, Euangelia metrica</head>
                <head type="James">Iuvencus</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">250</height>
                        <width unit="mm">170</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">9.8 x 6.8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 1 + 115</extent>,
                        <layout>21 and 20 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>vii</origDate>, <handNote>in large
                        uncials on lines deeply ruled with a dry point. Two scribes have been employed</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1 flyleaf, A (three) I<num>8</num>-XIIII<num>8</num></collation>.</p>

                <p>This is the oldest manuscript of <name type="author">Iuvencus</name>.</p>

                <p function="Research">The description furnished by Mr Bradshaw for <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Zangemeister 1877">Zangemeister in Sitzungsberichte d. k. k. Akad. d. Wissenschaften in
                        Wien LXXXIV 553</ref>, and reprinted in <ref type="bibl" target="Humer 1891">Huemer's Juvencus
                        (Vienna Corpus), p. xxiv</ref>, may be given here:<lb/>
                    <q>MS. 304 in uncial letters probably of the <date>vii</date>th century, consisting of <layout>three
                            separate preliminary leaves, followed by 14 4-sheet quires, numbered in the centre of the
                            lower margin of the last page of each quire. There was probably a 15th quire of 2 sheets,
                            now lost, at the end of the volume. The pages contain 21 lines in the 1st, 13th and 14th
                            quires, and 20 lines through the rest of the volume</layout>. The measurement is 10 inches
                        by 6.75 or 7 inches in breadth. The text is written continuously (not in verses), with
                        punctuation at the end of each verse, and a larger and blacker letter at the beginning of each verse.<lb/>
                        <decoNote>The three preliminary leaves are ornamentally written in large capitals (11 lines to a
                            page), within borders, the first and last pages being enclosed in an arch, the rest within
                            rectangular borders</decoNote>. They contain the verses known in connexion with <name
                            type="person">St Isidore</name> and his Library <q>Sunt hic plura sacra</q> etc., but
                        differing from those in the editions both in order and matter <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda"
                            >(note that this is the earliest known copy of these verses)</supplied> and containing only
                        the Bible, <name type="person">Origines</name>, <name type="person">Hilarius</name>, <name
                            type="person">Augustinus</name>, <name type="person">Theodosius</name>, ending up with
                            <q>ecce <name type="author">Iuuencus</name> adest tibi</q>, and on the opposite page the
                        text of <name type="author">Iuuencus</name> begins without any rubric, the first preface being
                        written <decoNote>in the same fancy capitals</decoNote> as the verses of <name type="person">St
                            Isidore</name> thus (4<abbr rend="superscript">a</abbr>
                        <locus>4r</locus>); <name type="person">Mattheus</name> instituit ... the first preface ends
                            (4<abbr rend="superscript">b</abbr>
                        <locus>4v</locus>) <name type="person">Iohannis</name> fremit – misteria uitae | caluetii : ||
                        aquilini : | : siue iuuenci : so far <decoNote>in large fancy capitals</decoNote>, then
                        immediately in ordinary uncials: Immortale nihil – then on leaf 5<abbr rend="superscript"
                            >b</abbr> (<locus>5v</locus>) canentis, Dulcis iordanes ut xpo digna loquamur : ~ Rex fuit –
                        leaf 36<abbr rend="superscript">a</abbr> (<locus>36r</locus>) tetigit seruator ihs. sana
                        ministerium praebebat femina mensis: ~~ then at once in larger capitals: sapientissimi uiri
                        Iuuenci: xpiani : euangeliorum liber primus: explicit Incipit liber secundus caluetii ~ aquilini
                        ~ Inde philippus ait >>> these last words are <decoNote>in red</decoNote> but in ordinary
                        uncials, over leaf (36<abbr rend="superscript">b</abbr>
                        <locus>36v</locus>) it proceeds: cernes dubitare quiesce et proprios huc saepe greges ad pocula
                        duxit. Progrediens uide na oculis tueri licebit ad hoc seruator talia dicta detulit. Iamque dies
                        – the 2nd book ends, and the 3rd begins thus (67<abbr rend="superscript">a</abbr>
                        <locus>67r</locus>): turbasque reliquit. Explt Incpt liber tertius (<decoNote>in red</decoNote>)
                        Fuderat – the 3rd book ends, and the 4th book begins (93<abbr rend="superscript">b</abbr>
                        <locus>93v</locus>): hominum seletio fiet: Euangeliorum liber tertius explct (<decoNote>in
                            red</decoNote>) Incpt eiusdem liber . . (<decoNote>in black</decoNote>) quartus ? feliciter
                        ? (<decoNote>in red</decoNote>). Talia – The MS. breaks off book IV, verse 733, thus (115<abbr
                            rend="superscript">b</abbr>
                        <locus>115v</locus>) nunc meminisse decet qm planus ille solebat. The remaining lines, here
                        wanting, would occupy nearly 3 leaves of the next quire, which probably consisted of four leaves
                        only. There is no trace in the volume of the Library to which it belonged before the
                        Reformation; the only entry which seems to have given this information on the first page has
                        been carefully erased.</q>
                </p>

                <p function="Provenance">To this some remarks may be added. <lb/> As to the owners of the manuscript in
                    medieval times. There is, as is stated above, an erasure at the top of f. <locus>1r</locus>. It is
                    of one word only, of ten or twelve capital letters, apparently. The first letter might be A and the
                    last S. <lb/> On the margin of f. <locus>72v</locus> is neatly written (<date>x?</date>) the word
                    sugga. On f. <locus>75v</locus> at top in pale ink (as noted by <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Marold 1886">Marold</ref>) is the name <name type="person">Engelberga</name>
                        (<handNote>in a German hand</handNote> according to <ref type="bibl" target="Traube 1891"
                        >Traube</ref>). <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda"><ref type="bibl" target="Traube 1891">Traube,
                                <hi rend="italic">O roma nobilis</hi> p. 57</ref>, compares the marginal reference in
                        the <ref type="ms" target="CHB363">Berne MS. 363</ref> to <name type="person">Angelberga</name>
                        wife of <name type="person">Louis II</name>. <decoNote>A note in the College Library copy of
                                <ref type="bibl" target="Nasmith 1777">Nasmith's Catalogue</ref> records an opinion
                            (possibly that of <name type="person">Traube</name>) that the ornamentation of this MS. is
                            Hispano-Gothic</decoNote>.</supplied><lb/> The book has evidently been long in <name
                        type="place">England</name>. There are a good many marginal notes <handNote>in an English hand
                        of cent. <date>viii or ix</date>, rather rough</handNote>. There are also a few interlinear
                    glosses (all apparently in Latin) <handNote>in a neater hand of cent. <date>x</date> (?)</handNote>.
                    I incline to identify it with the <q>Juvencus in Romana scriptura</q> which is mentioned in our
                    oldest catalogue (<date>xii</date>) of <name type="place">Christ Church, Canterbury</name> (<ref
                        type="bibl" target="James 1903"><hi rend="italic">Ancient Libraries</hi>, p. 11, no. 152</ref>).
                    This had the mark HL, not now traceable in the manuscript. <lb/> Two features might suggest the
                    possibility that the book has a connexion with <name type="place">Spain</name>. These are (1) the
                    occurrence of Saracenic arches in the ornament of the preliminary leaves, (2) the passages from
                        <name type="author">Isidore of Seville</name> inscribed thereon.<lb/> But though pages framed in
                    horse-shoe arches do occur in early Spanish MSS. (e.g. those of Beatus on the Apocalypse) they also
                    occur in Italian art: see for instance a <name type="place">Monte Cassino</name> martyrology of
                    cent. <date>xii</date> in <name type="person">Mr H. Y. Thompson</name>'s collection (<ref
                        type="bibl" target="James 1898">Fifty MSS. I, p. 37</ref>). And the popularity of <name
                        type="author">Isidore</name> was early and wide-spread.<lb/> Nor is there any clear indication
                    of Spanish habits of orthography in the text. On the whole, it is probably safer to regard the book
                    as of Italian origin.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i + 1-115 + c-d</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="115v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Iuuencus</name>, <title>Euangelia metrica</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="1r">
                            <decoNote>Framed in a Saracenic arch. The arch is divided into 17 compartments in each of
                                which is an oval gem with a roughly circular eye. The shafts are each divided into six
                                compartments: each contains a rough pattern of leaves. Two sprays project from the top
                                of each shaft. The lettering on this page (and those which follow) is in capitals, drawn
                                in outline with the pen and having the thick strokes coloured with yellow or
                                green</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>On ff. <locus>1v</locus>-<locus>3v</locus> the writing is enclosed in rectangular
                                frames; these are decorated, some with continuous patterns, others with devices in
                                compartments: green, red and yellow are used</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>On f. <locus>3v</locus> the frame takes the form of a Saracenic arch
                                again</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>On f. <locus>4r</locus> and most of f. <locus>4v</locus> the writing is still in
                                outlined capitals, the strokes filled in with colour. The normal writing begins near the
                                bottom of f. <locus>4v</locus></decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>The colophon of Liber I is curiously confused. I give a full transcript</ab>
                        <ab locus="36r">
                            <lg>
                                <l>Sapientissimi uiri <name type="author">Iuuenci</name> :</l>
                                <l>xpiani : euangeliorum. (<decoNote>Red capitals</decoNote>)</l>
                                <l>Liber primus: · explicit (<decoNote>Black capitals filled with yellow</decoNote>)</l>
                                <l>Incipit liber secundus (<decoNote>Red</decoNote>) </l>
                                <l>Caluetii: aquilini. (<decoNote>Black capitals filled with yellow</decoNote>)</l>
                                <l>Inde <name type="person">philippus</name> ait (<decoNote>Red, smaller</decoNote>)</l>
                            </lg>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="36v">
                            <lg>
                                <l>Cernes dubitare quiesce (<decoNote>Black</decoNote>) (II 110)</l>
                                <l>Et proprios huc saepe greges ad pocula duxit (<decoNote>Red</decoNote>) (II 264)</l>
                                <l>Progrediens uide na oculis tueri licebit. (<decoNote>Black</decoNote>) (II 109*) </l>
                                <l> Ad hoc seruator talia dicta detulit. (<decoNote>Red</decoNote>) (Cf. II 425,
                                    etc.)</l>
                            </lg>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>Text of Liber II <decoNote>with red, yellow and green initial</decoNote> then
                                begins<supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda">.</supplied></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <q>Nomina sacra. DS XPS SCS SPS DNS IHS.</q>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>Neumes have been inserted in one or two places</ab>

                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: SP 3/11/08, RJR 13/11/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks: strange characters on p. 101 and use of macrons.</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
