<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>






                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC311">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>311</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>D. 8</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>39</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Latin Prose Brut chronicle</head>

                <head type="James">Chronicon Angliae</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">245</height>
                        <width unit="mm">175</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">9.6 x 7</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 4 + 104 + 2</extent>,
                        <layout>32 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv late or xvi early</origDate>,
                        <handNote>in a very current hand</handNote>.</p>


                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>4 flyleaves, 1<num>8</num>-13<num>8</num>, 2 flyleaves</collation>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-iv + 1-104 + v-vi + c-d</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="101r">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Latin prose Brut chronicle</title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Chronicon <name type="place">Angliae</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Nova cronica de gestis regum Anglorum cum aliis incidenciis rerum notabilium et
                                mirabilium eorum temporibus contingencium a primo rege <name type="person">Bruto</name>
                                usque ad annum XIIII regis <name type="person">Henrici sexti</name> sub compendio
                                congesta</title>
                        </head>




                        <ab>On f. <locus>iv</locus> receipt: <q>To a galon of Vergus made halfe of crabbis</q></ab>
                        <ab>Notes in Latin on <name type="place">Glastonbury</name>, on <name type="person"
                                >Bernard</name>, on tithes etc.</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>iir</locus>: Table of Kings of <name type="place">England</name> (<name
                                type="person">William I</name> to <name type="person">Edward IV</name>), with dates of
                            accession, length of reign, places of coronation and burial</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>iiiv</locus>: <name type="person">M<abbr rend="superscript">r</abbr>
                                Watts</name> byinge sycke of a tartion (=tertian) fevor and recouered by <name
                                type="person">M<abbr rend="superscript">r</abbr> Docter Wotton</name> taking the
                            counsell w<abbr rend="superscript">t</abbr> in 3 days after that of one <name type="person"
                                >Robert manne</name> who dwellethe nere to <name type="place">Grace churche</name> faste
                            by <name type="person">m<abbr rend="superscript">r</abbr> torpey</name> the potycarie gaue
                            the sayd <name type="person">watts</name> a medysen not knowen the tewesday before
                            mychaelmas daye w<abbr rend="superscript">ch</abbr>
                            <name type="person">watts</name> (corr. from pasloe) dyed w<abbr rend="superscript"
                                >th</abbr> in vi howers after</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>ivv</locus> erased and revived <q>Pertinet liber iste <name type="person">John
                                    Alyn</name> (or Alyuer) Ex dono <name type="person">Johannis Kyrklande</name></q>.
                            Also the title, as in <name type="person">Nasmith</name>, <handNote>in the hand of the
                                text</handNote></ab>

                        <ab>Text</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r"><name type="place">Britannia</name> que nunc <name type="place"
                                >anglia</name> dicitur</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>There are marginalia in hands of cent. <date>xv</date> and
                                <date>xvi</date></handNote>
                        </ab>


                        <ab>Ends with assassination of <name type="person">James of Scotland</name></ab>
                        <explicit locus="101r">legatus quidam apostolicus in <name type="place">Scocia</name> tunc
                            existens dicti Regis camisiam postmodum domino Pape ut dicitur deferebat</explicit>
                        <ab>At the bottom of the page: <q>finitus xix die Augusti</q></ab>
                        <ab>The rest blank</ab>
                    </msItem>




                </msContents>



                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text:copied from James.txt CF</p>
                            <p>markup: CF</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by CF, but not by a second person</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 01.06.2007</p>
                            <p>remarks: </p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>



            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
