<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC324">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>324</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>I. 6</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>97(1)</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Le Miroir des dames</head>
                <head type="James">Miroir des Dames</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">234</height>
                        <width unit="mm">161</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">9.3 x 6.5</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 2 + 298</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 24 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xiv</origDate>, <handNote>in fine
                        upright French hand, brown ink</handNote>.</p>
                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num> I<num>12</num>-III<num>12</num> (12 canc.) IV<num>12</num> V<num>14</num>
                        (14? canc.) VI<num>12</num>-XIV<num>12</num> (12 canc.) XV<num>12</num> XVI<num>12</num>
                            XVII<num>4</num> XVIII<num>12</num>-XXIII<num>12</num> XXIV<num>10</num> XXV<num>12</num>
                            XXVI<num>10</num> (wants 10)</collation>.</p>
                <p><label>2 fo.:</label>
                    <secFol>prudence. ainsi lisons</secFol>.</p>
                <p function="Provenance">From the Library of <name type="person">Charles V of France</name>.</p>
                <p function="Decoration">
                    <decoNote>The style of writing and ornament is fine French. Borders of ivy-leaf (with many gold
                        leaves) springing from straight bands of gold and blue. Smaller initials, blue with red
                        flourishing, and red with green-blue flourishing. On <locus>iiv</locus> near upper L. corner:
                            <name type="person">Charles</name>. F. <locus>1r</locus> is fully bordered. The miniature, a
                        small square one, is much rubbed and part of the background scraped off. It represents the queen
                        standing under a roof or canopy supported on gold shafts, a little white dog on R., on L. a
                        Franciscan kneels and presents a gold book. Two shields are in the border below. <hi
                            rend="footnote">(1) party per pale, dexter az. semee of fleurs de lys or, with a bend arg.
                            bearing an indistinct charge gu.: sinister az. damaged. (2) party per pale az. fleurs de lys
                            or: dexter has label of 3 points gu.: sinister plain.</hi></decoNote>
                </p>
                <p function="Research" rend="afterContents">The prologue was printed by M. L. Delisle in <ref
                        type="bibl" target="Delisle 1886"><hi rend="italic">Notices et Extraits</hi>, 1886</ref>, t.
                    XXXI, as also the Catalogue of <name type="person">Charles V</name>'s library in his <ref
                        type="bibl" target="Delisle 1881b"><hi rend="italic">Cabinet des MSS.</hi> III</ref> 192. A copy
                    occurs in the catalogue of the Library of the Louvre, the 2nd folio beginning <hi rend="italic">ter
                        et reposer</hi>. Two copies in <ref type="bibl" target="Barrois 1830">Barrois' <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bibliothèque protypographique</hi></ref> (Bruges Inventory of Bibliothèque de Bourgogne)
                    no. 949 (<hi rend="italic">le souverain Roy</hi>) and 950 (<hi rend="italic">Et des biens que j'en
                        ay eus</hi>) also 2131, 2 which are the same. Other copies are at Brussels, <ref type="ms"
                        target="BBR555">no. 9555</ref>, British Museum <ref type="ms" target="LBL986">Add. 29986</ref>
                    as well as in the Bibliothèque Nationale.<lb/>The present copy is thus described in the Inventory of
                    the Library of the Louvre drawn up in <date>1411</date>. <q>(No. 890.) Item le miroir des dames en
                        françois, de bonne lettre de forme, a deux coulombes, historié et enluminé, commençant au
                            ii<abbr rend="superscript">e</abbr> fo. <hi rend="italic">prudence ainsi li homs</hi>, et ou
                        derrenier <hi rend="italic">vertuz vengence</hi>, couvert d'une chemise de toille à queue, et ii
                        petiz fermoirs d'argent dorez, esmaillez de France, et une pipe de broderie</q> (<ref
                        type="bibl" target="Delisle 1907">Delisle, <hi rend="italic">Recherches sur la Librairie de
                            Charles V</hi>: 1907</ref>, I, p. 247).<lb/>It is worth noting that <ref type="ms"
                        target="CCC210">William Worcester (Itineraries, p. 275)</ref> speaks of owning a copy of this
                    book: <q>de libro vocato le myrrour de dames cooperto rubeo coreo.</q></p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. aa + bb (binding fragments) + a-c + i-ii + 1-298 + d-f</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="frm">Middle French.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="294v">


                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Le Miroir des dames</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Prologue</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="1r">Ci commence le prologue seur le liure qui est apelez le mireour des
                            dames</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Selonc ce que dit vns mestres qui est nomez <name type="person"
                                >vegecius</name></incipit>


                        <explicit locusNew="2v">et sens fin auec le souuerain roy regner</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="2v">Ci est mis le fondement de leuure ensuient</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="2v"><name type="person">Salomons</name> qui fu de sapience par le don de
                            dieu</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Partial border and shield (with billets <hi rend="italic">gules</hi> on bend)
                                suspended from a leaf</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Headlines in red, changing with the subject of the text</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Part I ends:</ab>
                        <explicit locus="195v">pour venir finablement a la coronne de gloyre qui durra pardurablement.
                            Amen</explicit>

                        <rubric locus="196r">La seconde partie principal de ce liure qui parle quelle noble dame doit
                            estre par acquisition quar elle doit aquerir sapience. Premier chapitre</rubric>

                        <incipit locus="196r">Au commencement de ce liure il fu dit que il contenoit iii parties
                            principax</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Partial border: hanging to one of the leaves is the shield with label of three
                                points <hi rend="italic">gules</hi></decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="233v">qui miex amoit morir que feyre aucune chose par doublerie ne par
                            simulacion</explicit>
                        <ab>(Part III)</ab>
                        <incipit locus="233v">Au commencement de ce liure il fu dit etc.</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Partial border, and shield with bend <hi rend="italic">argent</hi>, here bearing
                                no charge</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                        <explicit locus="294r">qui en trinite parfecte vit et regne pardurablement</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="294r">Ci finist le mireour des dames. pleyse a dieu que il leur profite aus
                            ames</rubric>
                        <ab locus="294r">Alphabetical table. Abstinence-Vengence</ab>
                        <ab><locus>296v</locus>-<locus>298v</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 8.10.07</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
