<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC348">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>348</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>9. 4</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>327 (2)</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Matthew Paris OSB, Historia Anglorum (1135-79). Continuation of Matthew Paris OSB,
                    Chronica maiora III (1259-72), Leges Anglicanae</head>
                <head type="James">Matt. Paris. Leges Anglicanae</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">322</height>
                        <width unit="mm">205</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">12.5 x 8.2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 139</extent>. Cent.
                        <origDate>xvi</origDate>, <handNote>in a very current ugly difficult hand for the most
                        part</handNote>.</p>


                <p function="Additions">Bound in double vellum leaf of accounts (<date>xv</date>) containing long lists
                    of persons. The only heading is <q>Adhuc Aula et Carnaria</q>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i + 1-141 + ii + c-d</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="65v">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Matthew Paris OSB</name>, <title>Historia Anglorum
                                (excerpt, <date>1135</date>-<date>1179</date>)</title></head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Historia <name type="author">Matthei Parisiensis</name> a morte <name type="person"
                                    >Henrici I</name>. ad annum <date>1179</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locus="1r">Ex <name type="author">Mattheo Parisiensi</name>. libri <name type="person"
                                >comitis Arundel</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locus="1r">Defuncto autem <name type="person">Rege Henrico</name></incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="62v">junior rex Torneamenta exercuit</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="62v">A. d. m<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> c<abbr rend="superscript"
                                >o</abbr> lxxix<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr></rubric>

                        <ab>This article is transcribed from the <q>Arundel</q> MS. (now <ref type="ms" target="LBLR07"
                                >Royal 14. C. VII</ref> in the British Museum). A more complete transcript is in <ref
                                type="ms" target="CCC056">no. 56</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="66r" locusEnd="93v">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Matthew Paris OSB</name>, <title>Chronica maiora III
                                    (<date>1259-72</date>)</title></head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Continuatio historiae <name type="author">Matthei Parisiensis</name> ab anno 44<abbr
                                    rend="superscript">to</abbr>
                                <name type="person">Henrici III</name>. ad obitum ejus</title>
                        </head>

                        <incipit locus="66r">Eodem anno Rex anglorum <name type="person">henricus tercius</name> a
                            conquestu anno regni sui quadrages. tercio in <name type="place">Galliam</name>
                            transfretavit</incipit>
                        <explicit locusNew="92r">per lincem designatum omnia penetrantem</explicit>
                        <ab>(finis vitae cum fat (?))</ab>

                        <ab>This article is transcribed from the <q>Arundel</q> MS. (now <ref type="ms" target="LBLR07"
                                >Royal 14. C. VII</ref> in the British Museum). A more complete transcript is in <ref
                                type="ms" target="CCC056">no. 56</ref></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="94r" locusEnd="98v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">Ine</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Inae regis</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="93r" locusNew="94r">The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS.
                                96</ref>, and this copy is called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903"
                                >Liebermann (pp. xx, xxii)</ref> Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="99r" locusEnd="103v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">Alfred the Great</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Aluredi regis West-Saxonum</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS. 96</ref>, and this copy is
                            called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (pp. xx, xxii)</ref>
                            Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="103v" locusEnd="105r">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">Alfred the Great</name> and <name
                                    type="person">Guthrum</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Aluredi regis</name> et <name
                                    type="person">Godruni regis East-Angliae</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS. 96</ref>, and this copy is
                            called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (pp. xx, xxii)</ref>
                            Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="105r" locusEnd="106v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">Edward the Elder</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Edwardi senioris</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS. 96</ref>, and this copy is
                            called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (pp. xx,
                            xxii)</ref>Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="106v" locusEnd="115v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">&#198;thelstan</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Adelstani</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS. 96</ref>, and this copy is
                            called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (pp. xx, xxii)</ref>
                            Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="115v" locusEnd="117v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">Edmund</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Edmundi</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS. 96</ref>, and this copy is
                            called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (pp. xx, xxii)</ref>
                            Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="117v" locusEnd="119r">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">Edgar</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Edgari</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS. 96</ref>, and this copy is
                            called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (pp. xx, xxii)</ref>
                            Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="119r" locusEnd="127v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">&#198;thelred the
                                Unready</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Ethelredi</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS. 96</ref>, and this copy is
                            called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (pp. xx, xxii)</ref>
                            Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="128r" locusEnd="138v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Laws and institutes of <name type="person">Cnut</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Leges et institutiones <name type="person">Kanuti regis</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The Laws are copied from <ref type="ms" target="CCC096">MS. 96</ref>, and this copy is
                            called by <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann (pp. xx, xxii)</ref>
                            Corpus</ab>

                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF, CF 2nd</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 8.10.07</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
