<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC420">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>420</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>N. 27</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>204</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Astrological and Astronomical Tracts</head>
                <head type="James">Astronomica</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">200</height>
                        <width unit="mm">142</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">8 x 5.5</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. cir. 200 written and 200
                        printed</extent>. Cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate>. <handNote>The hand of the manuscript portions
                        is an upright one somewhat resembling an <q>engrossing</q> hand</handNote>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">On the flyleaf and elsewhere the name <name type="person">Johannes
                    Eston</name>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-ii + 1-247 + iii-iv</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="eng">Latin and English.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="13r" locusEnd="124v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Astrological and Astronomical Tracts</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Tractatus valde dignus et multum approbatus quod licet permissione divina scire
                                ventura tam per revolutionem superiorum corporum quam diversorum aliorum signorum, Or, A
                                perfette instruccyon of astrologie with the carecters of the sygnes and planetts, and
                                also divers other good rules and notys with many divers judgements that be necessarye
                                and requysyte belongyng to the same.</title>
                        </head>
                        <rubric locus="13r">Sequitur tractatus valde dignus - signorum prout in prologo et aliis
                            auctoribus sequentibus patet</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="13r">Quamquam solus deus in sua potestate</incipit>
                        <ab>3 pages: the 3rd has quotations from <name type="person">Ptolomeus</name>, <name
                                type="person">Aristoteles</name>, <name type="person">Sibilla</name>, <name
                                type="person">Erigida</name> (!), <name type="person">lulhardus</name>, <name
                                type="person">Turcus</name> ad quendam Romanum Pontificem, Respons. pontificis.</ab>
                        <incipit locus="15r">Hereafter followyth a perfett Instruccyon of Astrologie with the Carecters,
                            etc</incipit>
                        <ab>21 pp. a break</ab>
                        <rubric locus="27r">The Natyuytyes</rubric>
                        <ab>ff. 2</ab>
                        <rubric locus="29r">Here begynith a techynge of the newe Calender with many other helpy thynges,
                            etc</rubric>
                        <ab>Miscellaneous tracts or sections follow including a collection of <q>Jugements</q> for
                            hidden treasure and the like</ab>
                        <ab>Later</ab>
                        <rubric locus="91r">Incipit Inuolucio spere</rubric>
                        <ab>in Latin</ab>
                        <incipit locus="91r">Duo sunt extremi vertices mundi</incipit>
                        <ab><decoNote>This has diagrams in colour</decoNote>. An English version follows</ab>
                        <ab>A good many blank leaves follow</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="117r">Then a short tract in English</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="120r">and a Centiloquium also in English</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="125r" locusEnd="179v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author" key="Johannes-003">Johannes Stoeffler</name>, <title>Almanach noua
                                plurimis annis uenturis inseruientia</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Ephemeridum opus <name type="author" key="Johannes-003">Ioannis Stoefleri
                                    Justingensis</name> mathematici a capite anni redemptoris Christi
                                    <date>MDXXXII</date> in alios XX proxime subsequentes ad veterum imitationem
                                accuratissimo calculo elaboratum, <name type="place">Tubinge</name> anno XXXIII K. L.
                                Feb. <decoNote>Cum effigie autoris ligno incisa</decoNote></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="125r">Printed, has at top<lb/>Liber <name type="person">Joh. Eston</name> prec.
                                iii<abbr rend="superscript">8</abbr> iii<abbr rend="superscript">d</abbr>.<lb/><name
                                type="place">Tubingae</name> per <name type="person">Hulderrichum Morhart</name>
                            <date>anno xxxiii kal. Feb</date></ab>
                        <ab locus="163r">Followed by a couple of quires mostly blank <handNote>but containing some
                                astronomical matter in <name type="person">Eston</name>'s hand</handNote></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="180r" locusEnd="239v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author" key="Abrahami-001">Abraham ibn Ezra</name>, <title>Liber introductorius
                                in iudicia astrorum qui dicitur Principium sapientiae, transl. by <name type="person"
                                    >Peter of Abano</name></title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="author" key="Abrahami-001">Abrahe Avenaris Judei</name> astrologi
                                peritissimi in re judiciali opera ab excellentissimo philosopho <name type="person"
                                    >Petro de Abano</name> post accuratam castigationem in Latinam traducta. <name
                                    type="place">Venetiis</name>
                                <date>MDVII</date></title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Printed. <handNote>The margins much scribbled in another hand</handNote></ab>
                        <ab><name type="place">Venice</name>
                            <name type="person">P. Liechtenstein</name>, <date>1507</date></ab>
                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 27/05/2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
