<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC044">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>44</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>I. 1</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>92</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Pontifical</head>
                <head type="James">Pontificale (CanterburyóEly)</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">330</height>
                        <width unit="mm">245</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">13.7 x 10</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 1 + 201</extent>,
                        <layout>20 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xi (and xvi)</origDate>, <handNote>The
                        original text is in a most magnificent round black script of the type which I associate with
                            <name type="place">St Augustine's, Canterbury</name></handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1 flyleaf, 1<num>8</num> (wants 1, 2) 2<num>8</num>-6<num>8</num> (wants 2) |
                            7<num>8</num>-16<num>8</num> (gap) 17<num>8</num>-24<num>8</num> | 25<num>8</num>
                            26<num>4</num></collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">It is probable to my mind from this <supplied>(the hand reminiscent of <name
                            type="place">St Augustine's, Canterbury</name>)</supplied> and from the invocations in the
                    Litany that the book was written at <name type="place">Canterbury</name>. But, as we shall see, it
                    belonged in <date>cent. xv</date> to <name type="place">Ely</name>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">On the flyleaf (<locus>i</locus>), <handNote>in the <origDate>xvith
                            cent.</origDate> hand</handNote> which reappears at the end, is:<lb/>
                    <q>Index huius pontificalis.</q><lb/> I do not think it is one of <name type="person"
                    >Parker</name>'s additions: it seems to me earlier.</p>

                <p function="Additions">The original hand begins <locus locusNew="iii">1r</locus> with a Preface in
                    Anglo-Saxon. Two leaves are gone and the first page has been erased, but the text of it is probably
                    recoverable.</p>
                <p function="Research"><ref type="bibl" target="Wanley 1705">Wanley (p. 109)</ref> prints the end of
                    this Preface, which ends on <locus locusNew="1">2r</locus>.</p>
                <p function="Additions" rend="withinContents">In the lower margin of f. <locus>189v</locus> (p.
                        <locus>386</locus>) is an erased inscription of cent. <origDate>xv-xvi</origDate>:<lb/>
                    <q><name type="place">Ely</name><lb/> Iste liber pertinet ecclesie Eliensi.</q><lb/> Above it an
                    inscription of <name type="person">Parker</name>'s date erased (probably as being erroneous). I read
                    the words:<lb/>
                    <q>... vocat(us?) The red book of ...</q><lb/> This seems to show that the writer of the note
                    confused this MS. with <ref type="ms" target="CCC422">MS 422</ref>, which was really <q>the Red Book
                        of Derby</q>; and that he or some one else realized the mistake and erased the note.</p>
                <p function="Additions" rend="withinContents">The writing is splendid throughout. <decoNote>The initials
                        are perfectly plain, in green, blue or red</decoNote>.</p>
                <p function="Research" rend="withinContents">The Coronation-service is used by <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Wickham Legg 1900">Legg, <hi rend="italic">Three Coronation Orders</hi>, p. xxxviii (pl.
                        3)</ref> and <ref type="bibl" target="Liebermann 1903">Liebermann, pp. xxi, 215, 365, 401, 416
                        (ordeals)</ref>. He calls it Ce and assigns it to <date>1040-80</date>.</p>
                <p function="Research" rend="withinContents">See also <ref type="bibl" target="Henderson 1875"
                        >Henderson, <hi rend="italic">Liber pontificalis Eboracensis</hi>, p. xxi</ref>.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + pp. i-iv + 1-84 (85-94 missing) + 95-274 + 274a-b + 275-366 (367-368 missing) +
                        369-410 + ff. c-d</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat" otherLangs="ang">Latin and Old English.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="2" locusEnd="386">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Pontifical</title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="2v" locusNew="2">Incipit ordo uel examinatio in ordinatione episcopi</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="2">Antiqua sanctorum patruum institutio</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="3">On the margin of p. <locus>3</locus> is the <name type="place">Ely</name> mark
                                <figure xml:id="figure89a"/></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="3">In the lower margin an erasure</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="3">
                            <q>Iste liber pertinet ecclesie ...</q>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="6r" locusNew="9">In nomine domini. Incipit ordo qualiter domus dei consecranda
                            est</rubric>
                        <ab locus="8v" locusNew="12">In the Litany we have: <hi rend="italic">Apostles</hi>
                            <name type="person">Petre ii</name>, <supplied>(p. <locus>13</locus>)</supplied>
                            <hi rend="italic">Martyrs</hi>: <name type="person">Stephane</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Quiriace</name>, <name type="person">&#198;lphege</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Line</name>, <name type="person">Clete</name>, <name type="person">Clemens</name>,
                                <name type="person">Syxte</name>, <name type="person">Laurenti</name>, <name
                                type="person">Vincenti</name>, <name type="person">Apollonaris</name>, <name
                                type="person">Dionisii</name>, <name type="person">Salui</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Blasi</name>, <name type="person">Mauricii</name>, <name type="person">Georgii</name>.
                                <hi rend="italic">Confessors</hi>: <name type="person">Benedicte II</name>, <name
                                type="person">Martine</name>, <name type="person">Hieronime</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Gregori</name>, <name type="person">Augustine</name>, <name type="person">Dunstane
                                II</name>, <name type="person">Audoene</name>, <name type="person">Pauline</name>, <name
                                type="person">Byrine</name>, <name type="person">Suuythune</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Guthlace</name>, <name type="person">Fursee</name>. <hi rend="italic">Virgins</hi>:
                                <name type="person">Tecla</name>, <name type="person">Iuliana</name>, <name
                                type="person">Margareta</name>, <supplied>(p. <locus>14</locus>)</supplied>
                            <name type="person">Cristina</name>, <name type="person">Eufemia</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Agnes</name>, <name type="person">Agatha</name>, <name type="person">Lucia</name>,
                                <name type="person">Cecilia</name>, <name type="person">S(c)olastica</name>, <name
                                type="person">Austroberhte</name>, <name type="person">&#198;theldrytha</name>,
                                <name type="person">Mildrytha</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="22">In a second Litany, where three of each order are invoked, we have: <hi
                                rend="italic">Martyrs</hi>: <name type="person">∆lphege</name>, <supplied>(p.
                                    <locus>23</locus>)</supplied>
                            <name type="person">Eaduuarde</name>. <hi rend="italic">Confessors</hi>: <name type="person"
                                >Benedicte</name>, <name type="person">Augustine</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Dunstane</name>. <hi rend="italic">Confessors</hi>: <name type="person">Tecla</name>,
                                <name type="person">Scolastica</name>, <name type="person">Brigida</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="47">Neumes occur first <supplied source="bla">here [actually, first apear on p.
                                    <locus>38</locus>]</supplied></ab>
                        <ab locus="76">After f. <locus>39v</locus> (p. <locus>76</locus>) a leaf is missing</ab>
                        <rubric locus="82">In consecratione altaris</rubric>
                        <ab locus="100">Consecratio Ciborii</ab>
                        <rubric locus="103"><supplied>Consecratio</supplied> pauimenti aecclesiae</rubric>
                        <ab>(alphabet not given)</ab>
                        <rubric locus="105"><supplied>Incipit</supplied> benedictio ad uestimenta sacerdotalia</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="108"><supplied>Consecratio</supplied> episcopalis tunicae</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="110"><supplied>Oratio</supplied> ad offertorium lintheamen</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="111"><supplied>Benedictio</supplied> corporalis</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="114"><supplied>Oratio ad</supplied> patenam</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="115"><supplied>Oratio ad</supplied> calicem</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="117"><supplied>Prefatio</supplied> eucharistialis uasculi</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="118"><supplied>Benedictio</supplied> turibuli</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="119"><supplied>Benedictio uel consecratio</supplied> thimiamatis siue
                            incensi</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="124"><supplied>In benedictione sanctae</supplied> crucis</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="138"><supplied>Benedictio ad</supplied> imaginem <name type="person">sanctae
                                mariae</name></rubric>
                        <ab>(et <name type="person">Iohannis</name>)</ab>
                        <ab locus="138">[Anglo-Saxon glosses occur on pp. <locus>138</locus>, <locus>140</locus>]</ab>
                        <rubric locus="143"><supplied>Benedictio</supplied> uexillorum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="146"><supplied>Ad</supplied> scrinium uel arcam</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="151"><supplied>Prefatio consecrationis</supplied> capsarum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="157"><supplied>Ad</supplied> signum aecclesiae (bell)</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="165"><supplied>In consecratione</supplied> cymiterii</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="174"><supplied>In</supplied> reconciliatione
                            <supplied>altaris</supplied></rubric>
                        <rubric locus="186"><supplied>Oratio in</supplied> consecratione baptisterii</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="188"><supplied>Oratio ad benedicendum</supplied> librum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="190">Benedictio ad generalem cultum aecclesiae</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="190"><supplied>Benedictio</supplied> super munus</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="192">Ad nouam capillaturam incidendam</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="193" locusNew="192"><supplied>Oratio</supplied> ad clericum faciendum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="200">Incipit ordo nouem ad aecclesiasticorum graduum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="243">Incipit ordinatio episcopi</rubric>
                        <ab locus="258">A gap after p. <locus>258</locus></ab>
                        <rubric locus="272">Missa in consecratione archyepiscopi</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="275" locusNew="274a">Ad processionem archypresulis de roma uenienti palliumque
                            offerenti</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="278">Incipit consecratio regis</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="301">Finit consecratio regis quam sequitur consecratio reginae</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="308">Incipit ordinatio monachi</rubric>
                        <ab locus="310">Litany, <name type="person">Petre ii</name>, <supplied>(p.
                                <locus>311</locus>)</supplied>
                            <hi rend="italic">Martyrs</hi>: <name type="person">Stephane</name>, <name type="person"
                                >∆lfhege</name>, <name type="person">Ead&#447;arde</name>. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Confessors</hi>: <name type="person">Benedicte II</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Augustine</name>, <name type="person">Dunstane II</name>. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Virgins</hi>: <name type="person">Tecla</name>, <name type="person">Scolastica</name>,
                                <name type="person">Mildry&#541;a</name></ab>
                        <rubric locus="329">Incipit consecratio abbatis</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="341">Orationes ad ordinandum decanum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="346">Benedictio super uestimentum uirginis</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="347"><supplied>Benedictiones dicendae</supplied> super uirginem</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="356"><supplied>Incipit benedictio</supplied> uestis uidue</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="357"><supplied>Benedictio</supplied> uidue</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="360">Benedictio super nouum uestimentum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="361"><supplied>Benedictio</supplied> ciuitatis</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="362"><supplied>Benedictio</supplied> ferri, ab episcopo danda</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="365"><supplied>Incipit</supplied> exorcismus aquae ad iudicium dei
                            demonstrandum</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="379">Incipit adiuratio ferri uel aquae feruentis ad iudicium</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="384">Incipit exorcismus panis ordeacii et casei</rubric>
                        <ab>The original hand ends here at p. <locus>386</locus> in the middle of a prayer</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="387">The end is supplied <handNote>in a hand of <origDate>cent. xvi
                                    early</origDate></handNote> which is meant to imitate the original</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="389">The same hand adds Adiuratio aquae. Exorcismus satis and exorcisms for a
                            possessed person</ab>
                        <ab>ff. <locus locusNew="400">196v</locus>-<locus locusNew="402">197v</locus> blank</ab>
                        <ab>On <locus locusNew="403">198r</locus>-<locus locusNew="405">199v</locus> the same hand has
                            added <handNote>in a much smaller script</handNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="198r" locusNew="403">
                            <q>Qualiter concilium agatur prouinciale prima secunda et tertia die</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="399" locusNew="405">
                            <q>Benedictio super regem tempore sinodi</q>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="399" locusNew="405"><supplied>Benedictio super regem</supplied> cotidiana</ab>
                        <ab locus="399" locusNew="405"><supplied>Benedictio</supplied> ab archiepiscopo in dissolutione
                            sinodi</ab>
                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: CF 14.10.2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
