<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC470">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>470</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>G. 13</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>74</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Kalendar of Norwich Cathedral Priory, Office of the Virgin, Litany, Prayers. Hildebert
                    of Lavardin, De mysterio missae. Lawrence of Durham OSB, Hypognosticon. Osbert of Bawdsey, De
                    expugnatione Lysbonensi. Sermon, Ab oriente uenerunt magi </head>
                <head type="James">Hildebertus, Laurent. Dunelmensis, Osbernus, etc.</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">155</height>
                        <width unit="mm">112</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">6 x 4.2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 2 + 149 + 2</extent>,
                        <layout>23, 29, 26, 31 lines to a page. Three main volumes of</layout> cent. <origDate>xii late
                        and xiii</origDate>, <handNote>in several hands</handNote>.</p>

                <p function="Multivolume"><lb/><label>Volume II:</label>
                    <handNote>in a very beautiful upright hand</handNote>, cent. <origDate>xii late</origDate>.
                        <lb/><label>Volume III:</label> Change of hand. <lb/><label>Volume IV:</label>
                    <handNote>in a good small clear pointed hand</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num>, 1<num>12</num> | 2<num>8</num> (wants 1) 3<num>8</num> 4<num>8</num> |
                            5<num>16</num> 6<num>12</num>-11<num>12</num> (+1) | 12<num>6</num> 13<num>6</num>
                            14<num>8</num> 15<num>6</num> (wants 6) | b (three)</collation>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">From <name type="place">Norwich</name>: on f. <locus>24r</locus> at top is the
                    press-mark N. lxix. The Kalendar is also of <name type="place">Norwich</name>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">A late and mutilated note on f. <locus>ir</locus> (<origDate>xv</origDate>).</p>

                <p function="Additions">Flyleaf, parts of two leaves of a <origDate>xiii</origDate>th cent. logical (?)
                    MS. with some scribbles: <handNote>one of these might be in <name type="person">Bucer</name>'s
                        hand</handNote>, another of cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate> is:<lb/><name type="person"
                        >Robertus</name> surgito cras et ito ad officium.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-ii + 1-149 + iii-v + c-d</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <milestone n="I" unit="volume"/>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="12v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Kalendar of <name type="place">Norwich</name> Cathedral Priory</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Calendarium</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="1r">Kalendar <decoNote>in red and black</decoNote> (<origDate>xiv early?</origDate>).
                            Each month occupies a leaf and has elaborate tables of the Cycles. January and February are
                            at the end</ab>


                        <ab locus="1r"><hi rend="bold">March</hi><lb/>
                            <name type="person">Adrian</name>, <name type="person">Perpetua</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Geretrudis</name>, <name type="person">Cuthbert</name>, added<lb/>
                            <supplied agent="NJM">Cuthbert is actually in the original hand</supplied><lb/> 24 Passio
                                <name type="person">S. Willelmi</name>, <decoNote>red</decoNote></ab>

                        <ab locus="2r"><hi rend="bold">April</hi><lb/>
                            <name type="person">Petri Martyris</name>, added</ab>


                        <ab locus="3r"><hi rend="bold">May</hi><lb/> 7 <name type="person">Domiciani</name>, added<lb/>
                            11 <name type="person">Engulphi</name>, added<lb/> 13 <name type="person">Seruacii</name>,
                            added<lb/> 19 <name type="person">Dunstan</name>, original<lb/> 20 <name type="person"
                                >Ethelbert</name>, original<lb/> 28, 29, 31 <name type="person">Germanus</name>, <name
                                type="person">Maximus</name>, <name type="person">Petronilla</name>, added</ab>


                        <ab locus="4r"><hi rend="bold">June</hi><lb/> 1 <name type="person">Nicodemus </name>(!) = <name
                                type="person">Nicomede</name>, added<lb/>
                            <name type="person">Bonefacii</name>, <name type="person">Medardi</name>, added<lb/> 25
                                <name type="person">Gallicani</name>, added<lb/> 27 vii dormientes, added<lb/>
                            <name type="person">Botulph</name>, <name type="person">Alban</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Etheldreda</name>, original</ab>


                        <ab locus="5r"><hi rend="bold">July</hi><lb/> 19 <name type="person">Wilgefortis</name>, added:
                            in margin <name type="person">Vncumbyr</name><lb/> 26 <name type="person">Anna</name>,
                            added<lb/> 31 <name type="person">Neoti</name>, <name type="person">Germani</name>,
                            original</ab>


                        <ab locus="6r"><hi rend="bold">August</hi><lb/>
                            <name type="person">Oswald</name>, <name type="person">Taurinus</name>, original<lb/>
                            <name type="person">Clara</name>, added</ab>


                        <ab locus="7r"><hi rend="bold">September</hi><lb/> 16 Transl. S. reliquiarum, original<lb/> 24
                            Dedic. eccl. <name type="place">norwyc</name>. <decoNote>red with octave</decoNote></ab>


                        <ab locus="8r"><hi rend="bold">October</hi><lb/> 6 <name type="person">Fidei</name>,
                                <decoNote>red</decoNote><lb/> 7 <name type="person">Osithe</name><lb/> 13 <name
                                type="person">Edwardi</name>, added<lb/> 17 Transl. <name type="person">S.
                                Etheldrede</name>, original</ab>


                        <ab locus="9r"><hi rend="bold">November</hi><lb/> 16 <name type="person">Edmundi C</name>.
                                <decoNote>red</decoNote><lb/> 17 added : <name type="person">Anian</name>. <name
                                type="person">Gengoul</name><lb/> 20 <name type="person">Emundi reg</name>.,
                                <decoNote>red</decoNote></ab>


                        <ab locus="11r"><hi rend="bold">January</hi><lb/> 15 Boniti et maur. orig.: marg. added: <name
                                type="person">Maka</name>, <name type="person">Antony</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Martha</name>, <name type="person">Emerenciana</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Timothy</name>, <name type="person">Polycarp</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Valerius</name>, <name type="person">Radegund</name></ab>


                        <ab locus="12r"><hi rend="bold">February</hi><lb/> 2 <name type="person">Brigide</name>,
                            added<lb/> 5 <name type="person">Gilberti</name>, added<lb/> Also <name type="person"
                                >Vedast</name>, <name type="person">Helen</name>, <name type="person">Sotheris</name>,
                                <name type="person">Faustinus</name>, <name type="person">Iuliana</name>, and (26) <name
                                type="person">Augustine</name></ab>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>The additions seem to betray the hand of a foreigner</handNote>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <milestone n="II" unit="volume"/>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="13r" locusEnd="23v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Office of the Virgin, Litany, Prayers</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="13r">Daily offices</ab>
                        <rubric locus="13r">Ante matutinas</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="13r">Ad dominum cum tribularer</incipit>
                        <incipit locus="13r">Omnipotens sempiterne deus qui facis mirabilia solus</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="13r">Matutinas de Sancta Maria</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="13r">Hymn. Quem terra</incipit>
                        <incipit locus="13r">Antiphon. Benedicta tu</incipit>
                        <ab locus="13v">Lectio I</ab>
                        <incipit locus="13v">O beata maria quis tibi digne ualeat</incipit>
                        <ab locus="13v"><supplied>Lectio</supplied> II</ab>
                        <incipit locus="13v">Admitte piissima</incipit>
                        <ab locus="13v"><supplied>Lectio</supplied> III</ab>
                        <incipit locus="13v">Sancta maria succurre</incipit>
                        <ab locus="14r">Capitulum in Lauds</ab>
                        <incipit locus="14r">Sancta et immaculata</incipit>
                        <ab locus="14r">Memoriae in Lauds</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="14v"><name type="person">Augustine</name> as confessor</ab>
                        <ab locus="15v">After Prime the Litany</ab>
                        <ab>Martyrs: <name type="person">Edmunde</name>, <name type="person">Albane</name>, <name
                                type="person">Wlfade</name>, <name type="person">Dionisi</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Maurici</name>, etc.</ab>
                        <ab>Confessors: <name type="person">Remigi</name>, <name type="person">Audoene</name>, <name
                                type="person">Germane</name>, <name type="person">Iuliane</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Aug. cum soc.</name>, <name type="person">Cuthberte</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Ceadda</name>, <name type="person">Swithune</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Benedicte</name>, <name type="person">Jeronime</name>, <name type="person"
                                >Leonarde</name>, <name type="person">Egidi</name></ab>
                        <ab>Virgins: none English</ab>
                        <ab><name type="person">Wlfadus</name> was honoured at <name type="place"
                            >Peterborough</name></ab>
                        <ab locus="17v">Tierce</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="19r">After Compline:</ab>
                        <rubric locus="19r">Oratio in parasceue ante crucem</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="19r">Domine Ihesu Christe fili dei uiui qui precepto patris nostre carnis
                            infirma suscipiens</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="20v">Oratio <name type="person">Anselmi Archiepiscopi
                            Cantuariensis</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locus="20v">Omnipotens deus et misericors pater</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="20v">Oratio <name type="person">Sancti Augustinni</name> ante lectionem uel
                            predicationem</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="20v">Deus lux mentium expelle a me stulticie noctem</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="21r">Oratio <name type="person">Sancti Ambrosii</name></rubric>
                        <incipit locus="21r">Christe pater misericordiarum</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="21r">Oratio <name type="person">uenerabilis Bede</name> presbyteri</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="21r">Domine deus qui es uera et eterna</incipit>
                        <incipit locus="21v">Omnipotens sempiterne deus respice propicius preces ecclesie tue</incipit>
                        <ab>ff. <locus>22r</locus>-<locus>23v</locus> blank</ab>


                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="24r" locusEnd="35v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Hildebert of Lavardin</name>, <title>De mysterio missae</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="author">Hildebertus</name>, de missa</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="24r"><name type="author">Hildebertus</name> super missam.<handNote> A smaller
                                hand</handNote></ab>
                        <incipit locus="24r">Scribere proposui quid mistica sacra priorum</incipit>
                        <ab>(<ref type="bibl" target="Migne 171"><supplied>P. L.</supplied> CLXXI 1177</ref>)</ab>
                        <explicit locus="35r">Cum pater ad dextram cedit. et explet opus</explicit>
                        <rubric locus="35r">Explicit</rubric>
                        <ab locus="35v">blank</ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <milestone n="III" unit="volume"/>


                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="36r" locusEnd="124v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Lawrence of Durham OSB</name>, <title>Hypognosticon</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title><name type="author">Laurentii Dunelmensis</name> hypognosticon ad <name type="person"
                                    >Gervasium</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <rubric locus="36r"><title>Yponosticon</title>
                            <name type="author">laurencii du(ne)lmensis</name> de ueteri et nouo testa- mentis. Incipit
                            liber primus</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="36r">Principium rerum sine tempore tempora formans</incipit>
                        <ab locus="124v">Liber IX ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="124v">Noster et iste liber qui primum cepit ab ipso. Completus per eum desinat
                            hic in eo</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="124v">Explicit iste liber sit laus tibi summe magister</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="124v">Explicit liber <name type="author">laurencii dunelmensis</name></rubric>
                        <ab>
                            <ref type="bibl" target="Raine 1880">The prologue and some excerpts were edited with other
                                works of <name type="person">Laurence</name>'s for the Surtees Society in 1880 by J.
                                Raine</ref>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>On the last few leaves of it are many grammatical verses and <handNote>notes in various
                                hands</handNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="124v">note on Alleluia</ab>
                        <ab>Grammatical verses</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <milestone n="IV" unit="volume"/>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="125r" locusEnd="146v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Osbert of Bawdsey</name>, <title>De expugnatione Lysbonensi</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="Nasmith">
                            <title>Expeditio Francorum Anglorum et variarum nationum ad obsidendum Ulissipona in <name
                                    type="place">Portugallia</name>, tempore <name type="person">Hildefonsi regis</name>
                                per <name type="author">Osbernum</name></title>
                        </head>

                        <head type="James">
                            <name type="author">Osbernus</name>
                            <title>de expugnatione Lyxbonensi</title>
                        </head>
                        <incipit locus="125r"><name type="author">Osbernus de Baldreseie</name> R. salutem. Qualiter
                            circa nos habeatur</incipit>
                        <explicit locus="146r">luctus eorum in gaudium. ut cognoscant te solum deum uiuum et uerum et
                            quem misisti Ihesum Christum filium tuum qui uiuis et regnas per omnia secula seculorum.
                            Amen</explicit>
                        <ab>Printed from this, the only extant copy, perhaps the author's autograph, by <ref type="bibl"
                                target="Stubbs 1864">Stubbs <hi rend="italic">Memorials of Richard I</hi>, I
                                cxlii-clxxxii</ref></ab>
                        <ab locus="146v">blank</ab>

                    </msItem>


                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="147r" locusEnd="149v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Sermon, Ab oriente venerunt magi</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="147r">
                            <handNote>A sermon in another good hand</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="147r">Ab oriente uenerunt magi in bethleem adorare deum</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="147r">Dominus nobiscum sit et deducat nos per uias rectas</incipit>
                        <ab locus="149r">Note from <name type="person">Gregory</name>'s Pastoralis and another</ab>
                        <ab locus="149v">blank</ab>


                    </msItem>


                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 9/1/2009</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
