<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC478">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>478</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>Misc. 25</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>384</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Armenian Psalter</head>
                <head type="James">Armenian Psalter</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">138</height>
                        <width unit="mm">98</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">5.4 x 4</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 2 + 251 + 2</extent>,
                        <layout>17 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xiii?</origDate>, <handNote>much of the
                        writing is faint and damaged</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>2</num>, 1<num>8</num> 2<num>10</num>-12<num>10</num> 13<num>2</num>
                            14<num>10?</num> (1, 2 canc. ?) 15<num>10</num>-17<num>10</num> (wants 8) 18<num>10</num>
                            19<num>10</num> 20<num>12</num> 21<num>10</num> 22<num>10</num> 23<num>12</num>
                            24<num>10</num>-26<num>10</num>, b<num>2</num></collation>.</p>

                <p function="Additions">On f. <locus>iir</locus>-<locus>iiv</locus> are small erasures.</p>
                <p function="Additions">On f. <locus>iiv</locus> (<origDate>xvi</origDate>):<lb/> Psalterium in lingua
                    et charectere armenica.</p>
                <p function="Research" rend="withinContents">It appears from <name type="person">Parker</name>'s
                    correspondence (pp. 265, 6, 71) that in <date>1565</date> he had sent a 'quayr of straynge
                    carecters' (so the <ref type="ms" target="CCC114A">MS. 114, p. 493</ref>) to <name type="person"
                        >Bishop Davies of St David's</name> to decipher. In a letter of <name type="person"
                        >Davies</name>' collaborator <name type="person">William Salesbury</name> (<ref type="ms"
                        target="CCC114A">MS 114, p. 491</ref>) to <name type="person">Parker</name> there is a postscript:<lb/>
                    <q>&#960;&#961;&#959;&#952;&#965;&#963;&#964;&#949;&#961;&#959;&#957;.
                        Yit to trouble your grace w<abbr rend="superscript">th</abbr> thys piece more
                        &#964;&#951;&#785;&#950;
                        &#965;&#788;&#963;&#964;&#949;&#961;&#959;&#955;&#959;&#947;&#943;&#945;&#950;.
                        After that my Lord by cwmferryng thies vnacquaynted
                        &#967;&#945;&#961;&#945;&#954;&#964;&#969;&#961; namely in the
                        wordes before tyme extracted cold fynd no consonant agreament, as in
                        &#x56b;&#x57d;&#x56b;&#x578; for Sion (meruaylyng to se the same lettre twyse
                        therin) and cold not make of it neither Walsh Englysh Dutche Hebrewe Greke nor Latin his L. gave
                        ouer to bestowe any more tyme theron. (And gave the matter to <name type="person"
                            >Salesbury</name><hi rend="footnote">Salesbury (see D. N. B.) had some reputation as a
                            philologist and was said to know nine languages.</hi> to settle: which he could not
                    do.)</q><lb/> This letter shows (a) that the book in question was Armenian, (b) that it had in it
                    words <q>extracted before tyme,</q> by the help of which <name type="person">Davies</name> tried to
                    read it. One of such words was Sion. Now the Psalter before us has, as noted above, many proper
                    names transliterated in the margin, and among these Sion occurs several times. I have no doubt
                    therefore that our book is that which was sent to <name type="person">Bishop Davies</name>.<lb/> The
                    identity of the person who succeeded in deciphering the book is worth investigating. It has been
                    thought, on the strength of a fragmentary letter in <ref type="ms" target="CTC335">Trin. B. 14.
                        52</ref>, that <name type="person">W. Lambarde</name> the antiquary had worked at Armenian. The
                    evidence is as follows: on the first leaf of that manuscript are six lines of Latin verse signed W.
                    L. (or W. P.) (forte <name type="person">Wilhelmus Lambarde</name>) says <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Wanley 1705">Wanley</ref>.<lb/> Below this, in a bad <origDate>xvi</origDate>th cent.
                    hand, is the following (printed with several mistakes in my <ref type="bibl" target="James 1900"
                        >Catalogue I 460</ref>: I have tried to correct the blunders here. See also <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Wanley 1705">Wanley, p. 169</ref>; <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype, <hi
                            rend="italic">Parker I</hi> 533</ref>):<lb/>
                    <q>Manye will Bragge of their knowledge and haveinge of Antiquities but the writer of the verses
                        above is the onlye man that ever I cold be acquainted with for the readinge of this boke and
                        other Antiquities, his Calender of the Byble maye apere to your grace but I most humblye beseche
                        you that y<abbr rend="superscript">e</abbr> paynfull workes by him gathered after your grace
                        hath perused might not be wraped vpp in obliuion how he hath traveled in the Armenian tongue may
                        apere ... </q><hi rend="footnote"><ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype <hi rend="italic"
                                >Parker</hi> I 533 (II 508)</ref> quotes the verses and the letter, and adds: <q>The
                            rest is wanting. The person that writ this I strongly conjecture to be <name type="person"
                                >Tho. Wotton Esq.</name>, and the worshipful, godly, and truly learned in antiquities
                            and a correspondent and friend of the Archbishop's.</q></hi><lb/> The identification of the
                    person here alluded to with <name type="person">W. Lambarde</name> depends on the correctness of the
                    interpretation of the initials W. L. (or P.).<lb/> The <q>Calender of the Byble</q> mentioned in the
                    letter ought to serve as a clue. There was a Calender of Scripture printed in 1575 (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="Sayle 1900">Sayle, <hi rend="italic">Early English Books</hi>, no.
                            96<supplied>8</supplied><!--(corrected from 969, James had the number slightly wrong)--></ref>)
                    which is attributed to <name type="person">William Patten</name> by <name type="person">Ames</name>.
                        <ref type="bibl" target="Tanner 1748">Tanner</ref> includes a Calendar of the Bible among <name
                        type="person">Lambarde</name>'s works, but merely on the strength of the documents quoted above,
                    which he had read in <ref type="bibl" target="Strype 1711">Strype</ref>. Another piece of evidence
                    seems to point strongly towards Patten as the person here alluded to. In <ref type="ms"
                        target="CCC575">Parker's Register</ref>, <name type="person">John Parker</name> adds to the
                    entry of this Armenian Psalter the following words: <q>8<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> perg. A
                        testimonie of Antiquities etc. cum alphabet' Armenico per Patten</q>. Among the printed books
                    given by <name type="person">Parker</name> to the College there is a tract corresponding to this
                    description, of which I will give particulars here. <figure xml:id="figure420b"/><figure
                        xml:id="figure421b"/><lb/> On the strength of this evidence I claim the position of the first
                    English student of Armenian for <name type="person">William Patten</name>. Plainly the initials in
                    the <ref type="ms" target="CTC335">Trinity manuscript</ref> should be read as W. P., not W. L.</p>
                <p function="Research">
                    <supplied agent="JamesCorrigenda"><name type="person">Professor Burkitt</name> has kindly supplied
                        the following note on the contents of the MS. It contains: <lb/>Pss. 1-17 (Greek, not English
                        numbers). <lb/>Exod. xv. <lb/>Pss. 18-35. <lb/>Deut. xxxii. 1-21. <lb/>Pss. 36-54. <lb/>Deut.
                        xxxii. 22-43. <lb/>Pss. 55-71. <lb/>Song of Hannah, I Sam. ii. <lb/>Pss. 72-88. <lb/>Isa. xxvi.
                        9-19 (sic). <lb/>Pss. 89-105. <lb/>Isa. xxxviii. 10-20. <lb/>[f. <locus>188r</locus>, originally
                        blank, has a note written by one <name type="person">Gregory</name>, not the original scribe of
                        the MS. I think.] <lb/>Pss. 106-118. <lb/>Isa. xlii. 10-13, xlv. 8. <lb/>Jonah ii. <lb/>Pss.
                        119-147 <hi rend="italic">Lauda Ierusalem dominum</hi>. <lb/>Hab. iii. f.
                            <locus>245r</locus>-<locus>247v</locus>. <lb/>Creed <locus>248r</locus>. <lb/>Prayer of
                        Manasseh <locus>249v</locus>-<locus>250v</locus>. <lb/>It agrees in the main with the <ref
                            type="ms" target="CUL676">University Library MS. Dd. 6. 76</ref></supplied>
                </p>
                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-ii + 1-227 + 227a + 228-250 + iii-iv + c-d</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="arm" otherLangs="lat">Armenian and Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="250v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Armenian Psalter</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="1r">rather damaged. <decoNote>Rough ornament at top in blue and
                            yellow</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>The incipits of the Psalms are added throughout in Latin in the margin <handNote>by a hand
                                of cent. <origDate>xvi early</origDate></handNote>. <decoNote>Many Psalms have rough
                                marginal ornaments at their beginnings</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="21v">After PS. xvii (xviii) <hi rend="italic">Diligam te</hi> is a psalm or
                            canticle marked: Non est de psalterio: and one similarly marked closes each division</ab>
                        <ab>On f. <locus>24r</locus> at the end of this is a scribble <handNote>in a hand of cent.
                                    <origDate>xv-xvi</origDate> and (<origDate>xvi</origDate>)</handNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="24r">Sunt hic octo libri. Et ultimus psalmus in unoquoque libro non est de psalterio </ab>
                        <ab locus="24v">blank</ab>
                        <ab locus="25r">Book II. <hi rend="italic">Celi enarrant</hi></ab>
                        <ab locus="53v" locusNew="55v">blank</ab>
                        <ab locus="56r">Book III. <hi rend="italic">Noli emulari</hi></ab>
                        <ab locus="90v">blank</ab>
                        <ab>Proper names are often transliterated in the margin</ab>
                        <ab locus="91r">Book IV. <hi rend="italic">Miserere mei deus</hi></ab>
                        <ab><decoNote>At the end of this book are three full-page (or nearly so) pictures in frames with
                                red and green grounds: yellow, red and green are almost the only colours</decoNote>.
                            They seem to me to be by an European hand and not later than cent.
                            <origDate>xiii</origDate></ab>
                        <ab locus="119v">
                            <decoNote>The Virgin crowned, seated, holding up a small fruit. The Child robed in green on
                                her knee</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="120r">
                            <decoNote>The Crucifixion with <name type="person">Mary</name> and <name type="person"
                                    >John</name>. Sun and Moon above</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="120v">
                            <decoNote>Christ seated in the rainbow, in vesica, with book, blessing. Evangelistic emblems
                                in the spandrels</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="121r">Book V. <hi rend="italic">Quam bonus israel</hi></ab>
                        <ab locus="155v">blank</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="156r">Book VI. <hi rend="italic">Domine refugium</hi></ab>
                        <ab locus="156r">blank <supplied>[there appears to be no blank in this section, or before the
                                next book]</supplied></ab>
                        <ab locus="189v" locusNew="187v">An obliterated rubric</ab>
                        <ab locus="189r" locusNew="188v">Book VII. <hi rend="italic">Confitemini domino quoniam
                                bonus</hi> (CVII)</ab>
                        <ab locus="219v">blank</ab>
                        <ab locus="220r">Book VIII. <hi rend="italic">Ad dominum cum tribularer</hi></ab>
                        <ab>Ends f. <locus>250v</locus> (251)</ab>
                        <ab>Two blank leaves follow <supplied>(ff.
                            <locus>iiir</locus>-<locus>ivv</locus>)</supplied></ab>


                    </msItem>




                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt BA</p>
                            <p>markup: BA</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 30/01/2009</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
