<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC485">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>485</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Bible</head>
                <head type="James">Biblia</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">260</height>
                        <width unit="mm">175</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">10.3 x 6.8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 3 + 379</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 54 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate>, <handNote>in a
                        very good small hand</handNote>.</p>
                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>4</num> (1 lining cover, 4 gone), 1<num>16</num>-12<num>16</num> (16 canc.) |
                            13<num>16</num>-24<num>16</num> (wants 15, 16)</collation>.</p>
                <p function="Provenance">At the bottom of the page <supplied>(f. <locus>ir</locus>), in a different hand
                        from the booklist described below</supplied>: <lb/>Hunc librum concessit mihi et deliberauit
                    ven. in X<abbr rend="superscript">o</abbr> pater et <name type="person">dominus Reg. Abbas</name>
                    <name type="place">monasterii S. petri Glouc.</name> quousque <name type="person">Johannes
                        Orchard</name> monachus dicti monasterii mihi solverit xxvj<abbr rend="superscript">s</abbr>
                        viij<abbr rend="superscript">d</abbr> nomine <name type="person">Johannis Twenyng</name>
                    monachi, etc. Et predicto ven. patri <name type="person">Reg.</name> tradidi librum scilicet Bibliam
                    quam implegiauit michi dictus <name type="person">J. Twenyng</name>.<lb/> The Abbot in question is
                        <name type="person">Reginald de Haunne</name>, who presided from <date>1263</date> to
                        <date>1284</date>.<lb/> There is little room for doubt that the book is from <name type="place"
                        >Gloucester</name>.<lb/> The flyleaves supply some interesting records. In the cover is written
                        (<date>xiii</date>):<lb/> Hunc librum fecit scribi <name type="person">Robertus de
                        Aldeswyrth</name> (<name type="place">Aldsworth</name> is near <name type="place"
                        >Gloucester</name>).<lb/> Sum de communi. nolo fieri specialis<lb/> Tradar sic uni quod cunctis
                    sim generalis.<lb/> qui me furatus fuerit aut alienauerit. sit ille maledictus.<lb/> Plectatur pena
                    tali quod sit anathema.<lb/> Then in a <date>xvi</date>th cent. hand, with a thick line drawn
                    through it:<lb/> Sum <name type="person">Richardi Mirre</name> emptus de <name type="person"
                        >Willelmo Davis</name> Clerico. </p>


                <p function="Binding">Brown leather binding with later stamp in gold of crest: a stag's head and neck
                    erased, surrounded by garter and surmounted by baron's coronet.</p>

                <p function="Additions">Press-mark C. 3. 21.</p>


                <p function="Additions">On the next leaf <supplied>(f. <locus>ir</locus>)</supplied>, <handNote>in a
                        good set hand of cent. <date>xiii</date></handNote>:<lb/> Hii sunt libri <name type="person"
                        >Roberti de Aldesword'</name>. videlicet <lb/> Quinque biblie. quarum una est apud Hereford.
                    <lb/> Item duo spalteria glosata.<lb/> Item Decreta et Decretalia. <lb/> Item Scolastica historia.
                    <lb/> Item Ecclesiasticus et liber sapientie glosati. <lb/> Item Epistole canonice glosate. <lb/>
                    Item Due summe de uirtutibus et alia summa <name type="person">Petri cantoris</name> parisiasensis
                    et tractatus qui uocatur templum domini in uno uolumine. <lb/> Item Summa de uitiis et testamentum
                    patriarcharum. <lb/> Item Summa <name type="person">gaufridi</name>. <lb/> Item Summa <name
                        type="person">Reymundi</name> et tractatus de anima ualde subtilis. <lb/> Item Summa que dicitur
                    qui bene presunt. et <name type="person">Rabanus</name> de corpore domini et glose super quartum
                    librum sententiarum. et Meditationes <name type="person">S. Bernardi</name>. et liber de quantitate
                    anime. et exceptiones de confessione b. <name type="person">Augustini</name>. <lb/> Item tractatus
                    super XII prophetas cum quibusdam nouis constitutionibus papalibus et generalis capituli. <lb/> Item
                    Sententie <name type="person">lumbardi</name>. <lb/> Item Summa <name type="person">Willelmi
                        Autisiodor'</name> super sentencias. <lb/> Item liber qui uocatur Gemma sacerdotalis. <lb/> Col.
                    2. <lb/> Item Sermones <name type="person">S. cantuar.</name> et glose super ecclesiasticum et summa
                    super sententias. <lb/> Liber qui uocatur disciplina lingue. cum sermonibus <name type="person"
                        >Manducatoris</name> et dominica oratio multipliciter exposita. <lb/> Item tractatus super
                    cantica canticorum. <lb/> Item Speculum ecclesie et summa de penitentia et expositio super
                    euuangelia dominicalia. <lb/> Item moralia super Iob. Item ferrum situ (i.e. <name type="person"
                        >Alex. Neckam</name>'s Corrogationes). <lb/> Item tractatus super xii prophetas. <lb/> Item
                    liber de claustro anime. Item expositio super exodum. <lb/> Item destinsiones super spalterium.
                    <lb/> Item prouerbia et edificatoria alia <name type="person">W. Cancelar' Lincol.</name> edita.
                    Item <name type="person">Boecius</name> de trinitate. <lb/> Item sermones <name type="person"
                        >Roberti pullani</name>. <lb/> Item tract. de fide spe et caritate. <lb/> Item tract. super
                        eccl<abbr rend="superscript">um</abbr>. It. spalterium. <lb/> Item <name type="person"
                        >belet</name> et <name type="person">Innocent.'</name> super missam et multiplices super canonem
                    misse tractatus. <lb/> Item tract. super epp. et euuangelia dominicalia. <lb/> Item tract. <name
                        type="person">bonauentur'</name> super sententias. <lb/> Item exp. super epp. et euuang. domin.
                    et sermones de precipuis festiuitatibus anni. </p>
                <p function="Additions">On the verso <supplied>(f. <locus>iv</locus>)</supplied>, <handNote>in a hand of
                        cent. <date>xvi</date></handNote>:<lb/> What dayes of the moone are good or bad for certayne
                    thinges heere specified. A list follows. </p>

                <p>On the next leaf <supplied>(f. <locus>iir</locus>)</supplied>, <handNote>in a large fine set hand
                            (<date>xiii-xiv</date>)</handNote>, a list of the books of the Bible. Genesis i<abbr
                        rend="superscript">us</abbr>. Exodus ii<abbr rend="superscript">us</abbr> etc., to Apochalipsis
                        lxii<abbr rend="superscript">us</abbr>. There is nothing erratic in the list. The verso is
                    blank.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-ii + 1-381</foliation>.</p>
                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="381v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Bible</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">Prologues</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Frater Ambrosius</incipit>
                        <incipit locusNew="3r">Desiderii mei</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="3r">Genesis-Deut.</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="62r">Jos. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="70r">Iud.</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="78r">Ruth</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="79r">Reg. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="119v">Paral. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab>No prayer of Manasses</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="141r">Ezr. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="144v">Neh.</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="149v">Esth. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="153v">Tob. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="157r">Iud. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="162r">Iob (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab>Followed by</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="170v">Job exemplar patientie etc.</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="171r">Psalter (Gall.)</ab>
                        <ab><locus>191v</locus> blank</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="192r">Prov. (pr.) - Eccl.</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="202r">Cant. (in dialogue with rubrics)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="203v">Sap. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="208v">Ecclus.</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="223r">Oratio Salomonis</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="224r">Isa.-Ezech. (proll.)</ab>
                        <ab>At the end of Ezech. is a paragraph</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="272r">Ubicunque medicina uel sanitas necessaria est <name type="person"
                                >Raphael</name> uadit. Interpretations of several names are given, ending with: <name
                                type="person">Zacharias</name> lingua syra adiutor. mundum muliebrem cultam dicit in
                            auro</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="272r">Dan. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="278v">Twelve Prophets (proll.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="291r">Macc. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="308r">Evv. (pr. Matheus ex iuda, etc. Luke has pr. at end)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="341v">Paul. Epp. (proll.: Romani sunt partes <name type="place"
                            >ytalie</name>)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="362r">Acts (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="372r">Cath. Epp. (pr.)</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="376v">Apoc. (pr. of <name type="person">Gilbert</name>)</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="376v">Omnes qui pie uolunt uiuere.</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="381v">At the end of Apoc. is written (<origDate>xvii</origDate>): A prophesie
                            found vnder y<abbr rend="superscript">e</abbr> ground foundation of <name type="place">S.
                                Denis</name> in fraunce, written in hebrue. <lb/>
                            <date>1620</date> Generall warres in <name type="place">Italie</name>. <lb/>
                            <date>1622</date> There shall be no Pastor. <lb/> ...... <lb/>
                            <date>1630</date> All flouds shall drie up and there shalbe but one Pastor</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="381v">At the bottom of the page in another hand (<origDate>xvi</origDate> or
                                <origDate>xvii</origDate>): Biblia hec sacra per <name type="person">S.
                                Hieronumum</name> translata et manuscripta hec sunt <name type="person">Gulielmi
                                Roberts</name>. Ex dono <name type="person">Hieremiae Martyn</name> medicinae
                            doctoris</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="bib">On the lining of the last cover are earlier inscriptions:<lb/> (a) an erasure
                            of some lines</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="bib">(b) <lg>
                                <l>Quisquis eris qui transieris pro me precor ora</l>
                                <l>Sum quod eris fueram quod et es sta perlege plora</l>
                            </lg></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="bib">(c) In the hand of the <name type="place">Gloucester</name> inscription at
                            the beginning: <lg>
                                <l>Omnis claustralis perfesse (professe?) sub ordinis alis</l>
                                <l>Respice deuote passus sum qualia pro te</l>
                                <l>In claustro mecum residens sis sum quia tecum</l>
                                <l>Per claustri sedem celi lucraberis edem. Wylls (?) (erased)</l>
                            </lg></ab>

                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The decoration of the book is odd and seems to me provincial. No gold seems to
                                occur: there is an unusual yellow, and a blue-green (e.g. Judges and Philippians). White
                                dots and rings are copiously used (e.g. Joshua)</decoNote>
                        </ab>


                        <ab>The notable initials are</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">
                            <decoNote>Prologue. The usual writing figure</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="3r">
                            <decoNote>Genesis. Six pictures of the days of creation</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="18v">
                            <decoNote>Exodus. A group of four figures</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="30v">
                            <decoNote>Levit. Two figures: the one on R. looks out of a window or door</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="79v">
                            <decoNote>Note the colouring of I Reg</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="90v">
                            <decoNote>2 Reg. Outline sketch of a king in the margin</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="129r">
                            <decoNote>2 Par. has odd gay colouring</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="171r">
                            <decoNote>Ps. 1. David playing the harp</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The Nocturnes and the triple division are marked by decorative initials</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="179v">
                            <decoNote>Salvum me fac. A man in the water</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="181v">
                            <decoNote>Exultate. Man on horseback looking back to L. and holding up a rod</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="184r">
                            <decoNote>Cantate and Domini exaudi each have a black monk praying</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="186r">
                            <decoNote>Dixit dominus. Christ throned, blessing</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="192r">
                            <decoNote>From Prov. to Ecclus. the initials are in red and blue with delicate penwork, very
                                bright in colour</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="224r">
                            <decoNote>With Isaiah the polychrome initials begin again. No more figured initials
                                occur</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="341v">
                            <decoNote>The Pauline Epistles show some very strange combinations of colour</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJM 20. 8. 2008</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
