<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC540">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>540</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Book of Hours (Use of Rome)</head>
                <p>
                    <supplied>This MS description is not part of the M. R. James catalogue.</supplied>
                </p>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">160</height>
                        <width unit="mm">110</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">6.5 x 4.5</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 217</extent>. Single
                    column of 17 lines. <handNote>Writing and decoration Avignon</handNote>, <origDate>late 14th
                        cent.</origDate></p>

                <p function="Binding">
                    <decoNote>Binding of 19th cent. stamped with fleur-de-lis.</decoNote>
                </p>

                <p function="Provenance">Early owner in the neighbourhood of <name type="place">Cordes-sur-Ciel, near
                        Albi</name>. A note of the building of the <name type="place">Château de Cordes</name> in
                        <date>1222</date> is added on November 7th in the Calendar. The town was fortified at that time
                    by <name type="person">Raymond VIII, count of Toulouse</name>, following the sack by <name
                        type="person">Simon de Montfort</name> in <date>1215</date> during the Albigensian Crusade.
                    Given to the College by <name type="person">Almeric Hugh Paget, First Baron Queenborough</name>, in
                        <date>1923</date>. A label on f. <locus>ir</locus> records this. It came up for sale at
                    Sotheby’s on <date>21 November 1923</date>, lot 403, with a description wrongly dating the
                    manuscript to 1340-48 which is based on an indulgence promulgated in <date>1348</date> on f.
                        <locus>213v</locus>, and ascribing, also wrongly, the illumination to the artist of the Hours of
                        <name type="person">Jeanne d’Evreux, queen of France</name>. <name type="person">Sir Geoffrey
                        Butler</name>, Fellow Librarian, wrote to <name type="person">Lord Queenborough</name> on
                        <date>31 October 1923</date>, “You asked me from time to time to report to you when anything of
                    interest turned up in Sotheby’s catalogues”, drawing his attention to various items, including lot
                    403. The letter is enclosed in <name type="person">Lord Queenborough</name>’s copy of <ref
                        type="bibl" target="Masters and Lamb 1831">Masters' History of Corpus 1831</ref> now in the
                    library at <name type="place">Leeds Castle, Kent</name>. The manuscript may have interested Butler
                    from the apparent similarity to <ref type="ms" target="CCC324">MS 324</ref> which may have been
                    illuminated for <name type="person">Jeanne d’Evreux</name>. <name type="person">Lord
                        Queenborough</name> agreed, he bought the manuscript for £100 and gave it to the College.</p>


                <p function="Decoration"><decoNote>Framed miniatures, illuminated ornamental initials, line endings and
                        borders. The style of all these can be compared with Avignon illumination of the late fourteenth
                        century as noted by C. de Hamel in <ref type="bibl" target="de Hamel 2007">The Parker Chronicle,
                            3, 2007, pp. 12-13</ref></decoNote>. He considers it is likely that the book was made at
                        <name type="place">Avignon</name> c. <date>1390-1400</date>, and notes that the text is
                    consistent with Books of Hours from <name type="place">Avignon</name>, with two citations of papal
                    indulgences from there, including that of <date>1348</date>. <decoNote>Also, the illustrated Hours
                        of St Catherine, fols. <locus>163r</locus>-<locus>166v</locus>, is a feature of books from
                        Avignon (others include <ref type="ms" target="BNF527">Paris, BnF, ms. lat 10527</ref>, fols.
                        59r-67v, <ref type="ms" target="ONB450">Vienna, ÖNB cod. s.n. 9450</ref>, fols. 189r-196v, and
                            <ref type="ms" target="NYPS49">New York Public Library, Spencer ms 49, II</ref>, ff.
                        17v-27v). These three manuscripts and about half a dozen others are all related in style to
                        Corpus MS 540; some of them are by the artist <name type="person">Giovanni de Tolosa, or Jean of
                            Toulouse</name>, recorded in the accounts of <name type="person">Clement VII</name>,
                        antipope in <name type="place">Avignon</name>
                        <date>1378-94</date></decoNote>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i + 1-217 + ii</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>

                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="3v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Indulgence and prayers to <name type="person">St Sebastian</name></title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <handNote>By a different scribe, probably added at a later date than that of the main
                                text</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="1r">Indulgence for attending masses</ab>
                        <incipit locus="1r">Si quis vult clemenciam altissimi salvatoris exorare</incipit>
                        <ab>Gives an offer of an indulgence of 100 days for attending certain masses which are listed
                            with the texts of their introits: De adventu - Ad te levavi; De nativitate - Puer natus; De
                            apparicione Domini (i.e. Epiphany) - Ecce advenit; De dominica lx (i.e. Sexagesima) - Exurge
                            quare; De resurrectione (Easter Sunday) - Resurrexi; De ascensione - Viri Galilei; De
                            pentecoste - Spiritus Domini; De cruce (Invention of the Holy Cross) - Nos autem gloriari;
                            De Maria - Vultum tuum; De assumpcione - introit not listed; De apostolis - Mihi autem; De
                            angelis - Benedicite dominum. The list ends on f. <locus>2v</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="3r" locusEnd="3v">
                        <head type="CCC">Suffrage for <name type="person">St Sebastian</name></head>
                        <incipit>O martir beatissime miles Christi</incipit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="4r" locusEnd="15v">
                        <head type="CCC">Calendar</head>

                        <ab><decoNote>Calendar written in red and black with the KL’s in gold with blue and pink red
                                frames and infills with short extensions of gold ivy leaves</decoNote>. Contains saints
                            of the region of <name type="place">Albi</name> and <name type="place">Rodez</name>, and an
                            added note on Nov. 7th records the building in <date>1222</date> of the castle of <name
                                type="place">Cordes</name>. <name type="place">Cordes</name> is between <name
                                type="place">Albi</name> and <name type="place">Rodez</name>. This suggests that the
                            owner of the book perhaps lived in or near <name type="place">Cordes</name></ab>

                        <ab>July 23rd <name type="person">Sigolena</name> - born in the seventh century near <name
                                type="place">Albi</name></ab>
                        <ab>Sept. 6th <name type="person">Eugenius Ep.</name> - died at <name type="place">Albi</name>
                            in <date>505</date> - the feast of the translation of his relics</ab>
                        <ab>Sept. 7th <name type="person">Carissima</name> - born at <name type="place">Albi</name> in
                            the fifth century</ab>
                        <ab>Sept. 10th <name type="person">Salvius Ep.</name> - bishop of <name type="place">Albi</name>
                            in the sixth century</ab>
                        <ab>Oct. 16th <name type="person">Gratus</name> - martyred c. <date>316</date> in the diocese of
                                <name type="place">Rodez</name></ab>
                        <ab>Nov. 4th <name type="person">Amancius Ep.</name> - the first bishop of <name type="place"
                                >Rodez</name> d. c. <date>445</date></ab>
                        <ab>Nov. 5th <name type="person">Martiana</name> - born at <name type="place">Albi</name> in the
                            eighth century - her relics were preserved at the cathedral</ab>
                        <ab>Nov. 7th Anno domini <date>1222</date> fuit edificatum <name type="place">castrum de Cordua
                                albigensii</name> per comitem tholosani</ab>
                        <ab>Nov. 13th <name type="person">Dalmacius Ep.</name> - Bishop of <name type="place"
                                >Rodez</name>, d. c. <date>581</date></ab>
                        <ab>Dec. 11th <name type="person">Paul of Narbonne</name> - patron of the neighbouring dioceses
                            of <name type="place">Carcassonne</name> and <name type="place">Narbonne</name></ab>

                        <ab>f. <locus>16r</locus>-<locus>16v</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="17r" locusEnd="21r">
                        <head type="CCC">Readings from the Four Gospels</head>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>All beginning with two line initials of gold with blue and pink red frames and
                                infills with short extensions of gold ivy leaves</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="17r">John</ab>
                        <incipit locus="17r">In principio erat verbum</incipit>
                        <ab locus="18r">Luke</ab>
                        <incipit locus="18r">In illo tempore missus est angelus <name type="person"
                            >Gabriel</name></incipit>
                        <ab locus="19r">Matthew</ab>
                        <incipit locus="19r">Cum natus esset Ihesus in <name type="place">Bethleem</name>
                            <name type="place">Iude</name></incipit>
                        <ab locus="20v">Mark</ab>
                        <incipit locus="20v">In illo tempore recumbentibus undecim discipulis apparuit illis
                            Ihesus</incipit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="5" locusStart="21v" locusEnd="21v">
                        <head type="CCC">Invocations in honour of the <name type="person">Virgin Mary</name></head>
                        <ab>These to be said daily in case of dying without confession. <handNote>Added in a different
                                hand than the main text</handNote></ab>
                        <incipit locus="21v">Pater digna Dei venie</incipit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="6" locusStart="22r" locusEnd="69v">
                        <head type="CCC">Hours of the Virgin Mary of the Use of Rome</head>

                        <ab locus="22r">
                            <decoNote>Matins. Two thirds page framed miniature of the Annunciation with a full border of
                                gold, blue and pink ivy leaves in part set on a gold ground. The miniature has a
                                background of gold rinceaux on red. Ornamental initial of three lines with blue and pink
                                ivy leaves on gold</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="32r">Lauds begins imperfectly. <decoNote>The leaf containing the miniature at the
                                beginning is lacking</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="43r">Prime begins imperfectly. <decoNote>The leaf containing the miniature at the
                                beginning is lacking</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="47r">
                            <decoNote>Terce. Two thirds page framed miniature of the Nativity with a full border of
                                gold, blue and pink ivy leaves. The miniature has a background of gold rinceaux on pale
                                green. Ornamental initial of three lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on
                                gold</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="51v">
                            <decoNote>Sext. Two thirds page framed miniature of the Adoration of the Magi. The miniature
                                has a background of gold diaper pattern on pale green. Ornamental initial of three lines
                                with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="56r">None begins imperfectly. <decoNote>The leaf containing the miniature at the
                                beginning is lacking</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="58v">Vespers begins imperfectly. <decoNote>The leaf containing the miniature at the
                                beginning is lacking</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="59r">Compline begins imperfectly. <decoNote>The leaf containing the miniature at the
                                beginning is lacking</decoNote></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="7" locusStart="70r" locusEnd="77v">
                        <head type="CCC">Psalms and antiphons of the Virgin</head>

                        <ab>To be read on various days of the week</ab>
                        <rubric locus="70r">Isti tres psalmi sequentes cum suis antiphonis dicuntur die martis et die
                            veneris</rubric>
                        <ab locus="70r">Antiphon: Specie tua et pulchritudine tua. Psalm: Eructavit cor meum</ab>
                        <ab locus="72r">Antiphon: Adiuvabit eam Deus vultu suo. Psalm: Deus noster refugium</ab>
                        <ab locus="73r">Antiphon: Sicut letancium omnium nostrum. Psalm: Fundamenta eius</ab>
                        <rubric locus="73v">Isti tres psalmi sequentes cum suis antiphonis dicuntur die mercurii et die
                            sabbati</rubric>
                        <ab locus="74r">Antiphon: Gaude Maria virgo. Psalm: Cantate Domino canticum novum</ab>
                        <ab locus="75r">Antiphon: Dignare me laudare. Psalm: Dominus regnavit</ab>
                        <ab locus="76v">Antiphon: Post partum. Psalm: Cantate Domino canticum novum</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="8" locusStart="77v" locusEnd="84r">
                        <head type="CCC">Hours of the Virgin Mary</head>
                        <ab>Variants for the liturgical year</ab>
                        <rubric locus="77v">Sabbato ante primam dominicam de adventu usque ad vigiliam nativitatis
                            Domini mutatur officium beate Marie</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="78v">Ad matutinas invitatorium hymnus et omnia alia non mutantur usque ad
                            lectiones</rubric>
                        <ab>Then follows a listing of variant lessons, responsories, versicles, antiphons, capitula and
                            collects</ab>
                        <rubric locus="81v">Et nota quod supradicte orationes antiphoni et versus ad omnes horas
                            dicuntur usque ad vigiliam nativitatis Domini</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="82v">Istud officium beate Marie virginis mutatur a vigilia nativitatis Domini
                            usque ad festum purificationis</rubric>
                        <rubric locus="83v">Notandum quod a vigilia pasche usque ad ascensionem Domini fit officium
                            beate Marie virginis sicut ante adventum</rubric>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="9" locusStart="84v" locusEnd="86r">
                        <head type="CCC">Mass of the Virgin Mary</head>
                        <rubric locus="84v">Missa de beata Maria</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="84v">Salve sancta parens</incipit>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="10" locusStart="86v" locusEnd="89r">
                        <head type="CCC">Seven Joys of the Virgin</head>
                        <ab locus="86v">Revelation of the Virgin Mary to St Thomas of Canterbury regarding the Seven
                            Joys</ab>
                        <rubric locus="87v">Incipiunt gaudia per dictum sanctum super hiis ordinata</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="87v">Gaude flore virginali</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of four lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with small
                                partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="11" locusStart="89r" locusEnd="90v">
                        <head type="CCC">Gospel Reading of the Passion and a Prayer</head>
                        <rubric locus="89r">Passio domini nostri Ihesu Christi secundum Iohannem</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="89r">In illo tempore apprehendit Pylatus Ihesum et flagellavit</incipit>
                        <rubric locus="90r">Oratio</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="90r">Deus qui manus tuas et pedes tuas</incipit>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="12" locusStart="91r" locusEnd="102v">
                        <head type="CCC">Penitential Psalms</head>
                        <ab locus="91r">
                            <decoNote>Two thirds page framed miniature, badly damaged, of David kneeling in prayer
                                before God</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="91r">Domine ne in furore tuo</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of three lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with full
                                border of the same type as for Matins of the Virgin</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="13" locusStart="103r" locusEnd="108r">
                        <head type="CCC">Litany</head>
                        <ab>Does not contain any significant local saints</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="14" locusStart="108v" locusEnd="110v">
                        <head type="CCC">Mass of the Holy Trinity</head>
                        <rubric locus="108v">Missa de sancta trinitate</rubric>
                        <incipit>Benedicta sit sancta trinitas</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of four lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with
                                partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="15" locusStart="110v" locusEnd="113r">
                        <head type="CCC">Mass of the Holy Spirit</head>
                        <rubric locus="110v">Missa de sancto spiritu</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="110v">Spiritus Domini replevit orbem terrarum</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of four lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with
                                partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="16" locusStart="113r" locusEnd="115r">
                        <head type="CCC">Mass of the Holy Cross</head>
                        <rubric locus="113r">Missa de sancta cruce</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="113r">Nos autem gloriari</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of four lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with
                                partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="17" locusStart="115r" locusEnd="117v">
                        <head type="CCC">Mass of the Dead</head>
                        <rubric locus="115r">Missa pro defunctis</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="115r">Requiem eternam</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of four lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with
                                partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="18" locusStart="117v" locusEnd="118r">
                        <head type="CCC">Salutations to be said at the elevation at mass</head>
                        <rubric locus="117v">Iste salutationes dicuntur ad elevationem corporis Christi</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="117v">Ave domine Ihesu Christe verbum Patris filius virginis</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of three lines of the same type as the Readings from the Four
                                Gospels</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="19" locusStart="118v" locusEnd="118v">
                        <head type="CCC">Prayer to be said at mass</head>
                        <rubric locus="118v">In presencia corporis Christi oratio</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="118v">Domine Ihesu Christi qui hanc sacratissimam carnem</incipit>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of three lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with
                                partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="20" locusStart="119r" locusEnd="154v">
                        <head type="CCC">Hours of the Passion</head>
                        <ab locus="119r">
                            <decoNote>Two thirds page framed miniature of the Man of Sorrows standing in the tomb,
                                flanked by standing Mary and John, and behind the Cross and the Arma Christi. There is a
                                full border of gold, blue and pink ivy leaves</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>At the beginning of each hour there is an ornamental initial of four lines with
                                blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with small partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="125v">Lauds</ab>
                        <ab locus="130r">Prime</ab>
                        <ab locus="132v">Terce</ab>
                        <ab locus="137r">Sext</ab>
                        <ab locus="141v">None</ab>
                        <ab locus="146v">Vespers</ab>
                        <ab locus="150r">Compline</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="21" locusStart="155r" locusEnd="158r">
                        <head type="CCC">Short Hours of the Cross</head>
                        <ab locus="155r">
                            <decoNote>Two thirds page framed miniature of the Crucifixion with a full border of gold,
                                blue and pink ivy leaves. Ornamental initial of three lines with blue and pink ivy
                                leaves</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><locus>158v</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="22" locusStart="159r" locusEnd="162r">
                        <head type="CCC">Short Hours of the Holy Spirit</head>
                        <ab locus="159r">
                            <decoNote>Two thirds page framed miniature of Pentecost set against a blue ground with gold
                                stars. There is a full border of gold, blue and pink ivy leaves with interlace at the
                                corners. Ornamental initial of three lines with blue and pink ivy leaves. </decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab><locus>162v</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="23" locusStart="163r" locusEnd="166v">
                        <head type="CCC">Hours of St Catherine</head>
                        <ab locus="163r">
                            <decoNote>Two thirds page framed miniature of St Catherine standing holding sword and wheel
                                set against a green ground with gold rinceaux. There is a full border with acanthus
                                leaves against gold. Ornamental initial of three lines with blue and pink ivy leaves.
                            </decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="24" locusStart="167r" locusEnd="209r">
                        <head type="CCC">Office of the Dead of the Use of Rome</head>
                        <ab locus="167r">Vespers begins imperfectly. <decoNote>The leaf containing the miniature at the
                                beginning is lacking</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="173v">
                            <decoNote>Matins. Ornamental initial of four lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold
                                with partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="196r">
                            <decoNote>Lauds. Ornamental initial of four lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with
                                partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="25" locusStart="210r" locusEnd="212v">
                        <head type="CCC">Short Office of the Dead</head>
                        <rubric locus="210r">Incipit officium mortuorum in brevi compendio</rubric>
                        <incipit locus="210r">Salutiferis meritis</incipit>
                        <ab>(hymn at Matins)</ab>
                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>Ornamental initial of four lines with blue and pink ivy leaves on gold with small
                                partial border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="26" locusStart="212v" locusEnd="212v">
                        <head type="CCC">Instructions regarding a vision of Christ</head>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>Added by a different hand than the main text</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locus="212v">Nota qua cito merita attribuuntur homini propter visionem Christi. </rubric>
                        <incipit locus="212v">Primo necessaria vite illa die sibi ministrantur</incipit>
                        <ab>Seven other instructions follow</ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="27" locusStart="213v" locusEnd="216v">
                        <head type="CCC">Missa pro morte evitanda</head>
                        <ab>
                            <handNote>Added by a different hand than the main text</handNote>
                        </ab>
                        <rubric locusEnd="213v">Missa pro morte evitanda a domino papa data anno domini millesimo
                            cccxlviii</rubric>
                        <ab>Gives an indulgence of 210 days to those hearing the mass and <q>portare in manu sua missam
                                audiens unam candelam ardentem per quinque dies continuos sequentes. Et sic mors
                                subitanea eis non nocebit. Et hoc est certum et probatum in Avinione et in aliis
                                partibus</q></ab>
                        <incipit locus="213v">Recordare domine testamenti tui</incipit>
                        <ab><locus>217r</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: Description compiled by NJM</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP</p>
                            <p>msCheck: SP</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
