<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC055">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>55</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>M. 13</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>151</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Stephen Langton, Commentaries on Selected Books of the Old Testament</head>

                <head type="James">Stephanus Langton super Vetus Testamentum</head>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">334</height>
                        <width unit="mm">222</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">13 x 8.8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 283 + 1</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 68 and 60 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xiii</origDate>,
                        <handNote>in two or three very good regular small hands</handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>1 flyleaf (mutilated), 1<num>8</num>-30<num>8</num> 31 (three)
                            32<num>8</num>-36<num>8</num></collation>.</p>

                <p><label>2 fo.:</label>
                    <secFol>Tabernaculum <name type="person">moysi</name>. funditus gratia</secFol>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">This seems to have been sent to <name type="person">Parker</name> from <name
                        type="place">Lincoln</name> by <name type="person">John Aelmer</name> when Archdeacon of Lincoln
                    (see a letter <date>3 Nov. 1567</date> in MS. <ref type="ms" target="CCC114B">114, no.
                    324</ref>).</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i + 1-283 + c-d</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="283v">

                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Stephen Langton</name>, <title>Commentaries on selected books of the Old
                                Testament</title></head>

                        <head type="James">
                            <title><name type="author">Stephanus Langton</name> super Vetus Testamentum</title>
                        </head>



                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Tabernaculum <name type="person">moysi</name> coopertum erat v.
                            cortinis</incipit>

                        <ab>
                            <name type="person">Iosue</name>
                        </ab>

                        <incipit locus="111r">Ego uisiones multiplicaui</incipit>

                        <ab>Iudicum</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="124r">Restituam iudices</incipit>

                        <ab locus="136v">
                            <name type="person">Ruth</name>
                        </ab>


                        <ab>Regum</ab>
                        <incipit locus="139r">Rectoribus populi</incipit>

                        <ab>Paralipomenon</ab>
                        <incipit locus="195v">Liber iste grece</incipit>

                        <ab>
                            <name type="person">Iob</name>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="207v">Fiant luminaria</incipit>

                        <ab>
                            <name type="person">Iudith</name>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="212r" locusNew="213r">Lucerna splendens</incipit>

                        <ab locus="221r" locusNew="221v">
                            <name type="person">Esther</name>
                        </ab>

                        <ab>
                            <name type="person">Esdras</name>
                        </ab>

                        <incipit locus="226v">Omnis scriba</incipit>

                        <ab>Maccabeorum</ab>
                        <incipit locus="238v">In <name type="person">Ioele</name> legitur</incipit>

                        <explicit locus="243v">populus turbidus scilicet luxuriosi</explicit>

                        <ab>
                            <name type="person">Isaias</name>
                        </ab>
                        <incipit locus="244r">Visio <name type="person">Ysaie</name></incipit>
                        <ab>Ending</ab>
                        <explicit locus="283v">in die quo noui</explicit>
                        <rubric locusNew="283v">Explicit summa super <name type="person">Ysaiam</name>. secundum
                            archiepiscopum Cantuariensem</rubric>


                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF, Cf 2nd</p>
                            <p>msCheck: CF 6.8.2007</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
