<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC628">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>628</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Psalter (Latin)</head>
                <p>
                    <supplied>This MS description is not part of the M. R. James catalogue.</supplied>
                </p>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">121</height>
                        <width unit="mm">90</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <extent>Single column, 20 lines per page</extent>. Writing and decoration <name
                        type="place">Paris</name>, of the mid-thirteenth century, about <origDate>1240</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">Presented to the College by the <name type="person">Rev. William Favell (Old
                        Member, matriculated 1922)</name> of Hove, Sussex, in <date>April 1976</date>, as recorded in a
                    pencil note on f. <locus>1r</locus>. A letter is also kept with the manuscript giving further
                    information. He had inherited it from the estate of his cousin, <name type="person">Richard Vernon
                        Favell</name>, sheriff of Cornwall, who died in <date>1936</date>. The Psalter appeared in the
                    Sotheby sale <date>14th July 1937</date>, lot 616, but seems to have been withdrawn and given to a
                    member of the family.</p>

                <p function="Decoration"><decoNote>Illuminated historiated and ornamental initials and line endings. The
                        style of all these can be compared with Parisian illumination of the mid thirteenth century as
                        noted by C. de Hamel in <ref type="bibl" target="de Hamel 2007"><hi rend="italic">The Parker
                                Chronicle</hi>, 3, 2007</ref>, p. 13. The figure style can be compared with the later
                            <hi rend="italic">Bibles moralisées</hi> of the 1240s</decoNote>.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. i-ii + 1-198 + iii-iv</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="176v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Psalter</title>
                        </head>


                        <ab>
                            <decoNote>The psalms of the liturgical divisions have large full-page historiated initials
                                with gold grounds. The lesser psalms have four line fully illuminated initials with
                                coils and leaves on a gold ground, and in some cases short illuminated extensions into
                                the border. There are line endings with ornamental patterns in gold, blue and
                                red</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locus="1r">Psalm 1. <decoNote><name type="person">David</name> harping; <name type="person"
                                    >David</name> beheading <name type="person">Goliath</name></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="28r">Psalm 26. <decoNote>Christ crowning <name type="person"
                            >David</name></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="45v">Psalm 38. <decoNote>Christ standing in discussion with <name type="person"
                                    >David</name></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="62r">Psalm 52. <decoNote>The fool, holding a bauble and biting on a disc, stands
                                before <name type="person">David</name></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="79r">Psalm 68. <decoNote>Christ blessing holding an orb; <name type="person"
                                    >David</name>, with arms extended, in the water. This initial is very damaged and
                                rubbed</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="98r">Psalm 80. <decoNote><name type="person">David</name> playing
                            bells</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="117r">Psalm 97. <decoNote>Two clerics in copes standing at a lectern</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="137r">Psalm 109. <decoNote>God the Father seated with the Son, with the Holy Ghost
                                between them</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="176v">Psalm 150. <decoNote>A grotesque with a helmet holding a shield with a blason,
                                yet to be identified, or a chevron gules between two roundels and a cross
                                sable</decoNote></ab>
                    </msItem>
                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="176v" locusEnd="193v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Canticles, Gloria and Credo</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab locus="176v">Confitebor. <decoNote>Six line ornamental initial with coils and leaves on a
                                gold ground. The other canticles have four line initials of similar type</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="192v">Gloria. <decoNote>Four line ornamental initial</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="193r">Credo. <decoNote>Four line ornamental initial</decoNote></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="194r" locusEnd="197v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Litany</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Saints characteristic of <name type="place">Paris</name> are <name type="person"
                                >Denis</name> among the martyrs, <name type="person">Germanus</name> and <name
                                type="person">Marcellus</name> among the confessors, and <name type="person"
                                >Genevieve</name> among the virgins. The inclusion of <name type="person">Dominic</name>
                            among the confessors suggests a date after <date>1234</date> when he was canonised</ab>
                        <ab locus="194r">Kyrie. <decoNote>Four line ornamental initial</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="197r">Litany Collects. <decoNote>Four line ornamental initials</decoNote></ab>
                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="4" locusStart="197v" locusEnd="198r">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Prayers</title>
                        </head>
                        <ab>Both have <decoNote>four line ornamental initials</decoNote></ab>
                        <incipit locus="197v">Protector vite sperantium</incipit>
                        <incipit>Pietate quaesumus Domine</incipit>
                        <ab><locus>198v</locus> blank</ab>
                    </msItem>






                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: NJM</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP</p>
                            <p>msCheck:</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
