<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC641">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>641</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno/>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>

                <head type="CCC">Antiphoner for Holy Week (fragment)</head>

                <p>
                    <supplied>This MS description is not part of the M. R. James catalogue.</supplied>
                </p>

                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">770</height>
                        <width unit="mm">560</width>
                    </measureGrp>. <origDate>Late sixteenth century</origDate>.</p>

                <p function="Provenance">Writing and decoration Spanish. Given by <name type="person">Mr Andrew
                        Johnson</name> in <date>2008</date>.</p>

                <p function="Decoration"><decoNote>Five large 3-line calligraphic ornamental initials tinted in pale
                        yellow</decoNote>.</p>

                <p>In late 16th century Spain part Antiphoners were made only containing the music for the services for
                    Holy Week. A complete example of 48ff. with calligraphic initials similar to MS 641 is in <ref
                        type="ms" target="SYD335">Sydney, University of Sydney Library MS 335</ref>, described in <ref
                        type="bibl" target="Melbourne 2008"><hi rend="italic">The Medieval Imagination</hi>, ed. B.
                        Stocks and N. J. Morgan, no. 38</ref>. The texts in this fragment are from Lauds of Maundy
                    Thursday, Matins of Good Friday and Matins of Holy Saturday, but as some leaves are missing the text
                    is not complete for this section of Holy Week. The texts are almost identical to those in the 1568
                    editio princeps of the <hi rend="italic">Breviarium Romanum</hi>. The original foliation on the
                    leaves suggests that the book in its full form had rather more leaves than the Sydney
                    Antiphoner.</p>


                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. 1-8</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin.</textLang>

                    <label>Contents</label>
                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="8v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Antiphoner for Holy Week fragment</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab locus="26r" locusNew="1r">Begins imperfectly in versicle for the final psalm of Lauds of
                            Maundy Thursday: (Homo pacis) meae in quo speraui</ab>
                        <ab> Responsory: Qui edebat panes meos ampliauit aduersum me</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1v" locus="26v">Antiphon to Benedictus: Traditor autem dedit eis signum</ab>
                        <ab locus="28r" locusNew="2r">Begins in antiphon for the last psalm of the first nocturn for
                            Matins of Good Friday: Insurrexerunt in me testes iniqui. <decoNote>Large calligraphic
                                initial</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="2v" locus="28v">Ends with responsory to the first Matins lesson: Omnes amici mei
                            derelinquerunt me</ab>
                        <ab locus="34r" locusNew="3r">Begins with responsory for the last psalm of the second nocturn of
                            Matins: Insurrexerunt in me testes iniqui</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="3v" locus="34v">Ends with part of the responsory for lesson four of Matins:
                            (Tamquam ad latronem) existis cum gladiis et fustibus</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="4r" locus="35r">Continuation of the responsory for lesson four</ab>
                        <ab locus="35v" locusNew="4v">Versicle for lesson four: Cumque iniecissent manus in Iesum.
                                <decoNote>Large calligraphic initial</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locus="44r" locusNew="5r">Opens imperfectly in the versicle for lesson seven of Good Friday
                            and continues with the responsory for lesson eight: Iesum tradidit impius summis principibus
                            sacerdotum </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="5v" locus="44v">Continuation of the responsory for lesson eight</ab>
                        <ab locus="52r" locusNew="6r">Begins with second psalm and the antiphon and verse for the third
                            psalm for the first nocturn for Matins of Holy Saturday: Ps. Domine quis habitabit. Ant.
                            Caro mea requiescet in spe. Ps. Conserua me. V. In pace in idipsum. <decoNote>Large
                                calligraphic initial for the antiphon</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="6v" locus="52v">Continues with the responsory to the third psalm: (Dormi)am et
                            requiescam. Then follows the responsory to the first lesson for Matins of Holy Saturday:
                            Sicut ouis ad occisionem ductus est </ab>
                        <ab locus="58r" locusNew="7r">Begins with antiphon for second psalm of second nocturn of Matins
                            for Holy Saturday: Credo uidere bona domini terra uiuentium, followed by antiphon to third
                            psalm: Domine abs(traxisti). Both have <decoNote>large calligraphic initials</decoNote></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="7v" locus="58v">Continues antiphon to third psalm: (Domine abs)traxisti ab inferis
                            animam meam</ab>
                        <ab locus="59r" locusNew="8r">Continues with responsory to fourth lesson for Matins of Holy
                            Saturday: Recessit pastor noster</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="8v" locus="59v">Continues with the responsory to the fourth lesson</ab>


                    </msItem>

                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>

                            <p>text: NJM</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP</p>
                            <p>msCheck:</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
