<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC081">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>81</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>A. 1</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>1</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Homer, Iliad, Odyssey. Quintus of Smyrna, Posthomerica</head>
                <head type="James">Homerus. Quintus Calaber</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Paper</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">402</height>
                        <width unit="mm">225</width>
                    </measureGrp>, <measureGrp type="James">15.9 x 8.8</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 523 + 15</extent>,
                        <layout>35 lines to a page</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv</origDate>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>a<num>8</num> (wants 1) 1<num>10</num>-52<num>10</num> 53<num>4</num> (1 canc.)
                            b<num>8</num>: p. 987 omitted in old foliation</collation>.</p>

                <p>Traces of metal bosses (formerly on the cover) are visible on the first and last pages.</p>

                <p function="Additions">On f. <locus>ir</locus> notes by <name type="person">Parker</name>:<lb/> a.
                    Dominus huius Codicis <name type="person">Theodorus</name> natus <name type="place">Tharso
                        cilicie</name> ordinatus a <name type="person">Vitaliano papa</name> etc. Ends: annos natus
                    lxvj: <name type="place">Romae</name> Monachus. <name type="person">Matthaeus Cantaur</name>. <lb/>
                    b. In another hand (<name type="person">Joscelin</name>'s?):<lb/> Hic <name type="person"
                        >Theodorus</name> vir et seculari et divina literatura grece et latine instructus รณ neque unquam
                    prorsus ex quo <name type="place">Britanniam</name> petierunt anglis feliciora fuere tempora etc.
                    (from <name type="author">Bede</name>). <lb/> c. In the same hand as the last:<lb/> Hic liber <name
                        type="person">Theodori</name> repertus in <name type="place">monasterio diui Augustini
                        Cantuariensis</name> post dissolucionem et quasi proiectus inter laceras chartas illius cenobii
                    quem cumulum chartarum scrutatus quidam pistor quondam eiusdem cenobii invenit et domum portavit
                    monachis et aliis inhabitantibus idem cenobium inhabitantibus aut fugatis aut inde recedentibus. Sed
                    tandem foeliciter in manus <name type="person">Matthei Cantuariensis Archiepiscopi</name> hic liber
                    devenit. quem ut ingentem thesaurum apud se asseruat. [Added: Et reponendum vult vel in communi
                        <name type="place">Bibliotheca Academie Cantabrigie</name>, vel in fideli custodia m<abbr
                        rend="superscript">ri</abbr> collegii (qui pro tempore fuerit) <name type="place">Corporis
                        Christi et b<abbr rend="superscript">te</abbr> Marie</name> ibidem.]<lb/> d. In a third
                    hand:<lb/> Manus commentarii greci est <name type="person">Theodori Archiep<abbr rend="superscript"
                            >i</abbr></name>. Quamdiu hic liber scriptus fuit antequam <name type="person"
                        >Theodorus</name>
                    <name type="place">romam</name> peruenerit, nescitur.<lb/> The other preliminary leaves are
                    blank.</p>

                <p function="Research" rend="afterContents">The resemblance in certain points between the hand of this
                    Homer and that of the <ref type="ms" target="LTM321">Leicester Codex</ref> was noted by <ref
                        type="bibl" target="Harris 1887">Dr J. Rendel Harris (<hi rend="italic">Leicester Codex</hi>, p.
                        8)</ref>. I am not at all sure that the two hands are not identical. This particular scribe
                    varied extraordinarily in his work. A Demosthenes at <name type="place">Leyden</name> which has a
                    notice in the <q>Leicester</q> hand that it was written in <date>1468</date>
                    <q>by me <name type="person">Emmanuel of Constantinople</name></q> and given to <name type="person"
                        >G. Neville Archbishop of York</name>, would never have been identified as the work of the
                    Leicester scribe but for this notice. The Homer is rather strikingly like the Leicester hand: but is
                    written with a finer pen. That it was written and ornamented in <name type="place">Italy</name> in
                    cent. <date>xv</date> there can be little doubt. It is quite possibly a production by <name
                        type="person">Emmanuel of Constantinople</name> in the period before he came to <name
                        type="place">England</name>. <lb/> I have elsewhere suggested (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="James 1899">Sources, p. 9</ref>) that this book really belonged to <name type="place"
                        >Christ Church, Canterbury</name>, and not <name type="place">St Augustine's</name>, and that it
                    was brought over by <name type="person">Prior Sellinge</name>. It is likewise clear that <name
                        type="person">Parker</name> was misled by the
                    &#920;&#949;&#959;&#948;&#969;&#961;&#959;&#962; on p.
                        <locus>1</locus> of this book and so assigned it to <name type="person">Archbishop
                        Theodore</name> and that this was the starting-point of his other similar and similarly absurd
                    attributions. <lb/> The following note, which I found in <name type="person">Dr Masters</name>'s
                    copy of <ref type="bibl" target="Stanley 1722">Stanley's Catalogue</ref>, preserved in the College
                    Library, suggests another origin for this Homer. I have been unable to identify the document to
                    which reference is made. It should obviously be a letter of an Italian humanist in the Harleian
                    collection. Possibly it may be well known to students, but personally I must confess to ignorance.<lb/>
                    <q>Mem.: <name type="person">Humphrey Wanley</name>, Librarian to <name type="person">the late Earl
                            of Oxford</name>, told <name type="person">Mr Fran: Stanley</name>, son of the author, a
                        little before his death, that in looking over some papers in the Earl's Library, he found a
                        Letter from a learned Italian to his Friend in <name type="place">England</name> wherein he told
                        him there was then a very stately Homer just transcribed for <name type="person">Theodorus
                            Gaza</name>, of whose Illumination he gives him a very particular description, which
                        answer'd so exactly in every part to that here set forth, that he [<name type="person"
                            >Wanley</name>] was fully perswaded it was this very Book, and y<abbr rend="superscript"
                            >t</abbr> the
                        &#920;&#949;&#959;&#948;&#969;&#961;&#959;&#962; at the bottom
                        of 1st page order'd to be placed there by <name type="person">Gaza</name> as his own name, gave
                        occasion to <name type="person">Abp. Parker</name> to imagine it might have belonged to <name
                            type="person">Theodore of Canterbury</name>, which however <name type="person">Hody</name>
                        was of opinion could not be of that age.</q><lb/>
                    <name type="person">Theodore Gaza</name> died in <date>1478</date>; the suggestion here made is
                    quite compatible with the hypothesis that <name type="person">Sellinge</name> was the means of
                    conveying the Homer to <name type="place">England</name>, and does supply a rather welcome
                    interpretation of the
                    &#920;&#949;&#959;&#948;&#969;&#961;&#959;&#962; -inscription. The
                    MS. was used by <ref type="bibl" target="Barnes 1711">Joshua Barnes (1711)</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Paley 1871">Paley (Iliad II lix)</ref>, T. W. Allen (<ref type="bibl"
                        target="Monro and Allen 1907a">Odyssey, 1907</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Monro and Allen 1908a">Iliad, 1908</ref>), etc.</p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-vii + pp. 1-986 (987-988 missing) + 989-1070 + ff. viii-xv +
                    c-d</foliation>.</p>

                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="gre" otherLangs="lat">Greek and Latin.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>


                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1" locusEnd="457">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Homer</name>, <title>Iliad, with intermittent scholia</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Title of cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate></ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="1">&#932;&#919;&#785;&#931;
                            &#927;&#787;&#924;&#769;&#919;&#929;&#927;&#933;
                            &#921;&#787;&#923;&#921;&#769;&#913;&#916;&#927;&#931;
                            &#951;&#788; &#940;&#787;&#955;&#966;&#945;
                            &#961;&#788;&#945;&#968;&#969;&#837;&#948;&#943;&#945;</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="1">Below in Roman characters: <name type="person">Matthaeus Cantuar</name></ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1">Then in a hand not that of the main scribe</ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1"
                            >&#965;&#788;&#960;&#972;&#952;&#949;&#963;&#953;&#945;
                            (-&#953;&#962;) . &#945;</ab>

                        <rubric locusNew="1">&#769;&#913;&#787;&#955;&#966;&#945;
                            &#955;&#953;&#964;&#768;&#945;&#962;
                            &#967;&#961;&#769;&#965;&#963;&#959;&#965;
                            &#955;&#959;&#953;&#956;&#768;&#959;&#957;
                            &#963;&#964;&#961;&#945;&#964;&#959;&#965;&#785;
                            &#941;&#787;&#967;&#952;&#959;&#962;
                            &#945;&#787;&#957;&#940;&#954;&#964;&#969;&#957;</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="1">
                            <decoNote>The initial M of the text is in gold, surrounded by white branch-work (Florentine)
                                on pink, blue, and greenish grounds</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1">
                            <decoNote>In the lower margin within a green wreath the name
                                    <q>&#920;&#917;&#927;|&#916;&#937;|&#929;&#927;&#931;|</q>
                                in gold capitals. Probably not by the artist of the initial</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="19">
                            <decoNote>Liber B has the beginning of an initial in ink. No more occur until &#935;,
                                    <supplied>(p. <locus>393</locus>)</supplied> &#936; <supplied>(p.
                                        <locus>408</locus>)</supplied> which have them sketched in ink. &#937; has
                                none</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="457">The Iliad ends on p. <locus>457</locus></ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="2" locusStart="457" locusEnd="714">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <name type="author">Quintus of Smyrna</name>, <title>Posthomerica</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>Title of cent. <origDate>xvi</origDate></ab>
                        <rubric locus="457"><name type="author">Quintus Calaber</name>. Paraleipomena in libros <name
                                type="author">Homeri</name> in quatuordecim libros distincta</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="457">Old title in red</ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="457"
                            >&#922;&#959;&#943;&#776;&#957;&#964;&#959;&#965;</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="457">&#917;&#973;&#785;&#952;'
                            &#965;&#788;&#960;&#768;&#959;
                            &#960;&#951;&#955;&#949;&#943;&#969;&#957;&#953;
                            &#948;&#940;&#956;&#951;
                            &#952;&#949;&#959;&#949;&#943;&#954;&#949;&#955;&#959;&#962;
                            &#941;&#788;&#954;&#964;&#969;&#961;</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="457">
                            <decoNote>Initial in outline, and some to subsequent books</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Ends p. <locus>713</locus>. p. <locus>714</locus> blank</ab>

                    </msItem>

                    <msItem n="3" locusStart="715" locusEnd="1070">
                        <head type="CCC"><name type="author">Homer</name>, <title>Odyssey, with intermittent
                                scholia</title></head>
                        <rubric locusNew="715"
                            >&#959;&#787;&#948;&#965;&#963;&#963;&#949;&#943;&#945;&#962;
                            &#940;&#787;&#955;&#966;&#945;
                            &#959;&#788;&#956;&#942;&#961;&#959;&#965;
                            &#961;&#788;&#945;&#968;&#969;&#948;&#943;&#945;&#962;</rubric>
                        <rubric locusNew="715">&#902;&#787;&#955;&#966;&#945;
                            &#952;&#949;&#969;&#785;&#957;
                            &#945;&#787;&#947;&#972;&#961;&#951;
                            &#959;&#787;&#948;&#965;&#963;&#951;&#943;&#948;&#951;
                            &#960;&#945;&#955;&#955;&#940;&#948;&#953;
                            &#952;&#940;&#961;&#963;&#959;&#962;</rubric>
                        <ab locusNew="715">
                            <decoNote>Initial to text in outline</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>Ends p. <locus>1068</locus> (really 1070)</ab>
                        <explicit locusNew="1068">&#951;&#787;&#948;&#768;&#949;
                            &#954;&#945;&#768;&#953;
                            &#945;&#965;&#787;&#948;&#942;&#957;</explicit>
                        <ab>Below, <handNote>in a later hand</handNote></ab>
                        <rubric locusNew="1068">&#959;&#788;&#956;&#942;&#961;&#959;&#965;
                            &#949;&#787;&#960;&#953;&#964;&#940;&#966;&#953;&#959;&#957;</rubric>
                        <incipit locusNew="1068">&#949;&#787;&#957;&#952;&#940;&#948;&#949;
                            &#964;&#768;&#951;&#957;
                            &#953;&#788;&#961;&#768;&#945;&#957;
                            &#954;&#949;&#966;&#940;&#955;&#951;&#957; &#954;.
                            &#964;. &#955;.</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="1068">
                            <decoNote>Under this in a green wreath a bust of <name type="author">Homer</name>(?), a
                                turbaned bearded man in red buttoned coat with green collar facing L.: ground blue with
                                red border</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab locusNew="1068">Below this the Epitaph again in another hand in red: below it <decoNote>a
                                medallion like the first with similar ground: <name type="person">Athene</name>
                                full-face with helmet, spear, and shield. These are by the artist of the
                                &#920;&#949;&#959;&#948;&#969;&#785;&#961;&#959;&#962;
                                on p. <locus>1</locus></decoNote></ab>
                        <ab>pp. <locus>1069</locus>-<locus>1070</locus> (1071-1072) blank; quire b <supplied>(ff.
                                    <locus>viiir</locus>-<locus>xvv</locus>)</supplied> blank</ab>
                        <ab>The Scholia are sparse in the Iliad and only more copious in the Odyssey. They are very
                            likely not by the scribe of the text: but I am not sure of this</ab>

                    </msItem>
                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, BA, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: PE 23/1/2009</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
