<TEI>




    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Christi College Cambridge / PARKER-ON-THE-WEB</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Electronic edition - 560catalogueAfter</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>M.R. James, <title>Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Corpus Christi
                        College</title>, Cambridge 1912</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The James Catalogue was digitized then marked up following the TEI P5 Guidelines. The customized
                    model was provided by Giuliano Di Bacco, stored in an ODD file (parkerweb.xml): the latter was
                    written by GDB using ROMA vers. 2.x, with manual adaptations. The ODD file is used as a source to
                    compile the actual schema used to validate the xml: it is advisable to compile it in RelaxNG sintax
                    (parkerweb.rnc) through ROMA.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text>
        <front/>

        <body>

            <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier xml:id="CCC091">
                    <country>UK</country>
                    <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                    <institution>Corpus Christi College</institution>
                    <repository>Parker Library</repository>
                    <idno>91</idno>
                    <altIdentifier type="Stanley">
                        <idno>B. 3</idno>
                        <!--James corrects in corrigenda-->
                    </altIdentifier>
                    <altIdentifier type="TJames">
                        <idno>15</idno>
                    </altIdentifier>
                </msIdentifier>
                <head type="CCC">Histoire des Seigneurs de Gavres</head>
                <head type="James">Histoire des Seigneurs de Gaures</head>
                <p function="Codicology"><material>Vellum</material>, <measureGrp type="CCC">
                        <height unit="mm">360</height>
                        <width unit="mm">253</width>
                    </measureGrp><measureGrp type="James">14.1 x 10.2</measureGrp>, <extent>ff. 200 + 3</extent>,
                        <layout>double columns of 30 lines</layout>. Cent. <origDate>xv, second half</origDate>,
                        <handNote>in clear black hand approaching <q>lettre b‚tarde</q></handNote>.</p>

                <p><label>Collation:</label>
                    <collation>2 flyleaves, 1<num>8</num>-25<num>8</num>, 1 flyleaf</collation>.</p>


                <p>At various places portions have been cut off the lower margins of leaves: and in one place a triangle
                    is cut out. Probably there were signatures or shields of owners in these places.</p>
                <p function="Research">The text was printed in 1845 at Brussels by <ref type="bibl"
                        target="Gachet and Kreins 1845">Van Dale (<hi rend="italic">Histoire des Seigneurs de Gavres,
                            Roman du xv<abbr rend="superscript">e</abbr> siËcle</hi>)</ref> with introduction and
                    illustrations, and a glossary by <name type="person">Emile Gachet</name></p>

                <p type="CCC">
                    <foliation>ff. a-b + i-ii + 1-200 + iii + c-e</foliation>.</p>


                <msContents>
                    <textLang mainLang="frm">Middle French.</textLang>
                    <label>Contents</label>



                    <msItem n="1" locusStart="1r" locusEnd="200v">
                        <head type="CCC">
                            <title>Histoire des Seigneurs de Gavres</title>
                        </head>
                        <head type="James">
                            <title>Histoire des Seigneurs de Gaures</title>
                        </head>

                        <ab>The text begins</ab>
                        <incipit locusNew="1r">Les tres haulx et courageux faiz de noz anchiens predecesseurs escripz
                            pour exemple et memoire ala loenge diceulx</incipit>
                        <ab locusNew="1r">
                            <decoNote>This first page has a picture and full border of conventional and natural flowers
                                and foliage on plain ground. In the lower margin a shield surmounted with crest and
                                surrounded by the garter with motto. Shield and crest have been carefully erased and so
                                has a banner in the R. margin<lb/> The picture, rather rubbed, but in fine Flemish
                                style, represents the interior of a room with wooden roof. On L. stone fire-place with
                                fire. On R. bed in alcove: green tiled floor. Before the fire lies a nude infant. The
                                mother, in tall headdress, sits wringing her hands on seat (along the wall). Two maids
                                kneel on L. in consternation. In C. the Seigneur de Gaures in gown with stick,
                                gesticulating. Two men and two women on R. in consternation<lb/> Along the back wall is
                                a settle ending on R. in a kind of desk. The wall is hung with an arras, deep red
                                ground, gold birds in pairs, two rows of trees, on each a scroll bearing one word of the
                                garter motto. The incident shown is the Seigneur de Gaures throwing his infant son into
                                the fire (see f. <locus>8r</locus>)</decoNote>
                        </ab>
                        <ab>The text ends</ab>
                        <explicit locus="200v">Ceste histoire a este translatee de grec en latin et de latin en flamenc.
                            Et depuis a este transmuee en langaige franchoiz le derrenier jour de mars lan <date>mil
                                    iii<abbr rend="superscript">c</abbr> lvi</date>. Cy fine lystoire des seigneurs de
                            gaures</explicit>
                        <ab locusNew="200v">After this an erasure, possibly only a scribbled repetition of the colophon,
                            such as occurs on the flyleaf: <q>Sy fine lyst</q></ab>

                    </msItem>



                </msContents>
                <additional>
                    <adminInfo>
                        <recordHist>
                            <p>text: copied from James.txt SP</p>
                            <p>markup: SP</p>
                            <p>markupCheck: checked by SP, CF</p>
                            <p>msCheck: NJC 9.10.07</p>
                            <p>remarks:</p>
                        </recordHist>
                    </adminInfo>
                </additional>
            </msDesc>


        </body>

        <back/>
    </text>
</TEI>
